<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The charge of Socinianism against Dr. Tillotson considered in examination of some sermons he has lately published on purpose to clear himself from that imputation, by way of a dialogue betwixt F. a friend of Dr. T's and C. a Catholick Christian : to which is added some reflections upon the second of Dr. Burnet's four discourses, concerning the divinity and death of Christ, printed 1694 : to which is likewise annexed, A supplement upon occasion of A history of religion, lately published, supposed to be wrote by Sir R-- H--d [Robert Howard] : wherein likewise Charles Blount's Great Diana is considered, and both compar'd with Dr. Tillotson's sermons / by a true son of the Church.</title>
            <author>Leslie, Charles, 1650-1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 252 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47737</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1124</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19586</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12043385</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12043385</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53033</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47737)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53033)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 570:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The charge of Socinianism against Dr. Tillotson considered in examination of some sermons he has lately published on purpose to clear himself from that imputation, by way of a dialogue betwixt F. a friend of Dr. T's and C. a Catholick Christian : to which is added some reflections upon the second of Dr. Burnet's four discourses, concerning the divinity and death of Christ, printed 1694 : to which is likewise annexed, A supplement upon occasion of A history of religion, lately published, supposed to be wrote by Sir R-- H--d [Robert Howard] : wherein likewise Charles Blount's Great Diana is considered, and both compar'd with Dr. Tillotson's sermons / by a true son of the Church.</title>
                  <author>Leslie, Charles, 1650-1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 33 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edenburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: prelim p. [2].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tillotson, John, 1630-1694.</term>
               <term>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715. --  Four discourses delivered to the clergy of the diocess of Sarum.</term>
               <term>Howard, Robert, --  Sir, 1626-1698. --  History of religion.</term>
               <term>Blount, Charles, 1654-1693. --  Great is Diana of the Ephesians.</term>
               <term>Socinianism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53033:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi rend="blackletterType">Charge of Socinianiſm</hi> AGAINST Dr. TILLOTSON CONSIDERED.</p>
            <p>In EXAMINATION of ſome SERMONS He has lately Publiſhed on purpoſe to clear Himſelf from that IMPUTATION.</p>
            <p>By way of a DIALOGUE betwixt <hi>F.</hi> a Friend of Dr. <hi>T's</hi> and <hi>C.</hi> a <hi>Catholick Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is Added Some REFLECTIONS upon the Second of Dr. BUR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NET's Four Diſcourſes, concerning the Divinity and Death of <hi>CHRIST.</hi> Printed 1694.</p>
            <p>To which is likewiſe Annexed, A SUPPLEMENT upon Occaſion of a Hiſtory of Religion, lately Publiſhed, Suppoſed to be Wrote by Sir <hi>R.— H—d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein likewiſe <hi>CHARLES BLO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NT's</hi> Great Diana is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered; And both Compar'd with Dr. <hi>TILLOTSON's</hi> Sermons.</p>
            <p>By a True Son of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDENB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH:</hi> Printed MDCXCV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:53033:2"/>
            <p>☜ <hi>N. B.</hi> When the Reader meets with this Mark * <hi>P.</hi> 6. <hi>C.</hi> 2. <hi>line</hi> 51. He muſt caſt his Eye to the next <hi>Col.</hi> to this Mark ** and read that Four Line-Paragraph (which was left out <hi>by Miſtake</hi> in Compoſing, and <hi>thro' haste</hi> miſplaced in Correcting) at the firſt Mark.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. Col. 2 li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 50. read Subtily, p. 4. C. 2. l. 3. r. <hi>which</hi> by <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> l. 46. after of dele r. p. 6. C. 2. l. 51. r. permiſſion, <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 57. d. a p. 7. C. 1. l. 55. r. are <hi>not</hi> now, p. 7. C. 2. l. 53. for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. C. 1. l. 29. r. Imperfection, l. 37. r. Till-n, Col. 2. l. 37. r. Exult, l. 39. for That, r. Thus, p. 10. Col. 1. l. 3. r. Mountain <hi>that,</hi> l. 22. r. there is <hi>no</hi> more, C. 2. l. 49. r. lends, p. 11. C. 1. l. 19. r. <hi>his,</hi> C. 2. l. penul for generally r. Eternally, p. 12. C. 2. l. 2. r. run, l. 13. r. without either, l. 21. r. ſo obſtinately, p. 13. C. 2. l. 34. r. <hi>as</hi> to, p. 14. c. 1. l. 21. for to r. do, p. 15. col. 1. l. 9. r. Chriſt's, col. 2. l. 10. r. Juſtifies, l. 27. for to r. the, p. 16, col. 2. l. 25. r. over, p. 18. col. 1. l. 49. for Naturer. Honour, p. 19. col. r. l. 21. f. He r. there, p. 21. c. 1. l. 3. f. or r. as, c. 2. l. 42. f. by r. upon, p. 22. c. 2. l. Antep. r Conceive, p. 23. l. ult. f. put? p. 26. c. 2. l. 42. f. it r. is, p. 27. c. 1. l. 24 for fight r. light.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:53033:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THat which I have to Advertiſe the Reader of by way of <hi>Preface,</hi> is That the following Animadverſions upon Dr. <hi>Tillotſon's</hi> Sermons, were wrote before the Death of that Unhappy Man: and ſhould not now have been Publiſhed, were it not that his much Miſtaken and Pernicious Principles have ſurviv'd him, and are Recommended by the Authority of his Name.</p>
            <p>Yet the Reſpect I bear to the <hi>Dead</hi> might have reſtrain'd ſome Sharpneſs (if any ſuch be found) in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Sheets, had they been wrote ſince his Lamentable <hi>Exit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am likewiſe to tell the Reader that the <hi>Socinians</hi> have Publiſh'd an Anſwer to what they think, or pretend makes againſt them, in the <hi>Four</hi> Sermons, hereafter Examin'd, of Dr. <hi>Tillotſons;</hi> and the <hi>2d</hi> of Dr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi>'s Diſcourſes, which I have taken into Conſideration. Their Treatiſe bears this Title, <hi>Conſiderations on the Explication of the Doctrine of the Trinity, occaſioned by Four Sermons Preach'd by his Grace the Lord Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Canterbury— <hi>A Diſcourſe by the Lord Biſhop of</hi> Salisbury, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Printed <hi>1694.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this there is a Reply, by Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> for himſelf, in a Letter to Dr. <hi>Williams,</hi> and by the ſaid Dr. <hi>Williams</hi> in Vindication of Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> Publiſhed ſince his Death, both Printed together, <hi>1695.</hi> and carries this Title. <hi>A Vindication of the Sermons of his Grace</hi> John <hi>Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Divinity and Incarnation of our B. Saviour— From the Exceptions of a late Book, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled,</hi> Conſiderations on the Explications of the Doctrine of the Trinity. <hi>To which is annexed, a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the Lord Biſhop of</hi> Sarum, <hi>to the Author of the ſaid Vindication on the ſame Subject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Licenſe</hi> for Printing this Book, is Dated at <hi>Lambeth, 17. Nov. 1694.</hi> the very day before Dr. <hi>Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotſon</hi> was ſtruck with that Fatal <hi>Apoplexy,</hi> which carry'd him out of this World the <hi>fourth</hi> day after; and made Room for another <hi>Comprehenſive Latitudinarian</hi> who <hi>look'd</hi> over <hi>Lincoln,</hi> to Succeed him. But the Books above mentioned came to my view after ſome of the following Sheets were ſent to the Preſs, otherwiſe I had made more particular Obſervations upon them; for the preſent I had only opportunity to make ſome ſhort mention of them in ſome of the remaining Sheets.</p>
            <p>And here I muſt take notice, that whereas the aboveſaid <hi>Conſiderations</hi> p. <hi>63.64.</hi> Objected againſt the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count which Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> had given of the Grounds of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of our Religion were only a Gratification to the <hi>Humour</hi> of Mankind, who were fond of <hi>Myſteries:</hi> That the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> was to Comply with their Notion of a <hi>Senſible Deity:</hi> And his <hi>Paſſion,</hi> with their Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of <hi>Human Sacrifices:</hi> His <hi>Exaltation,</hi> with their Cuſtom of <hi>Deifying</hi> Men: His <hi>Interceſſion:</hi> with their Common Apprehenſion of <hi>Mediators,</hi> between the Gods and them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are a main Subject of the enſuing Diſcourſe. I ſay; theſe being thus Objected, together with ſome other Exceptions, againſt Dr. <hi>Tillot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>'s Doctrine, in the fore-quoted pages, his <hi>Vindicator</hi> Replys to ſome of the others, but leaves theſe above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned totally untouch'd. <hi>Vindication,</hi> page <hi>61.62.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether they were <hi>Material</hi> to be Anſwer'd I leave to what follows: and whether they are <hi>Anſwerable,</hi> upon any <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Principles, I refer to the Judgment of the Reader, and this ſort of <hi>No-Vindication</hi> of them.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſs Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> would read this <hi>Vindication</hi> of himſelf before he <hi>Licens'd</hi> it to be Printed.</p>
            <p>And, if he could have given any Anſwer to theſe moſt Monſtrous Objections made againſt him, be would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty have done it: Wherefore we muſt conclude him <hi>Self-Condemn'd:</hi> and yet he has not (at leaſt <hi>Publickly,</hi> as he ought) Recanted theſe Blaſphemous Errors: He ought to have <hi>Recanted</hi> and <hi>Abhorred</hi> them, both in <hi>Print,</hi> and in <hi>Pulpit,</hi> as he had Publiſhed them. But he has receiv'd his Sentence.—</p>
            <p>Here let me Reply, tho' not for Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> yet againſt theſe <hi>Socinians:</hi> They Argue that there was no <hi>Neceſſity</hi> for the <hi>Incarnation</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> and for this they Quote Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi>'s own words, <hi>Conſiderations p. 63. That the Goſpel, and the Pardon of Sin; might have been offer'd to Mankind by a</hi> Prophet <hi>in the Name of God.</hi> And becauſe he ſays it, they charge it upon the <hi>Church. Our Oppoſers</hi> (ſay they) <hi>Grant it, his GRACE Grants it.</hi> See the miſchief of this Man's <hi>Prevarications,</hi> and his Advancement to the <hi>Throne </hi>of<hi> Canterbury!</hi> But to the Argument, Firſt, the <hi>Vindicator, p. 61.</hi> (and conſequently Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> himſelf) does ſhamefully give up this Cauſe: and Plead for the <hi>No-need</hi> or <hi>Neceſſity</hi> either of <hi>CHRIST's Incarnation,</hi> or of his <hi>Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet it was the Height of Impudence in the <hi>Socinians</hi> to Object the <hi>No-neceſſity</hi> of the <hi>Incarnation,</hi> againſt the <hi>Divinity</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> when that ſame Argument Militates as ſtrongly againſt themſelves, as to the <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> For which, upon their Principles of <hi>No-Satisfaction</hi> being due to the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of <hi>God</hi> for <hi>Sin,</hi> there can no tolerable Account be given; for a <hi>Prophet</hi> might have <hi>Taught,</hi> and <hi>Preach'd,</hi> and been a good <hi>Example,</hi> and <hi>Interceſſor</hi> too; and Perform'd every one of the Conditions, and Ends, which they Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign for <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s coming into the World, and for the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of his <hi>Death</hi> upon the <hi>Croſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:53033:3"/>
            <p>This of Denying the <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> is the Heart of <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> and the <hi>Mill-ſtone</hi> which will ſink it into the Sea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for without this, there was no <hi>Need</hi> or <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> either for the <hi>Incarnation</hi> or <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> But the Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction</hi> being Eſtabliſhed, infers the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of the <hi>Divinity</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (without which an <hi>Adequate</hi> Satisfaction could not be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade) and the <hi>Divinity</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> does <hi>neceſſarily</hi> infes the <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality</hi> of <hi>Perſons</hi> in the <hi>Deity;</hi> which is the whole of the Difficulty alledg'd againſt the <hi>Trinity.</hi> So cloſely are theſe <hi>Divine</hi> Principles of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion link'd and joyn a together. The denial of any one of them breaks the whole Chain.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> in the aboveſaid <hi>Vindication</hi> of himſelf, <hi>p. 101.</hi> Inſtead of Recanting his former Error, proceeds expreſly to Diſpute yet farther againſt the <hi>Satisfaction;</hi> and ſays, that, <hi>It is no part of the Doctrine of our Church— our Articles</hi> (ſay he) <hi>are the only Standard to Judge of our Doctrine, as far as they go, but they have Determin'd nothing in this matter, but reſt in the General Notions of Expiation</hi> (which the Dr, Expounds not to mean SATISFACTION) <hi>and of Reconciling us to God.</hi> Thus this Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Doctor.</p>
            <p>But my laſt Topick, with which I cloſe my Obſervations upon his <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> has ſufficiently diſprov'd this; and ſhewn the Doctrine of the <hi>Satisfaction</hi> to be expreſly taught in the <hi>Homilies,</hi> and that they account not him who denies is to be a <hi>Chriſtian-Man,</hi> but an <hi>Adverſary to Chriſt and his Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſhall we ſuppoſe it poſſible that this Dr. never Read the <hi>Homilies,</hi> which he has Subſcrib'd? No, nor they very <hi>Articles</hi> which he Quotes? Or that the <hi>Homilies</hi> are not contain'd, and all expreſly nam'd in the ſaid <hi>Articles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or otherwiſe ſhall we think that he meant hereby to Impoſe upon unwary Readers, and thus to <hi>Belye</hi> and <hi>Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſifie</hi> the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> on purpoſe to conceal the more effectually his own <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from it?</p>
            <p>But tho' every Body is not well acquainted with the <hi>Homilies</hi> (through an inexcuſable neglect of reading them Publickly, as it is enjoyn'd) yet none can come to the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> without taking notice that in the very <hi>Prayer of Confecration, Chriſt</hi> is ſaid to have made full <hi>Satisfaction</hi> for the Sins of the whole World. The Dr. has forgot this too.—</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I will ſhew you the Advantage which the <hi>Socinians</hi> make of theſe <hi>ſeeming</hi> Defences of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Religion, which of all other Methods, do moſt effectually undermine and betray it. See how they Glory and Exult in this Performance of Dr. <hi>Burnets. Furthermore</hi> (ſay they) Conſiderations, <hi>p. 15. The</hi> Socinians, <hi>and all other ſmall and envied Parties of</hi> Chriſtians, <hi>are in his Debt, for Owning and Eſpouſing Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly, Divers ſuch Truths, as others perhaps ſee as well as he, but have not Sincerity, nor Generoſity enough, to avow them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here they deteſtably inſinuate that all are <hi>Hypocrites</hi> who, <hi>in good Earneſt,</hi> do oppoſe <hi>Socinianiſm:</hi> And gather from the Account which Dr. <hi>T.</hi> and Dr. <hi>B.</hi> give of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Faith, that others are of the ſame Opinion; while they ſee them not <hi>Oppos'd</hi> nor <hi>Cenſur'd</hi> for theſe their Blaſphemous Hereſie; but on the contrary, they are <hi>Vindicated, Excus'd,</hi> and their vile <hi>Sophiſtry Palliated</hi> and <hi>cover'd</hi> by the <hi>Divines</hi> in Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion. What the Conſequences of this may be is dreadful to apprehend!</p>
            <p>This Dr. <hi>B.</hi> has ſo Explain'd the Doctrine of the Church, as that the <hi>Socinians</hi> may cloſe with it. <hi>It is</hi> (ſay they) Conſiderat. <hi>p 31.32. the very Doctrine of the</hi> Socinians, <hi>which they have own'd from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in all their Books.</hi> And ſpeaking of the <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> they truly ſay, That <hi>his Lordſhip himſelf, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly diſlikes it, and Argues againſt it.</hi> Which they there prove from <hi>p. 135.</hi> of his Diſcourſe. <hi>In brief</hi> (ſay they) <hi>were the Queſtions about the</hi> Trinity <hi>and the</hi> Divinity of our Saviour <hi>adjuſted; there would be no longer Diſpute about the</hi> Satisfaction; <hi>as his Lordſhip has ſtated it. Nor, to ſay true, have we Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy with him, about the two former Queſtions; for he contents himſelf to ſay the</hi> Three, <hi>and when he ſays moſt, the</hi> Holy Three, <hi>diſclaiming</hi> (expreſly) <hi>the word</hi> Perſons; <hi>in the Senſe,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly taken— To ſay all at once</hi> (concludes that <hi>Socinian</hi> Author) <hi>I have not made this Reply, to oppoſe it to his Lordſhip's Diſcourſe, but to teſtifie our Reſpects to his Lordſhip; and that we ſubmit to his Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Lordſhip (as this <hi>Socinian</hi> ſtiles him) in his <hi>Vindication, p. 99.</hi> calls this an <hi>Imputation</hi> upon him; but yet does not clear himſelf from it; for which I refer to what followes, where it is Examined.</p>
            <p>I conclude this Preface with giving the Reader a needful <hi>Caution</hi> againſt theſe Horrible <hi>Socinians,</hi> that they are going about to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndermine the Authority of the <hi>Holy Scriptures;</hi> becauſe they cannot Reconcile them to their <hi>Damnable Hereſie.</hi> They have now <hi>(Conſiderat. p. 50.51.)</hi> Publickly aſſauted all the whole Works of St. <hi>John,</hi> his <hi>Goſpel, Epiſtles,</hi> and <hi>Revelation.</hi> This was the ſhortest way of Anſwering them; and, at the ſame time, of confeſſing that they were, no otherwiſe Anſwerable by them. I ſay nothing here to their Arguments, becauſe they are ſufficiently Confuted in Dr. <hi>William</hi>'s <hi>Vindication.</hi> Only let me Obſerve, that if their pretences againſt theſe parts of Scripture which make moſt againſt them, and which therefore they Reject, do hold, the whole <hi>Canon</hi> of the <hi>Scripture</hi> is rendered precarious, andour <hi>FAITH Uncertain.</hi> Which must be the conſequence, if theſe moſt Execrable of <hi>Hereticks</hi> ſhould prevail. Which God of his Mercy prevent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53033:3"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Charge of Socinianiſm</hi> AGAINST Dr. TILLOTSON, CONSIDERED, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>SInce our laſt Diſcourſe upon the Famous Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of <hi>Hell,</hi> preach'd before the Queen, 7th of <hi>March,</hi> 1690. upon <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.46. and Printed <hi>by Their Majeſties Special Command,</hi> The Author has this Year 93. publiſh'd 4 Sermons, two of them preach'd <hi>An.</hi> 79. and two <hi>An.</hi> 80. upon <hi>John</hi> 1.14. This he has done to clear himſelf from <hi>Socinianiſm.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>He ſays in his Advertiſement to the Reader, That he has Revis'd and <hi>Enlarg'd</hi> them; ſo that we cannot tell what Part of them was preach'd at the time Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, or what added ſince, to clear his Reputation now that he is got into an higher Station, ſo as to make ſuch a Vindication neceſſary. For it is to be preſum'd that he did not think it worth his while before, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he would not ſo long have lain under the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of having been neither <hi>Chriſtened,</hi> nor a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> in his Principles: Both which have not only been loudly Clamour'd, but objected in Print againſt him many years ago. Wherein only he truly Exercis'd <hi>Non-Reſiſtance;</hi> For he opened not his Mouth.</p>
               <p>But it is never too late to mend. And if he be not now; Pray God he may be a <hi>good Chriſtian</hi> before he dies. For I muſt confeſs, I do not think it ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently Evinc'd in theſe Sermons. In the Reading of which the Character which the <hi>Hiſtory of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> gives (tho' falſly) of <hi>Grotius</hi> came into my Mind; wherein he endeavours to make <hi>Grotius</hi> a tho'ro'-pac'd <hi>Socinian,</hi> but yet to have cover'd his Meaning ſo craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, particularly in his Comments upon this Firſt <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of St. <hi>John's</hi> Goſpel, whence this Author has taken his Text, as not to be known to be a <hi>Socinian,</hi> unleſs to a very diſcerning Reader.</p>
               <p>And I muſt obſerve, that this Author in the foreſaid 4 Sermons, tho' he ſeems to ſpeak home ſometimes; yet has taken ſpecial Care to avoid the only <hi>Shibboleth</hi> which the <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> could find out to diſcover the ſeveral Sorts of <hi>Arian</hi> and other <hi>Hereticks,</hi> who deny'd the <hi>Divinity of Chriſt.</hi> which was <hi>Conſubſtantiality.</hi> That God the <hi>Son</hi> was of the ſame <hi>Subſtance</hi> with his <hi>Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Several of them (for there were ſeveral Subdiviſions of them, and of different Opinions) would allow <hi>Christ</hi> to be of the <hi>like</hi> Subſtance with the <hi>Father<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> That is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is of the <hi>ſame</hi> Subſtance. And except the ſingle <hi>Iota,</hi> which is betwixt theſe two Words, they could ſwallow the whole <hi>Nicene Creed,</hi> by vertue of Diſtinctions, in which they were great Maſters; And it is very ſtrange that this Author ſhould forget this only Matterial Word, which is the heart of the whole Cauſe, and expreſly aſſerted in the <hi>Nicene Creed;</hi> eſpecially conſidering that Sermon 3. <hi>p.</hi> 140, 141. he quotes the words in that Creed immediately following theſe <hi>[Being of one Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance with the Father]</hi> which words he does not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and which being own'd by him would have been a more clear and full Vindication of his Orthodoxy in this point, than all theſe 4 Sermons; And ſince it was impoſſible he ſhould forget it, he repeating the ſame Sentence in the Creed wherein it is contain'd; we muſt conclude; that be left it out on purpoſe, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That he does not really believe it; tho' he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours with all his Art, to caſt a Miſt before the Reader's Eyes, in other Expreſſions, which to ſome might ſeem Tantamount, as <hi>Arius</hi> and his Followers did. Even our Modern <hi>Biddle</hi> in his <hi>Confeſſion of Faith touching the Holy Trinity,</hi> Printed in the Year 1648. and now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed in the Year 1691. <hi>Artic.</hi> 3. Confeſſes <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be <hi>Our Lord,</hi> yea <hi>Our God,</hi> and yet in the ſame <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> aſſerts, <hi>That he hath no other than a Human Nature.</hi> But he was a <hi>Senſeleſs Socinian,</hi> tho' now much Admir'd amongſt them in <hi>London,</hi> and his Books carefully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed. He Refin'd from the <hi>Socinians,</hi> and added to it the Old <hi>Anthropomorphite</hi> Hereſie, That <hi>God</hi> was a <hi>Body,</hi> of the <hi>Shape</hi> of a Man, <hi>Fingers, Eyes, Toes.</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53033:4"/>As the <hi>Socinians</hi> refin'd from the <hi>Arians,</hi> and gave the <hi>Son of God</hi> no Exiſtence before his Birth of the <hi>Virgin,</hi> and have exceedingly Entangled their Cauſe by it. The <hi>Arians</hi> were more <hi>Subtle</hi> and <hi>Learned</hi> than any of their Follo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers, who have grafted upon their Stock. It was hard to diſcover the depth of <hi>Arianiſm,</hi> They defended themſelves with Nice diſtinctions.</p>
               <p>They would call the <hi>Son, God,</hi> yea, <hi>Truly and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally God.</hi> As this Author confeſſes. 2 <hi>Serm. p.</hi> 123. And what plainer or fuller words could readily be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, wherein to confeſs the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>real</hi> Divinity of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>Angels</hi> and to <hi>Men;</hi> who are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Gods,</hi> but it is only in a <hi>Figurative</hi> and <hi>Borrowed</hi> Senſe? They are not <hi>truly</hi> and <hi>really God,</hi> as the <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> ſaid of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The Author in the ſame Sentence explains himſelf, and thoſe whom he calls his <hi>Adverſaries</hi> (whether <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> or <hi>Socinians</hi>) who ſay that Chriſt is <hi>truly and really God,</hi> by adding theſe words, <hi>by Office, and by Divine Appointment and Conſtitution.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>That is a very vain Diſtinction: For a God by <hi>Office,</hi> or any other way, ſo he be <hi>truly and really</hi> God, is as great as a God by <hi>Nature,</hi> becauſe nothing can be greater than <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, a God <hi>by Office,</hi> if he be <hi>truly</hi> and <hi>really</hi> God, muſt likewiſe be a God <hi>by Nature,</hi> for he could not, otherwiſe, be <hi>Truly</hi> and <hi>Really God:</hi> as he could not be <hi>truly</hi> and <hi>really Man,</hi> who were not a Man <hi>by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> or who did not <hi>truly</hi> and <hi>really</hi> partake of the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of <hi>Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, as a Conſequence of all this, the Author tells, <hi>ibid.</hi> That our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> did allow <hi>the very ſame Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Worſhip</hi> to be given to the <hi>Truly</hi> and <hi>Really</hi> God, tho' <hi>by Office,</hi> which we give to him who is God <hi>by Nature</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as theſe Adverſaries could not be found out by the word <hi>GOD,</hi> which they freely allow'd to Chriſt; no, not by the words <hi>Truly and Really God:</hi> So neither could the word <hi>Eternity</hi> fully diſcover them, <hi>viz.</hi> To aſſert <hi>Christ</hi> to have been from <hi>Eternity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We know ſeveral <hi>Adverſaries</hi> to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> who have aſſerted the <hi>World</hi> to have been from <hi>Eternity,</hi> and yet would not allow it to be <hi>God.</hi> It is part of the <hi>Muggletonian</hi> Creed, at this day, that <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>Water</hi> were from <hi>Eternity,</hi> and yet not <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Book call'd <hi>The Oracles of Reaſon</hi> (by that Execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Char. Blount,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gildon,</hi> and others of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bb</hi>'s wretched Diſciples) does argue expreſly for the <hi>Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> and of <hi>Mankind</hi> too, in the ſame State they are in now. This is printed for our Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the Year 1693. as one Branch of our Glorious <hi>Reformation,</hi> and Chriſtian <hi>Toleration.</hi> And if theſe <hi>Wits</hi> allow <hi>Eternity</hi> to meer Men, much leſs would theſe <hi>Socinians</hi> ſtick to call Chriſt <hi>Eternal,</hi> who own him to be <hi>truly and really God.</hi> For whatever is ſo, muſt be <hi>Eternal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore, as I ſaid before there was no <hi>Shibboleth,</hi> which all theſe our Adverſaries did refuſe, but that of <hi>Conſubſtantiality,</hi> and which <hi>this Author</hi> does refuſe; and while he does ſo, he muſt ſtill be reckoned among theſe <hi>Adverſaries</hi> to the <hi>Chriſtian Cathelick Faith.</hi> Tho' Tho among what particular Species or Denomination of them I will not determine; or whether he may not have refin'd to a degree and Peculiarity by himſelf, for he delights in <hi>Bold Stroaks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Biddle</hi> above told, is own'd by the <hi>Socinians,</hi> as a good and laudable Brother, tho he ſet up the Old and Exploded Hereſie of the <hi>Athropomorphites:</hi> And the <hi>Arians</hi> are admitted into their Communion, and, as ſuch, quoted and pleaded by them againſt the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, tho they held the <hi>Prae-Exiſtence</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> before his <hi>Incarnation,</hi> which the <hi>Socinians</hi> have rejected. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom ſome, even at this day, hold the <hi>Perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> which others of them do abſolutely deny. Some of them make theſe to be <hi>Creatures,</hi> others to be <hi>Really</hi> and <hi>Truly</hi> God, and not any thing different from <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay the Old <hi>Nazarens, Ebionites, &amp;c.</hi> are in the <hi>Brief Hiſt. of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitar.</hi> Quoted as the Primitive Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the <hi>Socinian</hi> Opinion, ſome of whom rejected the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> others all of it, but ſome Particular Books, which pleas'd their Fancies; Others own'd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scriptures never Received by the Church; and publickly allow'd and practiſed <hi>Altering</hi> the Holy Scriptures, which they called <hi>Mending</hi> of them; and ſome of them ſaid that Chriſt was begot by <hi>Joſeph</hi> like other Men, Nay by their <hi>Latudinarian</hi> Principles, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> himſelf, and his <hi>Alcoran</hi> muſt be admitted into their Confederacy, who ſpeak more honourably of <hi>Chriſt</hi> than the <hi>Socinians</hi> themſelves, and deſerve the Name of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> even in their own Senſe; as much as they can pretend to.</p>
               <p>In the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> if you will but own <hi>Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly</hi> the Authority of their Church, to the Height they Aſſert it; you ſhall be own'd a good <hi>Catholick,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed by an <hi>Implicit</hi> Faith in all other Articles of the Creed, tho you be never ſo ignorant, or hold particular Opinions different from the Church.</p>
               <p>So, with the <hi>Socinians,</hi> if you will but reject the <hi>Conſulſtantiality</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> you ſhall have Liberty to make him a <hi>God,</hi> or a <hi>Creature,</hi> or what you will; You may talk of his <hi>Eternity,</hi> his <hi>True</hi> and <hi>Real God-Head;</hi> His being <hi>God of God, Light of Light,</hi> &amp;c. They have diſtinctions for all theſe. And tho they love not; nor like the Expreſſions, yet they can make a hard ſhift with them: They can puzzle People's Underſtandings, tho by very fooliſh and contradictory Arguments, How God by his Infinit Power, might have beſtowed <hi>True</hi> and <hi>Real Divinity</hi> upon another, and that even from <hi>Eternity;</hi> for what he can do to day, he might have done Yeſterday, and ſo backwards for ever.</p>
               <p>But then, this would have been only a voluntary Act of God; and what he did, he might not have done, if he had ſo pleaſed; and conſequently, that this <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted</hi> God, tho from <hi>Eternity,</hi> was ſtill a <hi>Precarious,</hi> tho a <hi>True</hi> and <hi>Real</hi> God; and yet not properly to be called a <hi>Creature,</hi> that is, like <hi>Finite</hi> Things, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd in time.</p>
               <p>But on the other hand, to make another Perſon <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantial,</hi> that is, of the ſame <hi>Nature</hi> with God the Father, this infers the neceſſity of a Plurality of <hi>Perſons</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:53033:4"/>in the very <hi>Nature</hi> of the Godhead, and ſo to be of the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>Faculties</hi> are of the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of the <hi>Soul,</hi> ſo that it could not be a <hi>Soul</hi> without the <hi>Faculties,</hi> nor a God, without the <hi>Perſons,</hi> and tho one depends upon another, and ſprings from another, yet they are all equally <hi>Neceſsary, Co-Eternal,</hi> and <hi>Co-Equal,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>all</hi> of the ſame <hi>Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This grows too hard for a Diſtinction, and our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians,</hi> as they call themſelves, will compound for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, ſo you keep off from this <hi>Conſubſtantiality.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore the <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> could find no other <hi>Criterion</hi> to diſcover the ſubtle Hereſie of theſe pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> of ſeveral Degrees and Claſſes, who, tho differing never ſo widely among themſelves, yet all join, and reckon themſelves as Brethren; againſt the moſt Glorious, and moſt ample Revelations of the ever <hi>Bleſſed Trinity,</hi> Recorded in the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> And whoever refuſe this <hi>Test,</hi> cannot be accounted ſound in the <hi>Chriſtian Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But where there is unwillingneſs it will one way or another ſhew it ſelf; and it is eaſie to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt thoſe Expreſſions which proceed from a hearty Conviction, and thoſe which are taken up out of force and neceſſity, to clear our ſelves from an Imputation which lies upon Us.</p>
               <p>This your <hi>Dr.</hi> diſcovers pretty plainly, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Caſe; for being neceſſitated, in a Vindication of himſelf, as to the <hi>Doctrin of the Trinity,</hi> to uſe the Word <hi>Perſons,</hi> he does it, as brought to it againſt his Will, very grudgingly and ſlightly, he does paſs it over, and cannot conceal his Inclination rather to the Diſtinction uſed by the <hi>Anti-Trinitarian Hereticks,</hi> to elude thoſe Texts which ſpeak of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> which is, that there are three <hi>Differences</hi> in the <hi>Deity,</hi> which are expreſs'd in Scripture by the three Denominations of <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt:</hi> and which they allow are ſpoken of after the manner of <hi>Perſons;</hi> as <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is ſaid to build hee Houſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But they will not allow them to be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and properly <hi>Perſons,</hi> or different <hi>Subſistences,</hi> but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly three ſeveral acceptations of the ſame <hi>Perſon,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the different Manner of his Revealing himſelf upon ſeveral occaſions: And thus they may make as many Perſons, <hi>in this Senſe of theirs,</hi> as their Fancy pleaſes to ſuggeſt. And <hi>in this Senſe,</hi> and <hi>no other,</hi> the <hi>Dr.</hi> is pleaſed to let the word <hi>Perſons</hi> paſs, ſince we muſt have it; tho at the ſame time he gives it ſuch a ſtab, as ſhews that he is by no means reconciled to it. But take his own words, which he gives as his determination of the whole Matter, and the utmoſt to which he will be brought. <hi>Serm.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 120.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Here then I fix my foot: That there are three <hi>Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences</hi> in the <hi>Deity,</hi> which the Scripture ſpeaks of by the Names of <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> and every where ſpeaks of them as we uſe to do of three diſtinct Perſons: And therefore I ſee no reaſon why in this Argument we ſhould <hi>Nicely abſtain</hi> from uſing the word <hi>Perſon;</hi> tho I remember that St: <hi>Jerom</hi> does <hi>ſomewhere</hi> deſire to be excuſed from it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Dr.</hi> and according to this, where he has occaſion to name the Three <hi>Perſons</hi> of God, he adds to explain himſelf, his own word <hi>Differences,</hi> which he likes better, thus, <hi>p.</hi> 122. The <hi>Three</hi> Differences <hi>or Perſons in the Divine Nature, expreſſed in Scripture by the Names of</hi> Father, Son, <hi>and</hi> Holy Ghoſt, &amp;c. and ſo in other places.</p>
               <p>And here, He has <hi>fixt his foot;</hi> you ſhall have no more of him, if you be not pleaſed with this, you muſt let it alone, and trouble him no more about <hi>Socinianiſm, Arianiſm,</hi> or any of theſe like Matters.</p>
               <p>But this <hi>ſomewhere</hi> of St <hi>Jerome</hi>'s was a ſtrange Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation for ſo Grave a <hi>Dr.</hi> to bring into the Pulpit upon ſo ſerious a Subject, if he thought it ſo. For, I fancy he ſpoke this with a Smile, ſaying to himſelf— I'll make this poor Auditory believe that I have a place of St. <hi>Jerome</hi> under my Thumb, to overthrow all this buſineſs of different <hi>Perſons</hi> in God; which word ſince they force me to uſe, I'll be revenged on it. But I will not name the Place in St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> for there are Rogues will be Examining of it, and put me to a great deal of trouble; It will do well enough for a Squib among the Crowd.</p>
               <p>But theſe poor hopes are vaniſhed; for this <hi>Dr.</hi> has already been taken to task, and ſtands Corrected for this, by a much more Learned Perſon than himſelf. The Author of the <hi>Animadverſions upon Dr.</hi> Sherlock's Book Entituled, <hi>A Vindication of the Holy and ever Bleſſed Trinity,</hi> &amp;c. Printed 1693. There <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 265. This Place of St. <hi>Jerome</hi> is quoted. And it is ſhewn, that St. <hi>Jerom</hi> did not Scruple to uſe the word <hi>[Perſon] or deſired to be excuſed</hi> (as our Author comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally words it, by way of wit) but on the contrary, that he did uſe the word <hi>[Perſon]</hi> and in the ſame Senſe, in this Queſtion, which is put upon it by us at this day, as one of the diſtinct <hi>Subſiſtences</hi> of the Divine <hi>Nature,</hi> or <hi>Subſtance,</hi> whom he did own to be <hi>Tres Perſonas Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſistentes.</hi> But that what ſcruple he had was concerning the Greek word <hi>Hypoſtaſis,</hi> which yet he did not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely reject, nor refuſe to make uſe of it, but thought it needed ſome <hi>Explanation,</hi> or rather <hi>Caution,</hi> in the uſe of it.</p>
               <p>But this Author (whatever <hi>ſcruple</hi> he may have, which he ſignifies in Hints very plain) will not too <hi>nicely</hi> abſtain from the Word <hi>Perſon</hi> (or any other word) ſince he can make it ſignify what he pleaſes, only a <hi>Difference,</hi> or a <hi>Somewhat,</hi> or a <hi>No-what,</hi> by a <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Reſervation,</hi> tho he knows thoſe he diſputes with, and thoſe he ſpeaks to, take it in another ſenſe.</p>
               <p>The great Art of the <hi>Socinians</hi> is in altering the meaning of <hi>Words,</hi> ſo that no words almoſt can bind them. And this <hi>Dr.</hi> does very ſubtlely recommend their Interpretations of Scripture, by bringing them ſometimes to prove the Divinity of Chriſt, that ſo he may take you off the much more ſtrong and full proof which lies in the true and plain meaning of the words. For example. <hi>Serm.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. He brings <hi>Phil.</hi> 2; 6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as a Proof of the Divinity of Chriſt; <hi>who being in the Form of God, thought it no Robbery to be equal with God.</hi> But inſtead of <hi>he thought is not Robbery,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The <hi>Dr.</hi> would have the Senſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53033:5"/>to be, He <hi>did not arrogate to himſelf to be equal with God,</hi> tho' it is quite contrary to the words, which are liter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally tranſlated. <hi>He thought it not Robbery to be equal: (i. e.)</hi> He did make himſelf equal. <hi>He did not arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate to himſelf to be Equal</hi> (i. e.) He did not make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Equal. Senſes which are in terms oppoſite. <hi>He did,</hi> ſays the Text; <hi>He did not,</hi> ſays <hi>Dr T.</hi> This is the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent anſwer which the Brief <hi>History of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> gives to this Text, and which the <hi>Dr.</hi> here recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends. And he ſays, that that Phraſe is uſed ſo by <hi>Plutarch.</hi> But he names not the words, nor Quotes the Place, which he would have done, if he had thought it for his purpoſe. For he cannot deny that the words are rightly Tranſlated, and they cannot bear two op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite Senſes,</p>
               <p>But now to bring himſelf off from ſeeming to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the <hi>Socinians</hi> in this <hi>Intepretation:</hi> He pretends to prove the <hi>Divinity</hi> of Chriſt from it, thus; <hi>Chriſt did not arrogate to himſelf to be Equal with God;</hi> (i. e.) <hi>He made no Ostentation of his Divinity,</hi> and this the <hi>Dr.</hi> ſays, <hi>He takes to be the true Meaning of that Phraſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it means much more eaſily, That Chriſt had no <hi>Divinity</hi> to make Oſtentation of, that he did not ſo much as pretend to it, or <hi>arrogate</hi> it to himſelf.</p>
               <p>By this <hi>Socinian</hi> Interpretation of the <hi>Dr</hi>'s, Here is firſt a very weak Argument brought for the Divinity of Chriſt, which is the moſt effectual Method to deſtroy a Cauſe. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Here is a very ſtrong Argument for his <hi>Divinity</hi> diverted and eluded. For let the Text lie in the plain and Grammatical Interpretation of the words, and they are not to be anſwer'd by the <hi>Socinians:</hi> For if it was <hi>no Robbery</hi> in Chriſt to be <hi>Equal</hi> with God, it follows unavoidably, That he was True and Real God by <hi>Nature.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Let us come now to the other great point of <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſm,</hi> the Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction.</hi> They deny that the <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> was a <hi>Satisfaction</hi> paid to the <hi>Justice</hi> of God for our Sins, for the <hi>Dr.</hi> has Clear'd himſelf in this Point likewiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>He hath Clear'd himſelf indeed! not only to have been, but ſtill to continue a rank <hi>Socinian</hi> in this Point, even where he endeavours moſt to make a ſhew, as if he were come off it. He mumbles it like Thiſtles. For tho the Great point be the Satisfying God's <hi>Juſtice.</hi> Yet he is ſo very Careful to avoid coming upon that Queſtion, That he names it but once in all thoſe 4 Sermons; And that after ſuch a manner as plainly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers, that he is ſtill of the Opinion he told us in his Sermon of <hi>Hell,</hi> of which he ſays there is no <hi>Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> Becauſe there was no need of any <hi>Satisfaction</hi> to Gods <hi>Juſtice</hi> at all. And that God's <hi>Juſtice</hi> is to be Conſider'd no otherwiſe than as a <hi>Politi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to ſecure his Government, and therefore does not infer any pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of Sinners, But that his threats may be only <hi>in Terrorem,</hi> or ſo far to be inflicted as may ſecure his Government from the <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation</hi> of <hi>wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men.</hi> As if God were afraid of being <hi>Depoſed</hi> by them. A ſtrange Notion of the <hi>Justice</hi> of God! But this New Doctrin of making Hell <hi>precarious</hi> does total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly overthrow the Doctrine of the <hi>Satisfaction of Chriſt,</hi> and plucks it up Root and Branch: For, if there be no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of a Hell, there can be no <hi>Neceſſity of Satisfaction</hi> for Sins; which this means are remitted without it. But your Author thinks to put us off with a Complement in this matter. <hi>Serm.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 211. He ſays, that this way of Remitting Sins by the Death of Chriſt, was a way, indeed, <hi>very Honourable to the Juſtice of God,</hi> and the <hi>Authority of his Laws.</hi> And this is every word he ſays, as to the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of God in all theſe 4 <hi>Sermons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He comes off like a Courtier, I confeſs, and will let it be <hi>very Honourable</hi> for God; (that is Civil!) if we would let alone any Arguments as to what the <hi>Nature of Juſtice</hi> requires, which makes it more than <hi>Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,</hi> even <hi>Neceſſary,</hi> That a <hi>full</hi> and <hi>adequate Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> be made to <hi>Juſtice;</hi> otherwiſe, <hi>Juſtice</hi> can be no more <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> is no more <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, it will appear that, if there was no neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſatisfying <hi>Justice,</hi> it was not only, not very <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable</hi> in God, but even not reconcileable to any No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we can have of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> to take the life of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Perſon without any neceſſity in the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>You are a ſort of People hard to be pleas'd, Therefore this good <hi>Dr.</hi> in Compliance to your Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and becauſe indeed he has treated very ſlightly of <hi>the Satisfaction</hi> in theſe 4 <hi>Sermons;</hi> he has ſince preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Sermon before the <hi>Queen</hi> at <hi>White-hall</hi> 9th of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril.</hi> 93. upon <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.29. on purpoſe, <hi>Cencerning the Sacrifice and Satisfaction of Chriſt;</hi> and it is publiſh'd <hi>by Her Majeſties Special Command,</hi> and was put into the <hi>Gazette.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>All this <hi>Honour</hi> had his Sermon of <hi>Hell</hi> above told; of which, we have formerly diſcours'd at large; and this ſhall have as fair dealing from me, to be <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially</hi> and <hi>honeſtly</hi> examin'd, without any <hi>Flattery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt therefore, I will ſhew the moſt <hi>Barbarous, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd,</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemous</hi> Notion he has of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> in General.</p>
               <p>And then, as to the Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> that he is Expreſly <hi>Socinian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Notion of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> in theſe firſt <hi>Four,</hi> and this ſingle Sermon expreſs'd, did I confeſs amaze me, beyond any thing ever I read, except of the ſame Author: And if no name had been affixed, I ſhould have gueſs'd no other than <hi>Muggleton,</hi> it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly his Size of apprehending the Scriptures, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the ofr a <hi>Lucian,</hi> or a <hi>Julian</hi> to mock, and ſlander Chriſtianity out of the World.</p>
               <p>But that you may know whether there be Reaſon for all this. <hi>First,</hi> I will ſhew you, That he makes the <hi>Foundation of Christion Religion</hi> to be ſome <hi>fooliſh</hi> and <hi>wicked Fancies,</hi> which got into People's heads, he knows not, and ſays, no matter, How, and inſtead of Reforming theſe, and commanding us to <hi>Renounce</hi> and <hi>Abbor</hi> them; which one would have expected; and which <hi>Chriſt</hi> did to all other Wickedneſs; The <hi>Dr</hi>'s Scheme is, That God in <hi>Compliance</hi> with theſe, and to indulge Men in theſe ſame <hi>Wild</hi> and <hi>wicked Phancies,</hi> did ſend <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Took his Life, and Inſtituted the whole Aeconomy of the <hi>Christian Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This appears ſo <hi>Dreadful,</hi> and <hi>astoniſhingly Impious,</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:53033:5"/>that you muſt have patience to take it in pieces, and ſee by what degrees the <hi>Dr.</hi> arrived at this New pitch of <hi>Super-Hobbiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Thoſe Revelations which all the Chriſtian World has hitherto believ'd God gave at the Beginning to <hi>Adam,</hi> and after to the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> and <hi>Prophets</hi> more expreſly of the <hi>Promiſed Seed;</hi> and thoſe <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>Institutions</hi> which God from the Beginning did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point as Shadows and ſenſible Repreſentations of the Expiatory Death of <hi>Christ</hi> upon the Croſs, ſuch as <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices,</hi> which for this End were commanded to <hi>Adam,</hi> practiſed by <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> his Children, and deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by uninterrupted Tradition, even to his <hi>Heathen</hi> Poſterity; tho they knew not their Original, more than they did their own, or that of the World's; All theſe the <hi>Dr.</hi> thinks to be only <hi>Fancies</hi> and <hi>Imaginations.</hi> which came (he knows not how) into Men's Brains.</p>
               <p>And that to comply with theſe was the End of <hi>Chriſt's Incarnation, Death,</hi> &amp;c. Whereas, on the Contrary, it has been the Received Opinion, that inſtead of God's imitating or following the Inventions of Men, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirations of the Devil, That the Inſtitutions of <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>Idolatrous</hi> Religions, were but <hi>Corruptions</hi> and <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitations</hi> of the <hi>True Religion</hi> Inſtituted by God; and that in this the <hi>Devil</hi> was but an <hi>Ape</hi> of <hi>God Almighty,</hi> whence aroſe the ſaying, That <hi>where God has a Church, the Devil has a Chappel,</hi> (i. e.) That the <hi>Devil</hi> does <hi>Ape</hi> and <hi>Imitate</hi> the Inſtitutions which God has appointed in his Holy Religion. Hence the <hi>Devil</hi> had his <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices,</hi> his <hi>Feasts,</hi> his <hi>Prieſts,</hi> &amp;c. Not that theſe Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions were of the <hi>Devil</hi>'s Invention; He did only i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate God's Inſtitution in all theſe things, as the Feaſt to his <hi>Calves,</hi> was in imitation of God's Feaſt in <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> (1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.32. But this <hi>Author</hi> turns the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and would have the <hi>Devil,</hi> or <hi>wicked Men,</hi> by his Inſpiration to have firſt invented theſe <hi>Religious Rites;</hi> And then that God did follow their Steps, and framed his Religion after the <hi>Pattern</hi> of theirs, or in Condeſcenſion to their <hi>wicked Phancies</hi> or <hi>Imaginations,</hi> as this Author words it. By which means, inſtead of the common Opinion, That God was the Author of all Religious Worſhip, and the Devil the Corrupter of it; This Author would perſuade us. That the Devil was the Author and firſt Inventer of it, and that God came in but at the ſecond hand in imitation of the Devil, and to graft upon his Stock; So that, if the Devil and Fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh men had let alone their Inventions, as of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> and <hi>Vicaricus Suffering,</hi> of a <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator,</hi> and of <hi>Mysteries;</hi> we had had no need of a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator,</hi> of a <hi>Christ</hi> to have been a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for us, or of any <hi>Mystery,</hi> or <hi>Religion</hi> at all: For all theſe the <hi>Dr.</hi> tells us, we owe to theſe <hi>Phantaſtical,</hi> and even <hi>Diabolical Prejudices,</hi> and <hi>Groſs Conceptions</hi> of Mankind. And this was not out of Forgetfulneſs of what is ſaid above of their Inſtitution by God. No, He mentions it ſeveral times, but ſo ſlightly and with that Contempt, as if no ſtreſs at all were to be laid upon it.</p>
               <p>Page 5. of the ſingle Sermon. He ſays. <hi>This Notion of the Expiation of Sin by Sacrifice, whether it had its firſt Riſe from Divine Revelation, and was afterwards propagated from Age to Age by Traditiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> I ſay, from whenceſoever this Notion come.—And</hi> P. 11. <hi>He (God) ſeems either to have poſſeſſed Mankind with this Principle, or to have permitted them to be ſo perſuaded, that Sin was not to be Expiated but by Blood; that is, either by the Death of the Sinner. or of the Sacrifice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Serm. 4. upon <hi>John</hi> 1.14. p. 185. <hi>It is not eaſie to give a certain account of the true Original of ſome Notions and Prejudiees concerning God and Religion, which have ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally obtained in the World.</hi> Several of theſe Notions he mentions in the ſame place, as Expiation of Sin by Sacrifices; The <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of <hi>Mediators</hi> to God, Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to <hi>Myſteries, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And theſe <hi>Notions</hi> (however come by) He does not make to be grounded upon any <hi>Truth,</hi> any <hi>ſolid Reaſon,</hi> but to be meerly <hi>Phantastical,</hi> to be <hi>common Prejudices</hi> of Mankind; Nay to be not only <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>fool<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh,</hi> but <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>abominable.</hi> Hear his own words, Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Sermon</hi> 4th. <hi>p.</hi> 179. He calls theſe, <hi>The Weakneſſes and Common Prejudices of Mankind—very weak and groſs apprehenſions.</hi> p. 189. <hi>very edd and Phantaſtical—very Lewd and Impious — very Inhuman and Cruel, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way unworthy of the Deity.</hi> p. 206. <hi>Inveterate pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices.</hi> Single Serm. p. 7. <hi>Barbarous and Inhuman.</hi> p. 29. <hi>Enormities and Cruelties. — <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nable and Bloody way of Worſhip.</hi> p. 35. <hi>Inhumne and Ineffectual way of Sacrificing one another, whereby inſtead of Expiating their Guilt, they did inflame it; and by thinking to make Atonement for their Sins, they did in truth add to the number and heinouſneſs of them.</hi> Serm. 4. p. 186. He calls this Worſhip <hi>the Worſhip of Devils, and not of God.</hi> And Serm. 3. p. 155. He confeſſes, The <hi>Devil</hi> and the <hi>World</hi> to be the <hi>two Great Enemies of our Salvation,</hi> which Chriſt came to <hi>Conquer and Triumph over.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, who would imagine, that the End of Chriſt's Coming ſhould be to gratify theſe Enemies of his whom he came to Deſtroy; To comply and condeſcend to theſe; and to indulge theſe Wild and Diabolical No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Mankind!</p>
               <p>But this ſubtle Doctor has found it out. Serm. 4. p. 179. <hi>The Wiſdom of God thought fit thus to order things, in Great Condeſcenſion to the Weakneſs, and common Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices of Mankind.</hi>—P. 184. <hi>For the Religion and Laws which God gave them were far from being the Beſt, and moſt Perfect in themſelves. In which Senſe ſome under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that paſſage in</hi> Ezek, <hi>where it is ſaid, That God gave them</hi> Statutes which were not good p. 187 <hi>God ſeems likewiſe to have very much ſuited the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſation of the</hi> Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, <hi>and the Method of our Salvation by the</hi> Incarnation <hi>and</hi> Sufferings <hi>of his</hi> Son, <hi>to the</hi> common Prejudices <hi>of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, especially of the</hi> Heathen <hi>World — by</hi> Gratifying <hi>them in ſome meaſure, and in a gracious</hi> Compliance <hi>with our</hi> Weakneſs, <hi>by</hi> bending <hi>and</hi> accommodating <hi>the way and method of our Salvation to our weak Capacity, and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Conceptions of things.</hi> p. 186. <hi>God ſeems to have had great Conſideration of ſome very</hi> weak <hi>and</hi> groſs <hi>Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of Mankind concerning</hi> Religion. <hi>p.</hi> 206. <hi>And he hath in great Goodneſs and Condeſcenſion to our</hi> Invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Prejudices <hi>concerning theſe things.—app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ared in the end of the World to take away Sin by the Sacrifice of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> Single Serm. p. 5. <hi>Anether reaſon of this Liſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſeems to have been a Gracious Condeſcenſion and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53033:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Almighty God, with a certain</hi> apprehenſion <hi>and</hi> perſuaſion <hi>which had very early and univerſally obtained among Mankind, concerning the Expiation of Sin, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſing the effendid Deity by Sacrifices.</hi> p. 6. <hi>God was pleaſed to</hi> comply <hi>ſo far with theſe</hi> Notions <hi>and</hi> Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions <hi>of theirs, as to make his own Son both a</hi> Prieſt <hi>and a Sacrifice.</hi> Serm. 4 p. 192. <hi>And indeed a great part of the</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Religion and Worſhip was a plain Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion to the General Apprehenſions of Men concerning this way of Appeaſing the Deity by</hi> Sacrifice. p. 193. <hi>And with this General Notion of Mankind,</hi> whatever the ground or foundation of it might be, <hi>God was pleaſed ſo far to comply, as once for all to have a General Atonement made for the Sins of all Mankind, by the Sacrifice of his</hi> Only Son. p. 195. <hi>The World was mightily bent upon Addreſſing their Requests and Supplications, not to the Deity imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, becauſe their</hi> Superſtition <hi>thought that too great a Preſumption, but by ſome</hi> Mediators <hi>between the Gods and them, who might with advantage, in this humble Manner, preſent their Requeſts ſo as to find Acceptance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Notion of theirs he calls <hi>Superſtition,</hi> to think that there needed any <hi>Mediator</hi> betwixt God and Man. They indeed miſtook the <hi>Mediator,</hi> and therein was their <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Idelatry:</hi> But the Notion was Right and Neceſſary; and deduc'd to them from <hi>Adam.</hi> (to whom it was Reveal'd) tho' they knew it not. But if their Notions of a <hi>Mediator</hi> and <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for Sin was <hi>wicked, Abominable, &amp;c.</hi> as this Author ſays, was it not <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>abominable</hi> to comply with ſuch a <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>abominable</hi> Notion? Nay, were not the very thing of a <hi>Mediator,</hi> or <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for Sin, a <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>abominable</hi> thing? How otherwiſe was the <hi>bare Notion</hi> of it ſo <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>abominable?</hi> I ſee not how he can eſcape upon this Scheme, either to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the <hi>Heathen</hi> Sacrifices, or Condemn that of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Either to ſay that there was no need of a <hi>Mediator,</hi> or to Confeſs that their Notion of it, which he calls <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition</hi> was juſt and good. But if it <hi>was Superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> is it not <hi>Superſtition</hi> ſtill? If a Mediator in Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral be <hi>Superſtition,</hi> is not this or that Mediator the ſame <hi>Superſtition?</hi> Is not appointing any <hi>Mediator</hi> a <hi>Superſtition?</hi> And muſt it not be <hi>Superſtition</hi> in any to think it neceſſary? As the <hi>Heathens</hi> did.</p>
               <p>And yet to Comply with this <hi>Superſtition</hi> of theirs, the Dr. maker the end of Chriſt's coming to be our <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator,</hi> p. 196. <hi>In a Gracious Complyance with this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Apprehenſion—God was pleas'd to constitute and appoint One in our Nature to be a perpetual</hi> Advocate <hi>and</hi> Interceſſor <hi>in Heaven for us.</hi> Again we know the <hi>Socintans</hi> are much offended, that there ſhould be any <hi>Myſtery</hi> in our Religion. And for this the Dr. gives the ſame Reaſon, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That it was only to comply with an odd Notion the World had got to have <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſteries</hi> in their Religion, Serm. 4 p. 188. <hi>The World was much given to admire</hi> Myſteries <hi>in Religion,</hi> p. 190. <hi>Since the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rld had ſuch an Admiration for Myſteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi>—God gave them a <hi>Myſtery inde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d.</hi> The Myſtery of Godlineſs, <hi>God manifest in the Fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Tim. 3.16.</p>
               <p>Otherwiſe we needed not have had any <hi>Mystery</hi> in our Religion, norany <hi>Mediator,</hi> nor any <hi>Expiatory Sacrifice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bleſſed God! This Man makes no more of the <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries</hi> of our <hi>Religion</hi> than to ſatisfie Men's fooliſh Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſities. <hi>He that will have a May-Pole. ſhall have a May-Pole.</hi> Since you will have <hi>Myſteries,</hi> here's one for you —<hi>God manifeſt in the Fleſh</hi>—This is to ſatisfie their fooliſh longing after <hi>Myſteries,</hi> and to give you your fill of <hi>Myſteries</hi>—Was there ever ſo impious a <hi>Burleſque</hi> upon <hi>God</hi> and upon the <hi>Religion</hi> of <hi>Chriſt!</hi> As if he was <hi>Incarnate</hi> for no other end but to make People <hi>wonder</hi> and <hi>Gaze,</hi> and becauſe of the <hi>Myſtery</hi> forſooth! And that he was <hi>Crucify'd,</hi> only to outdo <hi>Raw-Head and Bloody Bones,</hi> the Inhumanity of the <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>athen Sacrifices!</hi> That is, to Cure the <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> and <hi>Folly</hi> of Men, by Overacting them in both! For what are <hi>Myſteries,</hi> without any further. Conſideration than as <hi>Myſteries,</hi> that is, <hi>Wonders</hi> and <hi>ſtrange things,</hi> but the height of <hi>Folly,</hi> perfect <hi>Rary-Shows?</hi> And what an account is it of <hi>Religion</hi> to ſay, <hi>That God was manifeſt in the Fleſh</hi> to ſatisfie ſuch Childiſh Curioſity, and becauſe <hi>the World was given to admire Myſteries!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They were given likewiſe to Sacrifice, not only <hi>Beaſts,</hi> but to Sacrifice one <hi>Man</hi> for another, an <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> Perſon for the <hi>Guilty.</hi> But was not this a very <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>inhuman</hi> Cuſtom? Yes. The <hi>Dr.</hi> confeſſes it to have been even <hi>Diabolical.</hi> And yet to comply with this <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>Diabolical</hi> Cuſtom, and in <hi>Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of it, he would have to be the reaſon why God Sacrific'd <hi>Chriſt,</hi> an <hi>Innocent</hi> Perſon for the <hi>Guilty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It makes all my Fleſh creep, and my Soul to tremble within me, but to repeat ſuch Blaſphemous <hi>Schemes of Divinity,</hi> which makes <hi>God</hi> to be the <hi>Devil's Ape,</hi> and to have follow'd his wicked Inventions in the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But on the Contrary <hi>Christ</hi> himſelf aſſures us, That he came to deſtroy the works of the Devil, not to <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound</hi> with the Devil, much leſs to <hi>Gratify him,</hi> in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing his wicked Suggeſtions which he had put into the Minds of Men; and to carry them to greater heights of wickedneſs than ever the <hi>Devil</hi> himſelf could have done, or ſo much as have imagin'd, <hi>viz.</hi> Inſtead of the Sacrifices of <hi>Beaſts,</hi> or of <hi>Men</hi> (which the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> practis'd) to ſacrifice the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n of God</hi> himſelf.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Dr.</hi> puts this Objection, <hi>p.</hi> 28. of ſingle Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. And gives two Anſwers to it: Firſt, That <hi>God did not command his</hi> Son <hi>to be Sacrific'd, but his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> permitted <hi>the wickedneſs and violence of Men to put him to Death.</hi>—And <hi>that this is no mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e a Reſlection upon the Providence of God than any</hi> Enormities <hi>and</hi> Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties <hi>which by his</hi> Permiſſion <hi>are daily committed in the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. But if there was no more than God's bare Permiſſions in the Sacrifice of Chriſt, as in all other wicked Action, How was his <hi>Death</hi> a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> more than the Death of any other Man? You ſay, that God's Govenant with him for Remiſſion of the Sins of the Penitent was grounded upon his <hi>Death,</hi> and made with him before his <hi>Death;</hi> was not this a more than a bare Permiſſion of his Death? How did God make him both a <hi>Priest</hi> and a <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> by his Death, as the <hi>Dr.</hi> ſays he did, if he concurr'd no otherwiſe to his Death than by ſuch
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53033:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>a bare Permiſſion as he ſuffers an honeſt Man to be murder'd by Thieves? But</p>
               <p n="2">2. This cannot be called bare Permiſſion. It was a Method of God's own finding out, and Ordering; which exceeded the Inventions of Men and Angels. It is ſaid, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.28. That God did <hi>determine it before to be done.</hi> But tho God <hi>permits</hi> evil, You will not ſay, That he does <hi>determine,</hi> or <hi>Order</hi> it to be done; And God <hi>ſent</hi> his <hi>Son</hi> for this very end and purpoſe. This was more than <hi>only permitting it.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Dr.</hi> Explains it, <hi>p.</hi> 32. by this Compariſon, <hi>Suppoſe,</hi> ſays he, <hi>A Malefactor condemn'd, and the King's Sin to ſave him</hi>—is <hi>contented to ſubmit to great Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, and Sufferings.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>But ſuppoſe the King's Son prays and begs of his Father with Tears, That he would excuſe him from ſuch Suffering, as Chriſt pray'd to his Father. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.39. <hi>That that Cup might paſs from him?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>You would ſeem to imply as if Chriſt's Suffering were not voluntary.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>No, not all. But that it was not only his Father's bare Permiſſion, but his expreſs will and pleaſure that his Son ſhould Suffer. Therefore Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Not mine, but thy will be done,</hi> And therefore becauſe it was his Father's <hi>Will</hi> that he ſhould Suffer, he did voluntarily and reſignedly ſubmit to it. But I hope you will make this ſomething more than his Father's bare <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting</hi> of it.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 53.10. <hi>That it pleas'd the Lord to bruiſe him</hi> (Chriſt) <hi>and to put him to Grief, and he made</hi> Chriſt's <hi>Soul an Offering for Sin.</hi> This exceeds a bare Permſſion, ſuch as that by which God <hi>permits</hi> the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ormities</hi> and <hi>Cruelties</hi> committed in the World, which is all this Author would have meant by it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>His ſecond Anſwer is, <hi>p.</hi> 29. That <hi>by this means God did at once put an End to that unreaſonable and bloody way of Worſhip, which has been ſo long practiſed in the World—And it hath ever ſince obtained this effect, of making all other Sacrifices to ceaſe, in all Parts of the World where</hi> Chriſtianity <hi>hath prevailed.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>This is only repeating the Objection, inſtead of anſwering it, (as if the Sacrifice of Chriſt (upon this Author's Scheme) were not more <hi>unreaſonable</hi> and <hi>bloody</hi> than any other Sacrifices uſed before.</p>
               <p>And this being all the <hi>Dr.</hi> ſays to the Objection, we muſt ſuppoſe that he ſtill thinks it to be ſo <hi>unreaſonable.</hi> And it is the more, and not the leſs ſo, that it was as he ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 22. to comply with an <hi>unreaſonable</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation Men had of being ſav'd by the <hi>Vicari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> Suffering of ſome other in their ſtead; and that it was to gratifie this <hi>unreaſonable</hi> Expectation of theirs, That <hi>Chriſt</hi> did ſuffer; for, if it was <hi>unreaſonable</hi> for them to expect it, it was <hi>unreaſonable</hi> in Chriſt to ſuffer it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Repeat the <hi>Dr</hi>'s own Words—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>We are now upon vindicating Gods Providence for the <hi>permiſſion</hi> of <hi>Evil.</hi> that is, ſtarting another que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, to divert us from this we are upon, which is, The reaſon of Gods ſending his Son to Expiate the Sins of Men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <q>But this Expectation how <hi>unreaſonable</hi> ſoever, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhews it to have been the Common apprehenſion of Mankind in all Ages that God would not be appeaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor ſhould Sin be pardoned without <hi>Suffering:</hi> But yet ſo that Men generally conceiv'd good hopes that upon the Repentance of Sinners, God would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of a <hi>Vicarious</hi> Puniſhment, that is, of the Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome other in their ſtead. And very probably, as I ſaid before, in <hi>Compliance</hi> with this apprehenſion of Mankind, and in <hi>Condeſcenſion</hi> to it, as well as for other weighty Reaſons, beſt known to the Divine Wiſdom, God was pleaſed to find out ſuch a <hi>Sacrifice.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Dr.</hi> ſays here, That it is only <hi>probable</hi> that was the Reaſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Is it <hi>probable</hi> that God would Sacrifice his Son, in Compliance with an Expectation, <hi>How unreaſonable ſoever?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the <hi>Dr.</hi> in what I have quoted out of him before does not make any <hi>doubt,</hi> or <hi>perhaps</hi> of it; but ſets it down as a <hi>plain</hi> Caſe. As <hi>Serm.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 192. <hi>And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed</hi> (ſays he, in a <hi>poſitive</hi> Aſſeveration) <hi>A great Part of the</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Religion was a PLAIN Condeſcenſion to the general Apprehenſions of Men concerning this way of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſing God by Sacrifice.</hi> And therefore he does not ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Impiouſly to Blaſpheme that Religion which God gave to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and therein to arraign God its Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. He ſays, as above Quoted. Serm. 4. p. 184. That <hi>the Religion and Laws which God gave them was far from being the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt;</hi> Nay, plainly, that <hi>they were not good,</hi> by applying to them that Text. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.25. or at leaſt approving others Application of it that way, to which end he produces it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe Laws were <hi>not Good,</hi> that is, ſays the <hi>Dr.</hi> they were <hi>very imperfect in Compariſon of what he could have given them.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>So you may ſay of the Chriſtian Laws; they are <hi>Imperfect</hi> in reſpect to thoſe of Heaven. At this rate, nothing can be good but God. Yet God ſaid of his works, that they were very good. And ſaid ſo of his Laws which he gave to the <hi>Jews</hi> out of his own mouth. And ſure it is a moſt <hi>preſumptuous Blaſphemy</hi> for any Man to ſay, that they were not <hi>good.</hi> They were the ſame with the Chriſtian Laws, as much as could be before Chriſt came. They were all Types and Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners of his coming; and therefore they are call'd<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14.</note> Spiritual; their meaning was all Spiritual; They are called<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 2.16.</note> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and it is ſaid, that the Goſpel was firſt preacht to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and that<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 15.11.</note> they were ſav'd by the Goſpel, as well as we. The preaching of Chriſt is the Goſpel; and he was preached and exhibited in the whole Jewiſh Aeconomy, as the <hi>Seed promiſed,</hi> Gen. 3.15. <hi>which things the Angels deſire</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>To ſtoop down with Reverence and admire.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12.</note> They exceeded all Created underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ever to comprehend the full Glory, and Goodneſs, and Wiſdom which is contain'd in them, they far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel the whole material Creation; and the leaſt<note n="(*)" place="margin">Mat.</note> Tittle of the Law is preferr'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53033:7"/>Heaven and Earth,<note place="margin">5.18. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.17.</note> and ſhall out-laſt them. And was this Law far from being the beſt? Could this wiſe <hi>Dr.</hi> have found out better? Were theſe <hi>Statutes which were not good, and Judgments whereby Men ſhould not live?</hi> Was this the meaning of theſe words. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.25? Whereas the Reaſon given in the very ſame Sentence, <hi>v.</hi> 24 for God's threatning to give them <hi>Statutes which were not good,</hi> was as a juſt Judgment upon them for <hi>deſpiſing</hi> thoſe <hi>good Statutes</hi> which he had given them. Such Statutes, ſays God, <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>which if a Man do he ſhall even live in them.</hi> Yet this Author would have theſe to be the Statutes <hi>whereby men ſhould not live.</hi> This is an Excellent Interpretation! And for the word <hi>give,</hi> which I ſuppoſe muſt have miſled this Author, <hi>viz.</hi> That God is ſaid to <hi>give</hi> them theſe Statutes which <hi>were not good,</hi> and therefore he has Interpreted theſe to be the Law which God gave them; God is ſaid to <hi>give</hi> them theſe evil Statutes, <hi>v.</hi> 25. no otherwiſe than as he is ſaid to <hi>pollute</hi> them, <hi>v.</hi> 26. that is, to ſuffer them to be polluted, and to follow <hi>Idolatry,</hi> there meant by the Statutes which <hi>were not good.</hi> As God has threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.28. That it they would not ſerve him, He would give them up to <hi>Idolatry</hi> to ſerve Gods of <hi>Wood</hi> and <hi>Stone, &amp;c.</hi> But to ſay that the Laws which God gave <hi>were far from being the best,</hi> that they were <hi>not good,</hi> is ſuch a <hi>bold ſtroke</hi> as ſtops nothing ſhort of <hi>Blaſphemy.</hi> Whereas to expreſs their exceeding Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, and that there was no manner of defect or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection in them; They are often compared to Gold purified 7 times in the Fire, till no droſs at all was left. They were called<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Pure</hi> and <hi>Perfect,</hi> and therefore we are commanded neither to <hi>add</hi> nor <hi>diminiſh,</hi> They are called our<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.47.</note> 
                  <hi>Life,</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Holy,</hi> and <hi>Juſt,</hi> and <hi>Good,</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.96.</note> far exceeding all <hi>Perfection;</hi> But Dr. <hi>Til—t</hi> thinks they were nothing but a Complaiſance to the <hi>Folly</hi> and <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> of Men. O good God! Was the Glorious <hi>Goſpel</hi> and Salvation by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> not only exhited under its <hi>Types</hi> in the <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> but<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>promiſed before the World began.</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.11.</note> Purpoſed from <hi>Eternity,</hi>
                  <note n="‡" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.15 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forever;</hi> was the<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.20.</note> Blood of the <hi>Everlaſting Teſtament</hi> ſhed for no other Reaſons but to comply with Men's fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Expectations, <hi>How unreaſonable ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That ſuch dreadful Blaſphemy ſhould ever be heard in a Chriſtian Nation! That it ſhould paſs uncenſured!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Dr.</hi> ſays there may be <hi>other weighty Reaſons, best known to the Divine Wiſdom.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>This is perfect ſhirting and putting off. No doubt the Divine Wiſdom his many reaſons for every thing He does, which we cannot Comprehend. But the <hi>Dr.</hi> gives no other reaſon; and 'tis to be ſuppoſed he would have given a better, if he had it. Our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute is not what God <hi>knows,</hi> but what God has <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed.</hi> And how this Dr. underſtands thoſe Revelations, and whether according to the received Doctrine of the Catholick Church, particularly as it is profeſſed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in that Great and Fundamental Point of the <hi>Satisfaction</hi> of Chriſt, wherein if what is ſaid be not ſufficient. I will further ſhew you, that he is altogether a <hi>Socinian,</hi> even in this Sermon which he has publiſhed to blind the Eyes of the World, and free himſelf from that Imputation.</p>
               <p>Firſt, He abſolutely and avowedly cuts off the whole Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction</hi> due to the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of God for our Sins; or if due, that it need not be paid, and therefore, whatever other reaſons there may be, <hi>That</hi> can be none o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Reaſons of <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Dying for us; <hi>Not</hi> (ſays the <hi>Dr.</hi> in this Sermon, <hi>p.</hi> 11.) <hi>That God could not have pardoned ſin without</hi> Satisfaction <hi>made to his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, either by the ſuffering of the ſinner himſelf, or if a Sacrifice in his ſtead.</hi> p. 26. <hi>God did not want Goodneſs to have forgiven ſin freely, and without any ſatisfaction.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Why? Will you ſay that God did want ſo much Goodneſs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>By <hi>Goodneſs</hi> here you mean <hi>Mercy;</hi> and we know it is the proper effect of <hi>Mercy</hi> to <hi>forgive;</hi> and God's <hi>Mercy</hi> is <hi>Infinite;</hi> and ſo is his <hi>Juſtice,</hi> they do not <hi>Thwart</hi> or <hi>Contradict</hi> one another, but they <hi>Exalt</hi> and <hi>Magnify</hi> one another.</p>
               <p>Now the <hi>Dr.</hi> would put a Sophiſm upon us. To bid us deny that <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> or <hi>Mercy</hi> will <hi>forgive;</hi> Or to ſay that God is ſtinted in his <hi>Mercy</hi> or <hi>Goodneſs.</hi> But we will ſay, That <hi>Juſtice</hi> cannot be <hi>ſatisfied,</hi> without full <hi>Payment</hi> made; and that God is not crippled or ſtinted in his <hi>Justice</hi> more than in his <hi>Mercy:</hi> for He is <hi>Juſtice</hi> it ſelf, and therefore what is neceſſary to the Nature of <hi>Justice,</hi> muſt be ſo to His Nature, for they are the ſame. In your Senſe, Gods <hi>Atributes</hi> fight with one another, and one muſt overcome the other.</p>
               <p>But, as we explain it, They all ſtand <hi>Full</hi> and <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite,</hi> and no one <hi>Encroaches</hi> upon the other: but they <hi>Rejoice</hi> and <hi>Exalt together,</hi> and one <hi>Extols</hi> and <hi>Glorifies</hi> the other.</p>
               <p>That Gods <hi>Justice</hi> is magnified in <hi>Requiring</hi> full <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction,</hi> His <hi>Wiſdom</hi> in <hi>Finding</hi> it; and his <hi>Mercy</hi> or <hi>Goodneſs</hi> in <hi>Giving</hi> that Satisfaction for us.</p>
               <p>Now I appeal to your ſelf whether this be not more Rational, than to make the End of all the Glorious Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of the Goſpel to be nothing elſe than a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with a parcel of <hi>unreaſonable;</hi> and even <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>Diabolical</hi> Fancies which had poſſeſs'd Men's Minds, <hi>no matter how:</hi> Eſpecially conſidering that the Author and Preacher of this Glorious Conceit, <hi>Serm.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 180. confeſſes, That notwithſtanding of all that he can ſay in favour of this Brat of his own Brain, <hi>It may ſtill ſeem ſtrange to a Conſidering Man, that God, who, without all this</hi> Circumſtance <hi>and</hi> Condeſcenſion, <hi>could have done the Buſineſs for which his Son came into the World—ſhould yet make choice of this way for the Redemption and Recovery of fallen Man.</hi> That is to ſay, That God ſhould Sacrifice <hi>his own Son</hi> for nothing, to no purpoſe in the World, when all that his Son came for, might have been as well done without it. And this indeed muſt eternally ſeem ſtrange to any Man of common ſenſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:53033:7"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>But the <hi>Doctor</hi> defends himſelf in the words juſt following, <hi>(viz.) I make no manner of doubt to ſay that it would be a great preſumption and boldneſs in any Man, to affirm that the infinite Wiſdom of God could not have brought about the Salvation of Men by any other way, than by this very way in which he hath done it.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>This is the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s uſual Topick (which I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to you in our laſt Converſation concerning his Sermon of <hi>Hell</hi>) when Reaſon fails him to fly to God's <hi>Omnipotence,</hi> and dare us to ſay that God <hi>cannot</hi> do this or that; and therefore that what the Dr. ſays, <hi>may be</hi> true, for who dare ſay that God <hi>cannot</hi> make it true?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>But after all, will you ſay that God could not have ſav'd Man any other way than by the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of <hi>Christ.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>To avoid that Irreverent manner of Expreſſion, of ſaving God <hi>cannot</hi>— I ſay that, from the very nature of <hi>Justice,</hi> which is <hi>God,</hi> there was a neceſſity for a <hi>full</hi> and <hi>adequate Satisfaction</hi> to be made for ſin.</p>
               <p>Whether any other <hi>Satisfaction</hi> could have been found beſides the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of <hi>Chriſt?</hi> is another que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. And not to enter into the Depths of God, I will give you theſe Reaſons why no other way was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible by any Argument or Thought imaginable to us. Becauſe the Perſon muſt be <hi>Infinite,</hi> who could pay an <hi>Infinite</hi> Debt, (for ſuch is Sin, being an offence againſt Infinite Goodneſs) and likewiſe muſt be <hi>Man,</hi> that the ſame <hi>Nature</hi> which offended, ſhould make the <hi>Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</hi> And therefore that <hi>Chriſt</hi> took upon him the <hi>Nature</hi> of Man, and not the <hi>Perſon</hi> of any Man; that he might make Satisfaction for <hi>Mankind,</hi> and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for any particular <hi>Perſon.</hi> Hence he took <hi>all</hi> our <hi>Natural,</hi> but <hi>none</hi> of our <hi>Perſonal</hi> Infirmities. He was ſubject to <hi>Sleep, Wearineſs, Grief, Pain,</hi> and even <hi>Death,</hi> all which are incident to our <hi>Nature:</hi> But not to <hi>Sickneſs, Blindneſs, Lameneſs,</hi> or any <hi>Perſonal</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities. Since therefore it was neceſſary that our Redeemer muſt be <hi>God-Man,</hi> I think it will follow that it could be none other but <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, I think this Queſtion is decided <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.39. where Chriſt prays, That if it were <hi>poſſible</hi> that Cup might paſs from him. Which ſhews that it was not <hi>poſſible</hi> for him to accompliſh the Redemption of Man which he had undertaken; without ſuffering death, Otherwiſe, no doubt, God wou'd not have refuſed the Petition of his <hi>Well beloved</hi> Son. And it is no impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of God, to ſay, there was no other way <hi>poſſible.</hi> But, on the contrary, it is carrying the notion of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> to the utmoſt height, that when there was but one <hi>poſſible</hi> way, <hi>Wiſdom</hi> ſhould find it out.</p>
               <p>And the <hi>Dr.</hi> himſelf ſtumbles upon this unawares: it is hard to be conſtant in Error, which is it ſelf all unconſtancy. p. 10 of ſingle Serm. he ſaid, <hi>That nothing leſs than the perfect Innocency and Holineſs of him who was to be a Sacrifice for us, could have explated the guilt of our ſins, and purchas'd eternal Redemption for us.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>Great Sufferings likewiſe in</hi> our nature, <hi>even to the ſuffering of</hi> Death <hi>were</hi> requiſit <hi>to the</hi> perfect <hi>expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sin; I ſay even to the ſuffering of</hi> Death.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s words. From whence I ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, That none had <hi>perfect</hi> Innocency and Holineſs but <hi>God,</hi> and therefore that none but He <hi>CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LD</hi> have Explated the Guilt of our Sins.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Sufferings, for Explating the Guilt of our Sins, muſt be in <hi>our Nature,</hi> therefore the <hi>Expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> muſt be likewiſe <hi>Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Theſe Sufferings muſt be even unto <hi>Death.</hi> From all which it follows, that none cou'd be this <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piator</hi> but <hi>Chriſt God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> and that he muſt Suffer even unto <hi>Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If all which be true, then I deſire the <hi>Dr.</hi> to anſwer his own Objection, and tell us how it was poſſible for the Redemption of Man to have been effected any other way?</p>
               <p>I would recommend to him his own Advice upon this very matter. <hi>Serm.</hi> 4th p. 181. which he ſays he follows, <hi>All along, to take the expreſs Declarations, or at least, the pregnant Intimations of Scripture, for his Ground and Guide: it being always ſafeſt to take the Reaſons of the Divine Counſels and Actions from God himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now we wou'd gladly know (for he has no where told us) in what place of <hi>Scripture</hi> it is reveal'd, that God's ſending his <hi>Son</hi> and all the Aeconomy of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> was to <hi>Gratifie</hi> and <hi>Indulge</hi> the <hi>Senſeleſs</hi> and <hi>Wicked Prejudices,</hi> which Men had pick'd up concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Religion.</hi> For that is the account the <hi>Dr.</hi> gives us of his Faith. And it is more Monſtrous by far than any ever I heard ſet up, even by the <hi>Socinians</hi> themſelves.</p>
               <p>Yet the <hi>Dr.</hi> does not forſake them, tho' he thus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances ſometimes in ſtretches beyond them. For ſingle <hi>Serm.</hi> p: 21. He ſets up in expreſs terms, the account the <hi>Socinians</hi> give of the Remiſſion of Sins by <hi>Christ,</hi> viz. That it was not upon account of any <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction</hi> made by <hi>Chriſt</hi> for our ſins; but only an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Covenant,</hi> they cannot tell why, which <hi>God</hi> made with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that if he wou'd be <hi>Crucified,</hi> God wou'd remit the ſins of the Penitent. And that there was no need nor neceſſity for this Covenant, becauſe God might have remitted ſins, as well without this Covenant; or upon any other Covenant, the turning of a Straw, or what you will; or upon no Covenant at all. So that this Covenant with Chriſt, was wholly <hi>Cauſeleſs, Needleſs</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Socinian Covenant</hi> this Author ſets up in the page above quoted, where he ſays, That upon the Sufferings of Chriſt, <hi>God thereupon entered into a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace and Mercy with Mankind, wherein he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd himſelf to forgive the ſins of theſe who Believe and Repent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus this Author holds with the <hi>Socinians</hi> by exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>Satisfaction</hi> from being any part of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant or conſider'd at all in it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>You wou'd make one think it ſtrange how the <hi>Dr.</hi> came to Preach and Publiſh ſuch a Sermon as this with a deſign againſt the <hi>Socinians.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It was really to do them ſervice; And reconcile Men more to their principles, by leſſening the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences which are conceiv'd betwixt them and us, (a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53033:8"/>Topick much in practice with the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes with the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as <hi>Mahomet</hi> went to the Mountain which wou'd not come to him) which he makes ſo ſmall as to conſiſt in <hi>nothing but words.</hi> p. 32. <hi>to ſignifie juſt nothing.</hi> p. 31. For an account of this you will find pp. 16. 31. and 32. He ſums up the difference 'twixt the <hi>Socinians</hi> and us, as to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> to conſiſt only in this, That the <hi>Socinians</hi> ſay Chriſt ſuffered <hi>for us,</hi> or <hi>for our Sake;</hi> whereas others wou'd have it underſtood that Chriſt ſuffered <hi>for us,</hi> that is, <hi>in our ſtead.</hi> Which the <hi>Dr.</hi> proves, p. 32. to be a <hi>meer Controverſie about words.</hi> And ſo the matter is ſhortly reconcil'd, which has ſo much taken up the <hi>Chriſtian Church.</hi> And that very <hi>undeſervedly</hi> and <hi>uncharitably,</hi> if the difference be no more than this Author wou'd have us believe: Out of Friendſhip to which Party is eaſie to diſcover; for he has turn'd the Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> which is the whole of this Controverſie, to be no part of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie; and indeed without it all the reſt is a Conteſt about words, and he wou'd make you believe, that there is more betwixt the <hi>Socinians</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> than, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt died <hi>for our Sake,</hi> or, <hi>in our Stead,</hi> which, he ſays, are the ſame.</p>
               <p>Having thus cleverly brought off his belov'd <hi>Socinians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Witneſs the ſweet and gentle Epithets of <hi>Brutal, Falſe, Nonſence,</hi> &amp;c. which in one page of the Hiſtory of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> (p. 24.) are beſtow'd on us. That our Faith is <hi>abſurd,</hi> and <hi>contrary both to Reaſon, and to it ſelf: Impoſſible, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable,</hi> and that <hi>not to diſern it is not to be a Man.</hi> Ibid. Beſides many other the like Endearing Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements, in other places. As <hi>Impudent, Blaſphemous,</hi> and even <hi>Diabolical,</hi> and <hi>Idolatrous; Polytheiſme, Depths of Satan:</hi> Thus they call the <hi>Christian</hi> Doctrine which we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs.</note> he no longer conceals his Dear and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate Affection to them. He prefers them before all ſorts of Men in the World, and ſays, 2 <hi>Serm.</hi> p. 72. That even the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant,</hi> the <hi>Popiſh,</hi> nay, the very <hi>Jeſuits</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, are in Compariſon of <hi>them,</hi> but meer <hi>Scolds</hi> and <hi>Bunglers.</hi> And p. 70, 71. He ſays, <hi>To do right to the Writers on that ſide</hi> (<hi>The</hi> Socinians) <hi>I muſt own generally they are a Pattern of the fair way of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputing, and of Depating matters of Religion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Heat and unſeemly Reflections upon their. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They generally argue matters with that</hi> Temper <hi>and</hi> Gravity; <hi>with that</hi> Freedom <hi>from Paſſion, and</hi> Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport <hi>which becomes a ſerious and weighty Argument. And for the moſt part they Reaſon</hi> cloſely <hi>and</hi> clearly, <hi>with extraordinary</hi> Guard <hi>and</hi> Caution, <hi>with great</hi> Dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity <hi>and</hi> Decency, <hi>and yet with</hi> Smartneſs <hi>and</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty <hi>enough, with a very</hi> gentle Heat; <hi>and few</hi> hard words.</p>
               <p>A Man could hardly deſcribe his Miſtreſs in a ſofter Air. The <hi>Socinians</hi> muſt be very ill natur'd if they take any thing amiſs which this Gentleman has ſaid againſt them. It was meer neceſſity; they ſee how <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly,</hi> and <hi>artificially</hi> he has done it; and when rightly underſtood (no doubt they underſtand him) what he has ſaid is with a deſign to give a better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of them than has been done, to take off that frightful Character with which ſome have painted them, not allowing them the very name of <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> Whereas, alas! The <hi>Dr.</hi> has told us that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing betwixt them and us, but a <hi>meer Controverſie about words,</hi> which all mean the ſame thing. And then, that they are the <hi>best Temper'd,</hi> the <hi>Goodest</hi> ſort of People in all the World. So that we need not be afraid of them, nor ſtand upon our guard againſt them. And then they are the moſt <hi>Ingenious,</hi> and the <hi>Sweeteſt</hi> Men, that we ſhould love to Converſe with them, and Read their Writings; all the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> writers are but <hi>Scolds</hi> and <hi>Bunglers</hi> to them.</p>
               <p>This is our Author's Method of oppoſing <hi>Socinaniſm,</hi> nor are they behind him in their Civility and due Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, in the Anſwer they have Publiſh'd this year 1694. to his aboveſaid four Sermons, with other Diſcourſes againſt them. <hi>He</hi> (ſay they, that is, Dr. <hi>Tid.</hi> whom they call <hi>Arch Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Cant.</hi>) <hi>is the Common Father of the Nation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Conſiderations on the Explications of the Doctrine of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Occaſion'd by four Sermons Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Crace the Lord Arch Biſhop of <hi>Cant,</hi> &amp;c. p. 43.</note>) <hi>and has Instructed the</hi> Socinians <hi>themſelves, with the Air and Language of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not of an Adverſary, or a Judge— He is Reſpected and Lov'd by All, but thoſe that are alſo known to Hate their Country; He hath no other Maligners, but the Enemies of the Nation it ſelf,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>CLAW ME AND I'LL CLAW YOU— Here is Love and good Correſpondence in abnudance Theſe Gentlemen know their Friends; And the Cauſe of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity</hi> is like to be well Defended, when it is maintain'd by ſome of a Party, on purpoſe that it may be ſoundly an-ſwer'd by others of them, who play Booty to one anothers Hands. And commend and recommend one another to all Mens Eſteem and Veneration.</p>
               <p>But that this may not be diſcover'd, they Argree ſometimes, like <hi>Counſels</hi> at the Bar, to fall foul upon one another, even to Scold, and call Names: which, to the wiſe Obſervers, ſerves only to expoſe either their <hi>Contradictory Banter,</hi> or otherwiſe their <hi>Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Malice,</hi> and <hi>Deceit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus notwithſtanding of Dr. <hi>T</hi>'s <hi>Honey Words,</hi> above told, and all his <hi>Love-fits,</hi> to the <hi>Socinians,</hi> he ſends them a <hi>Bit</hi> and a <hi>Blow. Amantium Ira— He plays with his Clog.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, I will give you his Character of <hi>Secinus</hi> himſelf, the Head and Founder of that Order, and then of the <hi>Socinians</hi> his followers.</p>
               <p n="1">1ſt <hi>Serm.</hi> p. 17. 18. He tells the method of <hi>Socin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> in Interpreting Scriptures, which was, <hi>meerly by Criticiſing upon words, and ſearching into all the Senſes they are poſſibly capable of, till he can find one, tho' never ſo</hi> forc'd <hi>and</hi> forreign, <hi>that will ſave harmleſs the Opinion, which he was before hand reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lved to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, even againſt the most Natural and Obvious Senſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53033:8"/>of the Text which he undertakes to Interpret.</hi> p. 44. That he puts <hi>quite another Senſe</hi> upon the Scripture, than the <hi>Dr.</hi> believes, <hi>was thought of by any Chriſtian Writer whatſoever before</hi> Socinus, p 45. He accuſes the <hi>Novelty— great Violence and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs,</hi> and <hi>utter Inconſistency</hi> of <hi>Socinus</hi>'s Interpretations of Scripture. And, that it may not be forgot, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats all this again, 2 Serm. p. 57. and in p. 58. he calls <hi>Socinus</hi>'s Interpretations <hi>Strain'd</hi> and <hi>Violent— Pitiful and wretched ſhifts— Precarious</hi> and <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi>— without either <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Modeſty</hi> (p. 68.) <hi>And as to the</hi> Novelty <hi>of it,</hi> Socinus <hi>himſelf makes no difficulty to own it, nay, he ſeems rather to rejoyce and Applaud himſelf in it. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy Man! That was ſo wedded to his own Opinion, that no Objection, no Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty could divorce him from it.</hi> (p. 77.) Socinus— <hi>Impoſing a new and very odd and violent Senſe— Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Senſe of the Chriſtian Church in all Ages down to this time— And all this only to ſerve and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port an Opinion which he had entertain'd before, and therefore was reſolv'd one way or other to bring the Scripture to comply with it. And if he cou'd not have done it, it is greatly to be fear'd, that he wou'd at last have call'd in queſtion the Divine Authority of S.</hi> John's <hi>Goſpel, rather than have quitted his Opinion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And to ſpeak freely, I muſt needs ſay, that it ſeems to me a much fairer way to reject the Divine Authority of a</hi> Book. <hi>than to uſe it ſo</hi> Diſingeniouſly, <hi>and to</hi> wreſt <hi>the plain Expreſſions of it, with ſo wuch</hi> ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>and</hi> violence <hi>from their most Natural and Obvious Senſe: for no Doctrine whatſoever can have any certain foundation in any</hi> Book, <hi>if this Liberty be once admitted, without regard to the plain Scope and Occaſion of it, to play upon the</hi> Words, <hi>and</hi> Phraſes. p. 80. Socinus <hi>by a dangerous Liberty of impoſing a forreign and forc'd Senſe upon particular Texts</hi> (has) <hi>brought the whole</hi> (H. Scriptures) <hi>into uncertainty.</hi> p. 82.— <hi>Any one that reads him may ſee he was ſufficiently conſcious to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> (of the <hi>Novelty</hi> and <hi>Boldneſs</hi> of his Interpretation) p. 83. Socinus <hi>was the firſt Author of this Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe it was impoſſible he could ever have been ſo fond of ſo ill favour'd a Child, if it had not been his own.</hi> p. 114 <hi>Of which</hi> (Antiquity) <hi>as</hi> Socinus <hi>had but little Knowledge, ſo he ſeems to have made but little account.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is our Author's Character of <hi>Socinus,</hi> a Man of <hi>no Learning,</hi> deſpiſing <hi>Antiquity,</hi> becauſe Ignorant of it. <hi>Arrogant</hi> and <hi>Conceited,</hi> paſt all <hi>Modesty,</hi> Boaſting that none in the World underſtood the true meaning of <hi>Scripture</hi> before <hi>himſelf.</hi> Of which the <hi>Dr.</hi> gives ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Quotations out of his own words. 2 Serm. p. 69. Yet that his <hi>Shifts</hi> were <hi>Pitiful</hi> and <hi>Wretched, Strain'd</hi> and <hi>Violent, Precarious</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Modeſty;</hi> That he was ſo poſitive an <hi>Opiniator,</hi> that he wou'd rather have deny'd the <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly Scripture.</hi> than been convinc'd of his Error; that he dealt ſo <hi>Diſingeniouſly</hi> with the <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> wreſting the plain Expreſſions of it in ſuch a manner, that the <hi>Dr,</hi> thought it preferrable to reject their <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority,</hi> rather than to abuſe them as he has done: Nay, that no Writing whatſoever can have any certain meaning, if <hi>Socinus</hi>'s Liberty be allow'd of <hi>playing</hi> with the <hi>VVords</hi> and <hi>Phraſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus much for <hi>Socinus</hi> himſelf. Let us now ſee whether this Author gives a more favourable Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of his Diſciples, to make good the High Eulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giums above told? <hi>Serm.</hi> 2. p. 69. ſpeaking of <hi>Schlictingius,</hi> one of the firſt Form in his School our Author ſays, he carry'd himſelf <hi>with more</hi> Confidence, <hi>but much leſs</hi> Decency than his Maſter; That he ſpoke <hi>ſo</hi> Extravagantly, <hi>and with ſo much Contempt of theſe</hi> Great <hi>and</hi> Venerable <hi>Names, who were the chief Propagators of</hi> Chriſtianity <hi>in the World, and to whom all Ages do ſo juſtly pay a Reverence, That</hi> (he ſaid) <hi>thoſe</hi> Ancient Interpreters <hi>went ſo far from the Apoſtles meaning, as if they had</hi> Rav'd <hi>and been</hi> out of their Wits.</p>
               <p>And the <hi>Dr.</hi> ſays in general of the <hi>Socinians</hi> Serm. 1ſt p. 39. That their Interpretations of the <hi>Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> were <hi>ſtrange</hi> and <hi>extravagant.</hi> (p. 44.) did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict not only the <hi>Ancient Fathers,</hi> but <hi>the General Conſent of all</hi> Chriſtians <hi>for</hi> 1500 <hi>years together.</hi> p. 61. That they <hi>avoid the plain and neceſſary Conſequence of</hi> Holy Scriptures <hi>by</hi> ſtrain'd <hi>and</hi> forc'd <hi>Arts of Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trtion.</hi> p. 62. <hi>Than which nothing can be more</hi> unnatural <hi>and</hi> violent. p. 65. <hi>Which I dare ſay no Indifferent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of St.</hi> John, <hi>that had not been</hi> prepoſeſs'd <hi>and</hi> byas'd <hi>by ſome</hi> violent prejudice <hi>would ever have thought of.</hi> p. 75. <hi>The plaineſt</hi> Text <hi>for any</hi> Article <hi>of Faith, how</hi> Fundamental <hi>and</hi> Neceſſary <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ever, may, by the ſame Arts and ways of Interpretation, be cluded and rendered utterly ineffectual for the establiſhing of it.</hi> p. 92. 93. <hi>This is ſo Arbitrary and Precarious a ſuppoſition, that I muſt confeſs my ſelf a little out of Countenance for them, that Men of ſo much Wit and Reaſon ſhould ever be put to ſo</hi> ſorry <hi>and</hi> pitiful <hi>a Shift.</hi> p. 96. <hi>This is ſo</hi> Inartificial, <hi>not to ſay</hi> Abſurd <hi>a way of avoiding a Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty— that no Man of</hi> common Ingenuity <hi>would make uſe of it.</hi> p. 99. <hi>A Senſe ſo very flat, that I can hardly abstain from calling it</hi> Ridiculous. p. 113. <hi>We may plainly ſee by this, That they can Interpret a</hi> Text <hi>right when neceſſity forceth them to it, and they cannot, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great Inconveniency to their Cauſe, avoid it: But when Men have once reſolv'd to hold faſt an Opinion they have taken up, it then becomes, not only Convenient but Neceſſary to underſtand nothing that makes against it: And this is truly the preſent Caſe: But in the mean time, where is</hi> Ingenuity <hi>and love of</hi> Truth? p. 115. <hi>They Triumph without</hi> Modeſty, <hi>and without</hi> Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. p. 125. <hi>Do they ſee no</hi> Abſurdity <hi>in all this? Nothing that is contrary to</hi> Reaſon <hi>and</hi> Good Senſe? <hi>Nothing that feels like</hi> Inconſiſtency <hi>and</hi> Contradiction? p. 129. <hi>Which way</hi> (the <hi>Socinians</hi> way) <hi>of dealing with them</hi> (the Holy Scriptures) <hi>ſeems to be really more</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelious <hi>to thoſe Holy</hi> Oracles, <hi>than the down-right rejecting of their Authority.</hi> And ſingle Serm. p. 18. <hi>He that can deny this</hi> (the Doctor's Argument againſt the <hi>Socinians</hi>) <hi>is perverſe to the highest degree, and I fear beyond the poſſibility of being Convicted.</hi> p. 20. <hi>Men may generally wrangle about any thing, but what a fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous Contention, what a Trifling in ſerious matter,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53033:9"/>what</hi> Barretry <hi>in Divinity is this?</hi> p. 30. <hi>So little do Men in the heat of Diſpute and Oppoſition, who are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to hold faſt an Opinion in deſpight of</hi> Reaſon <hi>and</hi> Good Senſe, <hi>conſider that they do many times in effect, and by neceſſary Conſequence, grant the very thing in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs terms, they do ſo ſtifly and pertinaciouſly deny.</hi> p. 32. <hi>And this for no other reaſon, that I can imagine, but becauſe they have deny'd it ſo often; and ſo long.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe ſo different Characters which the Dr. gives of <hi>Socinus,</hi> and the <hi>Socinians,</hi> may be Reconciled, by ſaying, as I ſuppoſe the <hi>Dr.</hi> means, that this later <hi>Evil Character</hi> belongs to them, only in this preſent Controverſy of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> the <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But that the former <hi>High</hi> and <hi>moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarly Excellent Character</hi> is due to them, in other matters of Religion, as againſt the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> which the <hi>Dr.</hi> ſeems to intend, 2. Serm. p. 79. where he ſays. <hi>That the</hi> Socinian <hi>Writers have mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Cauſe of the</hi> Reformation <hi>againſt the Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Corruptions of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>both in Doctrine and Practiſe, with great acuteneſs and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>And yet in the very next words. he ſays, <hi>That the</hi> Socinians <hi>have put into their</hi> (the Papiſts) <hi>hands better and ſharper Weapons than ever they had before for the weakening and undermining of the Authority of the Holy Scriptures.</hi> And p. 129. <hi>That nothing hath given a greater force to the Exceptions of the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>againſt the</hi> Holy Scriptures, <hi>being a ſufficient and certain Rule of Faith, than the uncertainty into which they</hi> (<hi>the</hi> Socinians) <hi>have brought the plaineſt Texts ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable for the Establiſhing of Doctrines of the greateſt Moment in the</hi> Chriſtian Religion, <hi>by their</hi> Remote <hi>and</hi> Wreſted <hi>Interpretations of them.</hi> And p. 124. <hi>That to avoid the ſhaddow and appearance of a Plurality of Deities, they ran readily into it. And into downright Idolatry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now how invalidating the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing <hi>Idolatry</hi> is managing the Cauſe of the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> with <hi>Accuteneſs</hi> and <hi>Advantage</hi> againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I leave to the Worthy <hi>Dr.</hi> to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain. And likewiſe how Men can deſerve ſuch extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Commendations for <hi>Wit,</hi> and <hi>Modeſty;</hi> and all <hi>Diſcretion</hi> and <hi>Temper</hi> in one point of Controverſy; and in another to be quite void of all theſe, to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all <hi>Ridiculous Abſurdities</hi> and <hi>Contradictions,</hi> and to manage either without <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Modeſty;</hi> to be ſo Wedded to their own Opinion, as rather to Renounce the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> than endure to be convinced by them, in their moſt fooliſh and groundleſs Errors, taken up againſt the whole <hi>Christian</hi> World ſince the days of <hi>Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Modeſty</hi> and <hi>Sweetneſs</hi> in a-Mans <hi>Temper,</hi> will ſhew it ſelf in all his Actions. And a ſtrong <hi>Reaſon</hi> cannot overlook a <hi>Contradiction</hi> in one caſe more than another, at leaſt not to be obſtinately ſo Wedded to it, as to be deaf to all Conviction.</p>
               <p>But we have ſpent too much time upon this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's Character of theſe <hi>Socinians;</hi> which is not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial, otherwiſe, than to ſhew his own Unconſtancy, and Inconſiſtency with himſelf; How unwillingly he is brought to appear againſt them; And what Salvoes and Shifts he makes uſe of to make them underſtand him, That he might not loſe their Favour.</p>
               <p>God grant <hi>Him</hi> and <hi>Them</hi> true Conviction, and Save Unſtable Souls from their Snares.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>SInce this was wrote, the Author before ſpoke of <hi>Dr. T.</hi> has Printed <hi>A Sermon concerning the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Divine Nature, and the B. Trinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here if ever we might expect full Satisfaction in this point: But it is ſo far from it, that of all the others we have conſider'd, this Sermon does moſt pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pably bewray his wretched <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> if not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worſe: for he not only ſpeaks the very <hi>Socinian</hi> Language of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> but he really undermines the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of God, by his ſetting it up upon a Foundation, which he himſelf, in this ſame Sermon, quite over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws. His great Proof is p. 10. <hi>The General Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Mankind concerning the</hi> Unity <hi>of God</hi> that, <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Divine Nature, is a Notion wherein the</hi> Greateſt <hi>and the</hi> Wiſeſt <hi>part of Mankind did</hi> always <hi>agree.</hi> p. 4. And yet, ſpeaking of the <hi>Heathen Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry</hi> (which was all the reſt of the World except the ſmall Nation of the <hi>Jews</hi>) he ſays plainly, p. 9. that, <hi>The generality were groſly guilty both of believing</hi> more Gods, <hi>and of worſhiping</hi> falſe Gods. p. 10. <hi>And did termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate their worſhip there</hi> (in the Idol) <hi>as being the very</hi> Deity <hi>it ſelf, which was certainly</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the Caſe of the</hi> greateſt <hi>part of the</hi> Heathen <hi>World.</hi> And yet upon the Belief of this <hi>Greateſt</hi> part, he builds, the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of God; when he confeſſes that this <hi>Greatest</hi> part did not believe the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of God. All the Salvo for this moſt palpable Contradiction is what he offers p. 9. <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the <hi>Divine Nature— was the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive and General Belief of Mankind, and that Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm and Idolatry were a Corruption and Degeneracy from the Original Notion which Mankind had concerning God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:53033:9"/>
            <p>I do not doubt but <hi>Adam</hi> worſhiped the True God. And it is as true that <hi>Idolatry</hi> came in very ſoon; ſome ſay <hi>Cain</hi> introduc'd it. And that there was a very great defection ſo quickly made, that it is Recorded of the Birth of <hi>Enos,</hi> That <hi>then began Men to call upon the Name of the Lord,</hi> Gen. 4.29. as if they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver done it before. And the Scripture tells of the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral</hi> Corruption before the Flood. After the Flood we know the <hi>whole World</hi> was ſwallow'd up in an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Idolatry, except only the <hi>Family</hi> of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and after him of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who alſo were continually lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing into it.</p>
            <p>what then becomes of this Author's <hi>Greateſt</hi> part of Mankind? And his <hi>always?</hi> That this <hi>Greateſt</hi> part did <hi>always</hi> agree in the Notion of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of God? Whereas he, in the ſame place, makes this <hi>Greateſt part</hi> to have been <hi>always</hi> ſince the World was Peopled, <hi>Believers</hi> and <hi>Worſhipers</hi> of <hi>more Gods</hi> and <hi>falſe Gods,</hi> in ſuch groſs <hi>Idolatry</hi> (as I cannot believe ever befel one Man ſince <hi>Adam,</hi> or that it is poſſible to beſal any Man, being ſo apparent a Contradiction, <hi>viz.</hi>) to terminate our Worſhip in the <hi>Image</hi> or <hi>Idol as being the very</hi> Deity <hi>it ſelf.</hi> For how can any Man believe ſuch a thing to be the <hi>Image,</hi> or <hi>Picture</hi> of another thing; and yet to be that very thing of which it is the <hi>Image?</hi> Or is it in any Man's power to believe that a thing can be the <hi>Image,</hi> or <hi>Idol</hi> of its ſelf? Cou'd <hi>Solomon</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this? Or was not he an <hi>Idolater?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We know whom this favours and there may be a time to Recant even our <hi>Neſtrum</hi> againſt <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> It won'd be no greater change, than what has been already! And <hi>there is no ſtop in Art,</hi> nor are we ever, <hi>too old to learn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much for his betraying the <hi>Unity</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> by placing it upon a Foundation, which he himſelf hath overthrown.</p>
            <p>Next to ſhew that, as to the <hi>Trinity</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> he ſpeak the very <hi>Socinian</hi> Language.</p>
            <p>All that he ſays of it is in Sect. 3. p. 19, 20. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he muſt ſay ſomething. He is ſoon weary of it, and firſt he gives a Broad-ſide againſt it in direct Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to what the <hi>Divines</hi> ſay of it (He deſires not, or deſerves not to be reckon'd one of the number) for the Diſpute is not about the words <hi>Trinity,</hi> or <hi>Perſon,</hi> but as to the <hi>Senſe</hi> of theſe words, in which they are uſed by <hi>Divines.</hi> The <hi>Socinians</hi> own a <hi>Trinity;</hi> and they have lately Re-printed and Publiſhed <hi>Bidle</hi>'s <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith touching the Holy Trinity.</hi> But all the matter is in what Senſe the word <hi>Trinity</hi> is us'd by our <hi>Divines,</hi> and by the <hi>Socinians,</hi> and in this he peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily determines againſt the Senſe of the <hi>Divines</hi> as <hi>Anti-Scriptural.</hi> He ſays, That <hi>neither the word</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <hi>nor perhaps</hi> Perſon, <hi>in the Senſe in which it is uſed by</hi> Divines <hi>when they treat of this</hi> Myſtery, <hi>are any where to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e met with in</hi> Scripture. This is directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> as taught by <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines.</hi> Put he brings himſelf off thus. <hi>Yet it cannot be deny'd</hi> (ſays he) <hi>but that Three are there ſpoken of by the Names of Father, Son, and Holy Ghost,</hi> [this no <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian</hi> in the World denies] <hi>in whoſe Name every</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>is Baptized,</hi> [this is likewiſe granted by the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians</hi>] <hi>and to each of whom the higheſt Titles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of God are in Scripture Attributed.</hi> Neither does this offend the <hi>Secinians,</hi> who Plead the ſame in anſwer to <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hn</hi> 1.3. as you have it in the <hi>Brief H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> which ſolves that Text, <hi>All things were made by him,</hi> (i. e.) by the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>word,</hi> thus: The <hi>word</hi> (ſays he) <hi>begins here to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of as a</hi> Perſon, <hi>by the the ſame figure of Speech, That</hi> Solomon <hi>ſaith, Wiſdom hath hath builded her Houſe, and heuen out her ſeven Pillars,</hi> Prov. 9.1. <hi>And that</hi> David <hi>calls Gods Commandments</hi> Councellours, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.24.</p>
            <p>And, in concluſion, this Author is willing to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound for the word <hi>Perſon</hi> (of which we have ſpoke before) <hi>So long</hi> (ſays he) <hi>as we mean by it neither more nor leſs than what the</hi> Scripture <hi>ſays in other words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he has told you before, that there is no ſuch thing to be found in <hi>Scripture, in the ſenſe in which it is uſed by Divines;</hi> And what other ſenſe he means, is eaſie to tell. For the preſent Controverſie is only betwixt the two <hi>ſenſes,</hi> of the <hi>Divines</hi> (as he calls them) and the <hi>Socinians:</hi> unleſs he means ſomething elſe by the word <hi>Divines,</hi> and ſo makes the whole a <hi>Banter</hi> upon us. For he does not explain himſelf, nor ſay one word more, in all that <hi>Sermon touching the Bleſſed Trinity;</hi> of the difference 'twxit the <hi>Socinians</hi> and us concerning this great <hi>Fundamental</hi> of our <hi>Faith.</hi> And whether this be or whether it be not, a ſufficient clearing of himſelf as to what ſide he inclines. when he could find no more to ſay againſt the <hi>Socinians</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this point, in a Diſcourſe which he <hi>Entitles,</hi> and ſo would make us believe to be, <hi>A Vindication</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Doctrines to the <hi>Bleſſed Trinity</hi> againſt that of the <hi>Socinians,</hi> I leave to the Impartial Reader.</p>
            <p>And now for a Concluſion, upon the whole, that has been ſaid of all his Sermons, they are all the Genuine effects of <hi>Hobbiſm</hi> which looſens the Notions of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, takes from it all that is <hi>Spiritual,</hi> Ridicules whatever is called <hi>Supernatural;</hi> it reduces <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Matter,</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> to <hi>Nature.</hi> In this School Dr. <hi>T.</hi> has theſe many years, held the Firſt Form, and now diffuſes his Poyſon from a high Station. It is many years ago ſince the E. of <hi>D.</hi> one <hi>Sunday,</hi> that Dr. <hi>T.</hi> Preach'd at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> told K. <hi>C.</hi> 2d that Mr <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bbs</hi> was got into the Pulpit, his <hi>Politicks</hi> are <hi>Leviathan,</hi> and his <hi>Religion</hi> is <hi>Latitudinarian,</hi> which is <hi>none;</hi> that is, nothing that is <hi>poſitive,</hi> but againſt every thing that is <hi>poſitive</hi> in other Religions; whereby to reduce all Religions to an uncertainty, and determinable on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the <hi>Civil Power;</hi> againſt whoſe Command Dr. <hi>T.</hi> does not think it lawful to Preach the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Preach'd before K. <hi>C.</hi> the ad at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> the 2d of <hi>April</hi> 80 upon <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh.</hi> 24.15.</note> 
               <hi>without ſuch extraordinary Commiſſion as the Apoſtles had; and that we were able to vouch it with Miracles, as they did;</hi> which is as much as <hi>Hobbs</hi> himſelf could have ask'd, if he had got into the Pult it in Perſon, and not ſent his Deputy: He is own'd by the <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> Wits of all <hi>England,</hi> as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53033:10"/>their true <hi>Primate</hi> and <hi>Apostle;</hi> They Glory and Rejoice in him, and make their publick Boaſts of him; He leads them not only the length of <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> (they are but ſlender <hi>Beaux</hi> have got no father than that) but to call in queſtion all <hi>Revelation;</hi> to turn <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> &amp;c. into a meer <hi>Romance,</hi> to Ridicule the whole as <hi>Blunt, Gildo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and others of the Doctor's Diſciples have done in Print. They now cry there is nothing but <hi>Natural Religion.</hi> All that which is called <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed,</hi> is at moſt but Gods Compliance with the <hi>Superstition</hi> of the vulgar, and what does that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern Men of Wit and Senſe? Since Religion has no deeper a Root, what Reverence, what Veneration is due to it? All the <hi>Ordinances</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Goſpel</hi> are but <hi>Politicks</hi> to ſecure <hi>Government</hi> and the threatenings even of <hi>Hell</hi> it ſelf are no more, and therefore, there is no <hi>neceſſity,</hi> no <hi>certainty</hi> that they will be inflicted; as our <hi>Primate</hi> has boldly aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the very Face of the Government, and his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon was Printed <hi>by their Majesties ſpecial Command.</hi> Thus to the <hi>Deists</hi> Triumph! And thus, <hi>actum est d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Religione,</hi> if none dare oppoſe <hi>theſe depths of Satan,</hi> and the <hi>Spiritual wickedneſſes</hi> which are now ſet up in high places. When this Sermon of <hi>Hell</hi> was firſt Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, it was handed about among the great Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chees, and ſmall Atheiſtical Wits, more than any new Play ever came out, He was not a Man of Faſhion who wanted one of them in his Pocket, ot could not draw it out at the Coffee-Houſe, and read a Lecture of the <hi>Prieſt-Ridden</hi> Ages, who were frighted with the <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> of <hi>Hell,</hi> only to keep them in abſolute ſubjection to the Church <hi>forſooth!</hi> And then to run two or three Diviſions in praiſe of Dr. <hi>T.</hi> as a Man of Senſe and Reaſon, and not afraid to undeceive the World, and break off from a Company of formal and <hi>narrow-ſpirited</hi> Church-men, who going on in the track of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, durſt not underſtand the Scriptures, out of the ancient Roade, in a Generous Latitude, over the Pailes of any Church or Profeſſion whatſoever; but crept on ſtill in their <hi>straight</hi> and <hi>narrow</hi> way to Heaven; which Dr. <hi>T.</hi> like another <hi>Prómetheus,</hi> having ſtole the Divine Secret, has opened ſo <hi>broad</hi> and <hi>wide</hi> as to let in the <hi>Latitudinarians,</hi> that is all the World; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome reaſonable time even <hi>Hell</hi> it ſelf: For God has only <hi>threatened,</hi> that <hi>they ſhall not enter into his Reſt;</hi> and the Dr. has determined in that <hi>Helliſh Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> p. 13. and 15. That God is not obliged to <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute</hi> his <hi>Threatenings,</hi> tho' he is to <hi>perform</hi> his <hi>Promiſes.</hi> But having ſpoke at large of this in a former Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation with you, I will not Repeat.</p>
            <p>I am now only from the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſtant Tract of all his Sermons (as well before as ſince this Revolution, but now highly improved and grown bolder) ſhewing you what a Face he puts upon <hi>Religion;</hi> he gives it quite another turn from what all other Divine, Ancient and Modern (except thoſe infected with <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bbiſm</hi>) have told us. They make the chief buſineſs of Religion to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect another World, tho' it is likewiſe highly uſeful, and the moſt efficacious of any other means whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to preſerve the Peace of this. But Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> Dr. <hi>T.</hi> &amp;c. make its <hi>chief,</hi> and indeed almoſt <hi>onely</hi> conſideration to reſpect the Peace and Quietneſs of this World. Which is largely ſet forth in his Sermon before the Houſe of Commons the 5th of <hi>November,</hi> 1678. upon <hi>Luke</hi> 9.55, 56. where, as if <hi>Religion</hi> were good for nothing elſe but to ſecure Temporal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Peace in this World; He demands Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſterially, and with great vehemence in theſe words <hi>And for God's ſake what is Religion good for, but to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Manners and Diſpoſitions of Men, to reſtrain Human Nature from Violence and Cruelty, from Falſhood and Treachery, from Sedition and Rebellion?</hi> And then, In the very next words, he roundly and without min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the matter, comes to the Objection, That if this be all the end of Religion, it were better to have no Religion at all, than to diſturb our outward Peace and Tranquility for it: Becauſe the <hi>End</hi> is always to be preferr'd before the <hi>Means;</hi> And therefore if the <hi>End</hi> of all <hi>Religion</hi> be only to preſerve the <hi>Peace of this World,</hi> it follows neceſſarily that <hi>Religion</hi> muſt give place to the <hi>Peace of this World;</hi> ſo that if both can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand together, we muſt part with our <hi>Religion</hi> to preſerve the <hi>Peace of this World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the <hi>Dr.</hi> does diſtinguiſh, and puts in a Salvo for his dearly beloved <hi>Natural Religion,</hi> becauſe he can make of that what he will. But he plainly and in terms gives up the Cauſe as to all <hi>Revealed Religion:</hi> That it were better have no ſuch thing, that is, no <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> rather than to diſturb <hi>our Peace in this World for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Better it were,</hi> ſays he, <hi>there were no</hi> Revealed <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and that Human Nature were left to the Conduct of its own Principles, and Inclinations, which are much more mild and merciful, much more for the Peace and Happineſs of Human Society, than to be acted by a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that is continually ſupplanting Government, and undermining the Wellfare of Mankind.</hi> This is their <hi>outward Wellfare</hi> he is ſtill ſpeaking of. And above in the ſame page, aggravating the miſchiefs of diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances upon account of Religion, <hi>(viz.) ſetting a kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner edge upon Mens Spirits,</hi> and making them more <hi>Cruel</hi> and <hi>Bitter</hi> to one another, he concludes thus. <hi>For let any Man ſay worſe of</hi> Atheiſm <hi>and</hi> Infidelity, <hi>if he can,</hi> Here is a bold Challenge, and the <hi>Dr.</hi> could not but foreſee the Anſwer which would be ready in every Man's Mouth, That <hi>Hell</hi> and <hi>Damnation,</hi> which are threatened as the puniſhment to <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and <hi>Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> were much worſe than any Embroylments could be in this World. But he has made <hi>Hell</hi> precarious, and conſequently <hi>Religion</hi> to look no further than this World, at leaſt with any <hi>certainty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is not only matters of ſuch conſequence as <hi>Government</hi> which the <hi>Dr.</hi> prefers to <hi>Revealed</hi> Religion: But, to ſhew his utmoſt Contempt of it, he has found out ſo very <hi>mean</hi> a thing to compare to it, and prefer before it, as muſt ſurpriſe and aſtoniſh every <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Reader.</p>
            <p>He makes a Womans giving out her Child to Nurſe to be a more heinous matter, than to renounce <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and all <hi>Revealed</hi> Religion. His words are theſe.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:53033:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And this;</hi> (ſays he, that is, a Womans Nurſing her own Child) <hi>is a Natural Duty; and becauſe it is ſo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Six Sermons Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, 1694. Serm. 3. <hi>Concerning the Education of Children,</hi> p. 103.</note> 
               <hi>of a mere neceſſary and indiſpenſable Obligation than any poſitive Precept of</hi> Revealed <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Belief of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is nothing elſe but a <hi>poſitive</hi> Precept of <hi>Reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Religion. <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the only truly <hi>Revealed</hi> Religion. God never <hi>Revealed</hi> any other: For the <hi>Goſpel</hi> was Preach'd to the <hi>Jews</hi> as well as unto us. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.2. The <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> taught Chriſt <hi>to come,</hi> as the <hi>Goſpel</hi> ſhewed him, when he <hi>was come.</hi> From the firſt <hi>Revelation</hi> of him <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. to the end of the World, it is the ſame <hi>Goſpel,</hi> the ſame <hi>Chriſt</hi> that is Revealed.</p>
            <p>And Dr. <hi>T.</hi> even ſince he came to <hi>Cant,</hi> has Printed it, and Publiſhed it to all the World, that he thinks, a Womans Nurſing her own Child is more <hi>neceſſary</hi> than the Belief of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and of more <hi>Indiſpenſible</hi> Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And his poor Reaſon, becauſe it is a <hi>Natural</hi> Duty, will advance every <hi>Paſſion</hi> or <hi>Vice</hi> that we think to be <hi>Natural,</hi> above all the Commands of God in <hi>Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We know what ſins the <hi>Libertines</hi> do plead for as <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural;</hi> and they think that <hi>Marriage,</hi> which is but a <hi>Poſitive</hi> Precept, ought not to ſuperſede the <hi>Natural</hi> Freedom.</p>
            <p>Theſe Men meaſure <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil</hi> by their preſent corrupted <hi>Nature,</hi> and thereby give their <hi>Luſts</hi> the <hi>Aſcendent,</hi> and a Superior <hi>Authority</hi> to the <hi>Written</hi> Word of God. By which means they have ſhaken themſelves looſe from all <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of <hi>Religion;</hi> But <hi>what they know</hi> Naturally, <hi>as Brute Beaſts,</hi> Jude 10. <hi>in thoſe things they corrupt themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What our <hi>Nature</hi> was before the <hi>Fall,</hi> we cannot n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w tell. And that only can be truly called <hi>Natural;</hi> that is, what was agreeable to our <hi>Nature</hi> in its <hi>Purity</hi> and in its <hi>Perfection;</hi> not now in its <hi>Broken</hi> and <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted</hi> Condition.</p>
            <p>Which is therefore much more ſafely conducted by unerrable <hi>Revelation</hi> from God; than to have thoſe <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Oracles</hi> over-rul'd, and ſuperſeded by our very Fallible Notions of <hi>Nature;</hi> which every Man may make to mean what he pleaſes: For what is counted very vile and abominable in ſome Nations, is practiſed without ſcruple, among other People, and thought ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Natural,</hi> and therefore very <hi>Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, a Man may think that to be <hi>Natural</hi> to day, which to morrow he may think quite otherwiſe. Which ſhews the <hi>Fallibility</hi> of this Rule.</p>
            <p>Even this great <hi>Natural</hi> Dr. himſelf, in the Reign of K. <hi>C.</hi> 2d thought (at leaſt <hi>Preached</hi> it before the K.) that <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Rebellion, Perfidiouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Perjury,</hi> were contrary to the <hi>Natural No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi>
               <note place="margin">3d <hi>Vol. of his Serm.</hi> 3d Serm. <hi>upon</hi> 1 John 4.1. p. 76. 77.</note> and therefore that no <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation</hi> was to be credited which did but <hi>Allow</hi> of them; no, not tho' even <hi>Miracles</hi> were done in confirmation of any ſuch <hi>Revelation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet, this notwithſtanding, he juſtified the Preſent Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the viſible <hi>Finger of God</hi> in it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thanksgiving Serm. for our Deliverance by the</hi> P. <hi>of</hi> O. p. 68. 69. 70, 71, 72.</note> and the plain <hi>Signatures</hi> and <hi>Characters</hi> of a more imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate <hi>Divine</hi> Interpoſiton. Such as the <hi>uncertainty of the Weather,</hi> the <hi>Infatuation</hi> of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Councils, and other ſuch like <hi>Signatures</hi> of a <hi>Divine</hi> Interpoſition, which he mentions: And from ſuch <hi>Miraculous</hi> Interpoſitions, he Juſtifiers thoſe (whom he calls, <hi>The Worthies of our Nation</hi>) who <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, Betray'd,</hi> and took Arms againſt K. <hi>James.</hi> So that we find the Doctors <hi>Nature,</hi> and his <hi>Natural No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> vary'd in a very little time, and upon a ſmall variation of Circumſtances; inſomuch that what one day, he would not truſt to <hi>Revelation</hi> or <hi>Miracles</hi> for; the next day, the <hi>turning of the Wind</hi> ſhall be Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſufficient.</p>
            <p>For ſome Mens Notions of what is <hi>Natural,</hi> are ſuited to what they find agreeable to their <hi>Nature,</hi> that is, to their <hi>Eaſe;</hi> their <hi>Convenience,</hi> or ſometimes to their <hi>Luſts</hi> and <hi>Pleaſures,</hi> or even their <hi>Reſentments</hi> and baſeſt <hi>Paſſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would not here be miſunderſtood, as if I meant to Decry all <hi>Natural</hi> Religion and Reaſon. No doubt, there is ſuch a Light imprinted in our <hi>Nature</hi> by God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But it is much darkened ſince to <hi>Fall,</hi> and needs the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of <hi>Revelation</hi> to direct our way to Heaven. And it ought to be ſubſervient to <hi>Revelation,</hi> which is all I plead for; and not ſet up againſt it, and prefer'd before it, as this <hi>Dr.</hi> and others of his Principles have raſhly done.</p>
            <p>I compare our Natural <hi>Light</hi> or <hi>Knowledge</hi> to the Creation of the <hi>Firſt Day.</hi> And it is the <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>First Day</hi> which we enjoy ſtill: But not as it was that day Created. It was Regulated and Modeled the <hi>Fourth Day</hi> into the <hi>Sun, Moon;</hi> and <hi>Stars:</hi> And now we have no Participation at all of the <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>First Day,</hi> but what we have from its Regulation on the <hi>Fourth Day,</hi> and conveyed to us from the <hi>Sun:</hi> Which I compare to <hi>Revealed,</hi> that is, the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, <hi>God</hi> is called Light, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.5. and <hi>Chriſt</hi> (<hi>Mat.</hi> 4.2.) is called <hi>the Sun of Righteouſneſs:</hi> and tho' there is a Precedent <hi>Natural</hi> Knowledge of God; like the <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Day;</hi> yet now that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is <hi>Revealed,</hi> the true Knowledge of God is to be had, as the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>only in the Face of Jeſus Christ:</hi> For none know God truly but the Son, <hi>and he to whom ſoever the</hi> Son <hi>will Reveal him. Mat.</hi> 11.27,</p>
            <p>And to go back <hi>now</hi> from the <hi>Revealed</hi> to <hi>Natural</hi> Religion, is, as if we ſhould forſake the <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>Sun,</hi> to grope after the <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as <hi>Chriſt</hi> is Superiour to our Natural <hi>Light,</hi> or <hi>Reaſon;</hi> ſo the Inſtitutions of his <hi>Revealed</hi> Religion, do take place of our <hi>Natural</hi> Inſtincts.</p>
            <p>Thus ſhall a Man leave his <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Mother,</hi> which are <hi>Natural</hi> Relations, and ſhall cleave to his <hi>Wife,</hi> which is a <hi>Poſitive</hi> Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> our <hi>Governors</hi> both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> our <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Political</hi> Fathers have greater Authority over us than our <hi>Natural</hi> Parents.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:53033:11"/>
            <p>So far is it from being true which Dr. <hi>T.</hi> has ſet up as a <hi>Maxim,</hi> that what he calls. <hi>Natural</hi> Duties, <hi>are of more neceſſary and Indiſpenſible Obligation, than any Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Precepts of</hi> Revealed <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the contrary, the Precepts of <hi>Revealed</hi> Religion, as they are of far Greater and Higher Authority than our own meer <hi>Natural</hi> Notions; So are they the ſureſt Indication of what was the <hi>Firſt</hi> and <hi>Original, Pure</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncorrurted</hi> Dictates of our <hi>Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have here only mentioned theſe ſhort paſſages out of ſome of Dr. <hi>T's</hi> Sermons, to ſhew his plain and down-right <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bbiſm;</hi> upon which I could enlarge, and ſhew you the ſame Thread to run through all his Works: But this I intend for a Task by it ſelf, my preſent Work being his <hi>Socinianiſm.</hi> And I think it an Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſible Duty to warn the World, eſpecially this poor Kingdom, of this Man's Diabolical Principles, becauſe he is got now into ſo high a Sphere, as to be able to do much miſchief among the Clergy, by preferring thoſe of his own Principles, the <hi>Latitudinarians;</hi> and by this means, he may bid fair to Pervert the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; he has deeply poyſoned them already. And if this be not a time to ſpeak, we may for ever after hold our Tongue. He that would not, in this Caſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his Life, and all that he had, would never do it for any Cauſe of Chriſt; for the Ax was never laid more palpably at the very Root of all Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>I hope what I have ſaid will at leaſt provoke abler Pens to Engage in Defence not only of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> but of the firſt Principles and Foundation of <hi>Religion in General;</hi> which the <hi>Hobbiſs;</hi> have depreſs'd far below that of the <hi>Heathen;</hi> who acknowledg'd <hi>Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation</hi> tho' they miſtook it: But theſe make it a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Tool and Engine of State, hung at the Belt of the Civil Magiſtrate, and diſpoſeable by him at his pleaſure, Theſe are yet more dangerous, more affronting to God, than the <hi>Socinians:</hi> For the <hi>Socinians</hi> argue, tho from a falſe Topick, for the <hi>Honour</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as if more <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> were <hi>Diſhonourable</hi> to the <hi>Divine Nature;</hi> But theſe dare Blaſphemouſly to make <hi>God an Ape</hi> to the <hi>Devil</hi> himſelf; and to be beholding to his Imvention, and the <hi>Capricio's</hi> of <hi>Fooliſh</hi> and <hi>Wicked</hi> Men, for all the Inſtitutions of his Holy Religion; and to have ſent our Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> into the World, and <hi>Sacrificed</hi> Him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Croſs</hi> for no other End than to comply with the <hi>wickedneſs</hi> of Men, and inſtead of <hi>deſtroying the works of the Devil,</hi> infinitely to <hi>out-do them,</hi> to put them out of Countenance, and make them aſham'd of their Little<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Sacrificing <hi>Beasts</hi> and <hi>Men,</hi> inſtead of which poor Butcheries and Murther, and to make them no more regarded, Here the <hi>Son of God</hi> ſhall be murthered, to ſhew how little miſchief the <hi>Devil</hi> could do in Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of <hi>God!</hi> And to frighten and amaze Mankind, the moſt wicked of them, and to ſtop their hand from the further purſuit of their little Inſignificant Cruelties to one another, by being ſtruck with the horror of ſuch <hi>Super-wickedneſs,</hi> and <hi>unnatural Barbarity;</hi> As the K. of <hi>Moab</hi> Sacrificed his Eldeſt Son, to ſtop the purſuit of his Enemies. (2 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.27.) by over glutting their Revenge and out-doing their Cruelty.</p>
            <p>Theſe are not Tares Sown in the <hi>Night,</hi> and by <hi>Stealth;</hi> But it is Rooting up all <hi>Revealed</hi> Religion in the <hi>Noon-day,</hi> and expoſing of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> to the Contempt and Buffoonery of Atheiſtical Wits. And if the <hi>Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> take no no notice of it; They are not <hi>Aſleep</hi> but <hi>Dead.</hi> God awaken them by a timely ſenſe of their Duty, and not by a Total Extirpation and Removeal of their Candleſtick. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="reflections">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53033:11"/>
            <head>Some REFLECTIONS upon the <hi>Second</hi> of Dr. <hi>BURNET's</hi> Four Diſcourſes, concerning the Divinity and Death of Chriſt. <hi>Printed 1694.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Had ended the Reader's Labour and my own, but that I am call'd back by a Book now lately Publiſhed; Licenſed by this Great <hi>Dr.</hi> Himſelf <hi>Jo. Cant.</hi> to give it the greater Authority; and wrote by his Collegue Dr. <hi>Burnst,</hi> now called Biſhop of <hi>Sarum;</hi> It is Entituled, <hi>Four Diſcourſes delivered to the Clergy of the Dioceſs of</hi> Sarum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Printed 1694.</p>
            <p>One of theſe Diſcourſes is <hi>Concerning the Divinity and Death of Chriſt;</hi> wherein there is ſuch a Notion of <hi>Chriſt's Divinity</hi> ſet down as would make any <hi>Christian</hi> Ear to tingle. He gives the very ſame account of it as <hi>the Brief History of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> in Anſwer to <hi>John</hi> 1.14. <hi>The Word was made Fleſh;</hi> that is, ſays that <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian</hi> Author, the Word <hi>dwelt in,</hi> or did <hi>Inhabit</hi> the Perſon of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> There is none that is unpreju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced but muſt ſee how very far this is from the full Import of that Text, and what a force is done to the words of the Text <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>was made Fleſh.</hi> This is ſure a degree beyond bare <hi>Inhabitation.</hi> It is true our <hi>Soul</hi> may be ſaid to <hi>dwell</hi> in our Body: But there is ſomething more, It is <hi>Imperſonated</hi> with our Body, whence there ariſes what the <hi>Schools</hi> call <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatio Idiomatum,</hi> between the <hi>Soul</hi> and the <hi>Body;</hi> That is, that the Properties of <hi>each</hi> are attributed to the <hi>Perſon</hi> who partakes of <hi>Both.</hi> Thus Man is called <hi>Mortal,</hi> becauſe his <hi>Body</hi> is ſuch; and <hi>Immortal,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his <hi>Soul</hi> is ſuch. And thus it is that <hi>Christ</hi> is called <hi>God,</hi> in reſpect to his <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his <hi>Human.</hi> Neither of theſe can be predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated of the other. The <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> is not the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nature,</hi> nor the <hi>Human Nature</hi> the <hi>Divine.</hi> The <hi>Soul</hi> is not the <hi>Body,</hi> nor the <hi>Body</hi> the <hi>Soul:</hi> But <hi>each</hi> of theſe is predicated of the <hi>Perſon</hi> who partakes of <hi>Both.</hi> All the <hi>Atiributes</hi> of the <hi>Divine,</hi> and <hi>Properties</hi> of <hi>Human Nature,</hi> are predicated of <hi>Christ;</hi> as all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> are predicated, tho' not of <hi>One another,</hi> yet of <hi>Man,</hi> who is made up of <hi>Both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the true Notion of <hi>Imperſonation,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this <hi>Chriſt</hi> could never be made <hi>Fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Spirit of God did <hi>Inhabit,</hi> or <hi>Inſpire</hi> the <hi>Apoſtles, Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Holy Men</hi> of Old: and will do every <hi>Saint,</hi> or <hi>Holy</hi> Perſon to all Eternity. But this does not make <hi>God</hi> to become <hi>Fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you anſwer that the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> or the <hi>Word</hi> (as the <hi>Socinians</hi> ſay, did inhabit or inſpire that Man <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> in an <hi>Higher Degree</hi> than other Men: That will make nothing, as to the <hi>Word's</hi> becoming <hi>Fleſh: God</hi> was no more <hi>Fleſh</hi> in <hi>Abraham</hi> or St. <hi>Paul,</hi> than in the <hi>Meanest Saint,</hi> tho' he inſpired one much more than another.</p>
            <p>Nothing ſhort of <hi>Imperſonation</hi> could make him to become <hi>Fleſh;</hi> or make that Fleſh <hi>Adorable</hi> without the higheſt Idolatry. Dr. <hi>B.</hi> thinks to ſolve all this by comparing God's <hi>Indwelling</hi> in <hi>Jeſus,</hi> to the <hi>Indwelling</hi> of God in the <hi>Cloud of Glory</hi> in the <hi>Temple,</hi> and he ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 127. That the <hi>Jews, worſhipped</hi> the Cloud of Glory, <hi>becauſe of God's Reſting upon it,</hi> and therefore that they <hi>could make no Objection</hi> to the Chriſtians Worſhipping of <hi>Christ, by vertus of the Indwelling of the</hi> Eternal word <hi>in Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Make no Objection<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Yes ſure; and Retort the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to the Confuſion of ſuch <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> For they did not worſhip the <hi>Cloud of Glory.</hi> That had been Rank <hi>Idolatry,</hi> Notwithſtanding of any <hi>Inhabitation</hi> of God there, and therefore from this Reaſoning, it muſt have been <hi>Idolatry</hi> to have worſhipped <hi>Chriſt,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of any <hi>Inhabitation</hi> of God in him.</p>
            <p>Nor will it ſolve this, that the <hi>Dr.</hi> ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 116. That there was a more <hi>perfest Indwelling of God in Chriſt, than in the Cloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So there was in the <hi>Cloud</hi> more than in the <hi>Temple;</hi> yet it had been as great Idolatry to have worſhiped the <hi>Cloud</hi> as the <hi>Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God's Preſence was never more viſibly exhibited in any Apparition under the Law, than when he deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon <hi>Mount Hereb</hi> in <hi>Fire, Cloud,</hi> &amp;c. He ſpoke out of that <hi>Fire</hi> with an <hi>Audible V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ice,</hi> which he did not out of the <hi>Cloud of Glory</hi> in the <hi>Temple.</hi> And yet he ſtrictly forbids the <hi>worſhipping</hi> of any thing they there ſaw, or the <hi>making</hi> any <hi>Reſemblance</hi> or <hi>Similitude</hi> of any thing that there appeared, leſt it ſhould cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt them to <hi>Idelatry,</hi> Deut. 4.15. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As before obſerved, the Degrees of <hi>Inhabitation</hi> ſay nothing to the making the thing inhabited to be God: No leſs Inhabitation than an <hi>Imperſonation</hi> can do that, becauſe no leſſer or other ſort of <hi>Inhabitation</hi> does car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with it the <hi>Communicatio Inli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>matum,</hi> ſo as to make <hi>God</hi> be called <hi>that thing,</hi> or <hi>that thing</hi> be called <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore it is a groſs Error which the <hi>Dr.</hi> aſſerts p. 113. <hi>That the Indwelling of the</hi> Jehovah <hi>was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Scripture Phraſe, ſaid to be</hi> Jehovah,</p>
            <p>It is ſo far from <hi>Scripture Phraſe,</hi> that all the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> do deteſt it as <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This diſtinction would juſtifie the worſhip of the <hi>Sun,</hi> as being a Glorious <hi>Tent</hi> or <hi>Tabernacle</hi> of God.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53033:12"/>And no doubt, God does <hi>Inhabit</hi> it, as he does every Creature in their ſeveral Degrees, and this will juſtifie all the wild <hi>Heathen Idolatry.</hi> For <hi>Higher</hi> or <hi>Lower</hi> in <hi>Creatures,</hi> that is, different degrees of God's <hi>Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> make no difference as to the <hi>worſhip</hi> of them. It is as much <hi>Idolatry</hi> to worſhip the <hi>highest Angel</hi> as the <hi>meaneſt Worm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore the <hi>Dr's</hi> Argument is moſt <hi>Heterodox,</hi> that the <hi>Inhabitation</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> makes <hi>Christ</hi> to be <hi>God:</hi> If by <hi>Inhabitation</hi> he means any thing ſhort of <hi>Imperſonation.</hi> Which if he had meant, he had never thought of explaining it, by the <hi>Inhabitation</hi> of God in the <hi>Cloud:</hi> Or thruſt himſelf upon ſuch a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipice of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> as to aver that the <hi>Cloud</hi> was <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah,</hi> and that they <hi>worſhipped</hi> the <hi>Cloud</hi> becauſe of <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>dw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lling</hi> in it.</p>
            <p>Yet as the former <hi>Dr.</hi> who Licenſes what this his <hi>Second</hi> has wrote, will not (as before told) ſtand out, or looſe any thing for the word <hi>Perſon:</hi> But then you muſt take what he means by it; So this Stickler, does now and then ſlip it in, that he may have it to ſay; but will not let himſelf be miſtaken, in explaining it, as above.</p>
            <p>The deſign is to wear Men off from this <hi>Perſonality</hi> by degrees; never making uſe of the word, but ſome way or other to expoſe it, and to lead Men from the true and full meaning of it, as it was neceſſarily uſed, on purpoſe to diſtinguiſh ſuch direful and waſting <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies</hi> as now infeſt the Church under much Sheeps Cloathing.</p>
            <p>For if God has not aſſum'd our Nature into his own <hi>Perſon;</hi> only dwelt in Chriſt, as in the <hi>Temple,</hi> as in the <hi>Cloud,</hi> tho' in an higher degree: <hi>Christ</hi> cannot be our <hi>God,</hi> and we are <hi>Idolaters</hi> in worſhipping Him; as much as the <hi>Heathen</hi> in worſhipping their <hi>Idols</hi> from the ſuppoſed <hi>Inhabitation</hi> of God in them. And God has not taken upon him <hi>our Nature,</hi> more than the Nature of <hi>Angels</hi> (as the Apoſtle argues <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.16.) Nay, God <hi>dwells</hi> more viſibly with his Angels, or <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habits</hi> them more ſully, and intimately, than <hi>Mankind.</hi> Therefore <hi>God's dwelling</hi> in a <hi>Man</hi> does no more make him <hi>God,</hi> than <hi>God's dwelling in the Angels of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> makes all them to be <hi>God.</hi> If this Argument hold, <hi>Lucifer</hi> was in the right when he pretended to be <hi>God:</hi> for he was the moſt <hi>Glorious Angel;</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently God did <hi>dwell</hi> in him in an <hi>Higher Degree</hi> than in <hi>other Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Example ſhews that no degrees of <hi>Inhabitation</hi> gives any Title to <hi>Divine Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What then has <hi>Mankind</hi> gain'd by God's <hi>Inhabitation</hi> in the <hi>Human Nature of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> if that be all? What is that to other Men? What better am I for that, than for his <hi>Inhabitation</hi> in the <hi>Human Nature</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or even in the dead Walls of the <hi>Temple?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O, yes, ſays the <hi>Dr.</hi> p. 120. <hi>The Great God is alſo our Faderal God, or</hi> Jehovah, <hi>by his dwelling in the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nature of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was He not <hi>Jehovah</hi> likewiſe, or a <hi>Faderal God,</hi> to the <hi>Jews?</hi> And that by his <hi>Dwelling</hi> in the <hi>Temple,</hi> and affording his Preſence there? Does he not call them his <hi>Faderal</hi> People? <hi>Gather my Saints together unto me, thoſe that have made a</hi> Covenant <hi>with me by Sacrifice.</hi> Pſal. 50.5.</p>
            <p>How is the <hi>Human Nature</hi> advanced beyond that of <hi>Angels?</hi> Or, as it is expreſs'd in St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi>'s <hi>Creed,</hi> how is the <hi>Manhood taken into God,</hi> if there be no more than a bare <hi>Inhabitation</hi> of God in the Fleſh? <hi>Chriſt is our Lord</hi> (ſays the <hi>Dr.</hi> ibid. p. 120.) <hi>nos by an Aſſumption into an High Dignity, or the Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Divine. Honour to him, but as the Eternal Word dwelt Bodily in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well then, <hi>Dr.</hi> You ſay that the <hi>In-dwelling</hi> of the <hi>Eternal word</hi> did not Communicate <hi>Divine Honour</hi> to <hi>Chriſt.</hi> How then, I pray you, is he <hi>Adorable?</hi> How is he God <hi>by Nature?</hi> Since (as you quote it in the next page 121.) it is the <hi>Definition</hi> which St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives of <hi>Heatheniſh Idolatry</hi> 4 Gal. 8. to worſhip thoſe who <hi>by Nature</hi> are not, Gods. And you your ſelf p. 110.) Give this Deſcription of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> that is, <hi>Either the worſhipping of other Gods beſides the true, or the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the true God under a Bodily Repreſentation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now you confeſs that the <hi>Eternal word</hi> dwelt <hi>Bodily</hi> in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> which I ſuppoſe you will not ſay of his dwelling in the <hi>Temple,</hi> or in any other <hi>Holy Man.</hi> and therefore to worſhip God only <hi>in</hi> Chriſt (which you would be at) is the worſhipping of God under a <hi>Bodily</hi> Repreſentation, more than worſhipping him in the <hi>Sun,</hi> or in any <hi>Image,</hi> becauſe he is not ſo <hi>Bodily</hi> Repreſented in them or in any thing elſe as in the <hi>Human Nature</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Christ. I</hi> ſay the worſhipping of <hi>Chriſt</hi> muſt, by this Rule, be the moſt direct <hi>Idolatry,</hi> if we ſuppoſe no more than an <hi>Indwelling</hi> of the <hi>Divinity</hi> in him; and not that his <hi>Human Nature</hi> was Exalted, and even <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſonated</hi> with the <hi>Divine</hi> Nature, whereby he was as truly and really, that is, <hi>Naturally God,</hi> as he was Man.</p>
            <p>But rather then let <hi>Chriſt</hi> be a <hi>Divine Perſon,</hi> the <hi>Dr.</hi> Would be content to looſe his own <hi>Perſonality,</hi> and Confound the very Notion of <hi>Subſiſtence</hi> or <hi>Perſonallity;</hi> at leaſt 'twixt <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Spirit;</hi> which he takes upon him to Explain in a New and Extraordinary Manner, for ſeveral Pages to gether. At laſt he comes to this. p. 106. <hi>Theſe are all the ways</hi> (ſays he) <hi>That we can apprehend of a Minds aſſuming matter, and being united to it, which is the having it under i'ts actuation or authority; So that the Acts of the mind give ſuch Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions to the Body, as Govern and Command it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Deſcription wou'd <hi>Imperſenat</hi> all the <hi>Angels</hi> which have appeared in <hi>Bodyes</hi> with that matter which they aſſum'd: for there is no doubt but they did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly well <hi>Command</hi> and <hi>Govern</hi> thoſe Bodyes: better much than we can do ours. Made <hi>'em Fly</hi> and <hi>Mount</hi> as they pleaſed.</p>
            <p>And upon this account the <hi>Eternal word</hi> was often <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſonated</hi> with <hi>Matter,</hi> before his being made <hi>Fleſh</hi> in the womb of the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin;</hi> if we believe, as it is Generally believed, That it was <hi>He</hi> who appear'd to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the <hi>Buſh,</hi> to <hi>Joſhua</hi> as the <hi>Captain of the Lord's Hiſt,</hi> to <hi>Abraham,</hi> in the form of an <hi>Angel,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:53033:12"/>
            <p>But all this was not aſſuming any of theſe forms, in which he appeared, into his own <hi>Perſon;</hi> for then wou'd have follow'd the <hi>Communicatio Idiomatum,</hi> ſuch <hi>Fire,</hi> or <hi>Body</hi> in which he appear'd would have been truly and Really <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> wou'd have been that <hi>Fire,</hi> or that <hi>Body.</hi> which as it is <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> to affirm, ſo this ſhews us a ſtricter Notion of <hi>Imperſonation</hi> than the <hi>Dr.</hi> ſets up; which is only the <hi>Minds Commanding</hi> and <hi>Governing</hi> of <hi>matter.</hi> In which Senſe, <hi>God</hi> muſt be <hi>Imperſinated</hi> with every <hi>Body</hi> in the World, for he <hi>Commands</hi> and <hi>Governs</hi> them <hi>Abſolutely;</hi> and he <hi>Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits</hi> and <hi>Dwells</hi> in every one of them, for <hi>in Him</hi> they have their <hi>Being.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Dr. in his <hi>Vindicatory Letter</hi> to Dr. <hi>Williams,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Quoted, p: 99. adds further, <hi>That this indwelling is</hi> a vital <hi>one, like that of the Souls dwelling in the Body, and not an</hi> aſſiſting <hi>one, like Inſpiration, or the Gift of Tongues or Miracles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this will not hinder the Conſequence above told. For in <hi>God</hi> we <hi>Live</hi> and <hi>Move,</hi> as well as have our <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in Him. <hi>Acts.</hi> 17.28; Therefore He may be even a VITAL <hi>Indwelling,</hi> and yet ſhort of <hi>Imperſenation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſays, That this <hi>Indwelling</hi> of the <hi>Word</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is LIKE <hi>that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the Souls dwelling in the Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be <hi>like</hi> it, but not of the ſame ſort. <hi>Every like,</hi> we ſay, <hi>is not the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſays above, in the ſame page; That <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the Divine and Human Nature in Chriſt, is repreſented in Scripture as the Compounding one Perſon, as much as in other Men the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of Soul and Body makes one Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, indeed is fairly ſaid, if it be as ſincerely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended.</p>
            <p>For, if this be ſo, there muſt follow the <hi>Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Idiomatum</hi> betwixt the <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Human</hi> Natures in Chriſt, as much as betwixt the <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Man.</hi> Which the <hi>Dr.</hi> will not allow. For, if he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd this, there cou'd be no Cauſe of Diſpute. And if he had thought thus, he cou'd never have explain'd it by the <hi>Indwelling</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Cloud;</hi> nor found any ſcruple againſt the word <hi>Perſon;</hi> nor have been forc'd to new and uncouth Expoſitions of <hi>Perſonality:</hi> Nor wou'd he have made a Diſtinction (as before told) betwixt the <hi>Man-hoed</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> or the <hi>Man Chriſt</hi> being advanc'd <hi>into God</hi> (as the <hi>Athanaſian Creed</hi> expreſſes it) or the <hi>Communicating Divine Honour to Him</hi> (as Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> words it p. 120. of his Diſcourſe above Quoted) I ſay, if he had Really and Truly believ'd the <hi>Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonation</hi> of the <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Human</hi> Nature in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as the <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> are <hi>Imperſonated</hi> in Man, as he would ſeem to ſpeak in his Vindication, he could not have made a Diſtinction between <hi>Christ's Aſſumption into an High Dignity, or the Communicating Divine Honour to Him,</hi> and betwixt the <hi>Dwelling</hi> of the <hi>Eternal Word</hi> Bodily <hi>in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For if by <hi>Bodily</hi> here he had meant a <hi>Bedily Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonation</hi> as betwixt MANS <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body,</hi> then that <hi>Man</hi> CHRIST had not only Divine <hi>Honour Communicated to Him</hi> (which the <hi>Dr.</hi> denies) by the <hi>Indwelling</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> but He Himſelf was the <hi>Word.</hi> But the <hi>Dr</hi>'s true meaning is, that the <hi>Bodily</hi> dwelling of the <hi>Word</hi> in the Man <hi>Chriſt,</hi> was only a dwelling in his <hi>Body,</hi> without <hi>Imperſonation,</hi> or Communicating His <hi>Divine Attributes</hi> to Him; and therefore that no Divine <hi>Honour</hi> was thereby <hi>Communicated to Him;</hi> which the <hi>Dr.</hi> aſſerts, as above Quoted, in the 120th p. of his <hi>Diſcourſe.</hi> And inſtead of correcting this, in his <hi>Vindication,</hi> he re-aſſerts it more poſitively in another as he thinks, more odious Form of words, For there p. 96. He puts the Caſe of a <hi>Mans</hi> being made a <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>that was ſo called, and was to be worſhipped as ſuch.</hi> And this he calls <hi>a new Doctrine, that it ſeems</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ſcarce conceivable how any one can entertain this, and yet retain any value for Religion: I muſt confeſs</hi> (ſays he) <hi>I cannot; and it is ſo natural for a Man to judge of others by himſelf, that I do not think others do it, or indeed can do it.</hi> Theſe are his words. And, by this, it is very plain that he does not think the <hi>Man</hi> Chriſt to be <hi>God,</hi> or, that <hi>Christ</hi> is <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> but only <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Man.</hi> And conſequently, that there is no <hi>Hypoſtatical,</hi> that is, <hi>Perſonal</hi> Union betwixt the <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Human</hi> Nature of Chriſt, as there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> in <hi>Man;</hi> For if there were, then the <hi>Communicatio Idiomatum</hi> muſt neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; that is, the <hi>Properties</hi> or <hi>Attributes</hi> of each of their <hi>Natures</hi> would belong to the <hi>Perſon</hi> who did par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of <hi>both.</hi> And the <hi>Man</hi> Chriſt would be as truly <hi>God</hi> as he was <hi>Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for the <hi>Dr</hi>'s Bug-bear word of a <hi>Man</hi>'s being made <hi>Gods.</hi> with which he thinks to frighten us, as if <hi>God</hi> could be <hi>made,</hi> let him know that there are none ſo abſurd as to think that <hi>God</hi> can be <hi>made;</hi> and that this is not the ſame thing as a <hi>Man</hi>'s being made <hi>God;</hi> becauſe, tho' the <hi>God-head</hi> cannot be <hi>made;</hi> and in that Senſe, nothing can be <hi>made</hi> God; yet a <hi>Man</hi> by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken into a <hi>Perſonal</hi> Union with God, becomes really <hi>God,</hi> as much as the <hi>Body</hi> becomes a <hi>Man,</hi> by its <hi>Perſonal</hi> Union with an <hi>Human Soul:</hi> Notwithſtanding of which <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> the two different <hi>Natures</hi> of <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Soul</hi> remain nothing the leſs <hi>diſtinct</hi> and <hi>Unconfounded</hi> in themſelves, and in their ſeveral <hi>Properties,</hi> Incommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicable to each other. tho' all equally Predicated of the ſame <hi>Perſon</hi> who partakes of both <hi>Natures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> by this Phraſe, in this place, does plainly declare againſt the <hi>Divinity</hi> of Chriſt, and that he neither <hi>does</hi> nor <hi>can</hi> believe it. Nay he <hi>Ridicules</hi> it, and <hi>Blaſphemes</hi> it, in ſetting up the Notion of <hi>a Man that was made a God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And tho' as he ſays, p. 99. <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the Divine and Human Nature in</hi> Chriſt, <hi>irrepreſented in Scripture as the compounding one Perſon, as much as in other Men, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of Soul and Body makes one Man.</hi> He muſt mean, by this, only that this was a <hi>Compariſon</hi> or <hi>Repreſentation</hi> uſed in Scripture whereby the <hi>Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> of the <hi>Word</hi> in <hi>Christ</hi> was in ſome manner, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed out, or repreſented, not that it was ſtrictly ſo. For if he had thought it <hi>ſtrictly ſo,</hi> that the <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Human</hi> Natures in <hi>Christ</hi> were as much <hi>Imperſonated,</hi> as <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> in other Men, he would never have made it an abſurdity that a <hi>Man</hi> was made <hi>God,</hi> more than that the matter of a <hi>Man's Body</hi> is made a <hi>Man.</hi> or part of the <hi>Perſon</hi> of a <hi>Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:53033:13"/>
            <p>He could never have ſtumbled upon ſuch broad Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy as to ſay, That no <hi>Divine Honour</hi> was Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to <hi>Christ,</hi> and that he <hi>was not our Lord, by an Aſſumption into an High Dignity,</hi> as before quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>Hence we muſt learn how to underſtand many of his Plauſible ſayings, as thus p. 127. of his <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> where, having Explain'd <hi>Perſonality,</hi> as above told, to mean no more than a Power in the <hi>Soul</hi> to <hi>Command</hi> and <hi>Govern</hi> the <hi>Body;</hi> he brings in a Plauſible Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for the <hi>Perſonal</hi> Union of the <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Human</hi> Natures in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> but yet with a <hi>Salvo</hi> to ſecure his ſecret meaning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So that upon theſe Reaſons</hi> (ſays he, and not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) <hi>we may well and ſafely determine that Chriſt is truly God and man: and that the God-head did as really dwell in his Human Nature, and became <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited to it, as our Souls dwell in our Bodies, and are <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſounds very <hi>Orthedox.</hi> But it is all to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood only <hi>upon theſe Reaſons.</hi> That is, which dwindle down <hi>Perſonality</hi> only to a Power to <hi>Command</hi> and <hi>Govern;</hi> and by <hi>Chriſt is God and Man,</hi> he means no more than that <hi>God</hi> dwelt in that <hi>Man</hi> Chriſt; and ſo He was both <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man;</hi> but not that they were one <hi>Perſon,</hi> any otherwiſe than as <hi>God</hi> did <hi>Command, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern,</hi> or <hi>Enliven</hi> that <hi>Man;</hi> (as he does all Men.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt was truly God.</hi> That is, as the <hi>Cloud</hi> was <hi>Jehovah,</hi> which the <hi>Dr.</hi> aſſerts in this ſame page, and is one of the Premiſes from whence he draws this Concluſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The God-head <hi>dwelt</hi> in Chriſt and was <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited</hi> to him, as our Souls <hi>dwell</hi> in our Bodies, and are <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited</hi> to them, that is, as the <hi>Dr.</hi> has Explain'd it, only to <hi>Command</hi> and <hi>Govern</hi> them.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee what true pains is taken by theſe two Great <hi>Doctors</hi> to Elude and totally to Enervat the whole <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Doctrine, and all the <hi>Terms</hi> wherein for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of <hi>Hereſies,</hi> it has been conceived and deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down to us from Chriſt and his Apoſtles through all Ages of the Catholick Church.</p>
            <p>If it be not ſo. Why are not they content to ſet down their Faith in the plain Terms uſed by the Church? Why all theſe <hi>New</hi> and <hi>Laborious</hi> Expoſitions? Why do they thus <hi>Intangle</hi> and <hi>Perplex?</hi> Why can they not ſay three <hi>Perſons</hi> in the <hi>Trinity,</hi> as well as three <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences,</hi> three <hi>ſomewhats?</hi> Why do they confound us as this <hi>Dr.</hi> p. 96. with the difference betwixt <hi>diſtinct</hi> and <hi>diſtinction?</hi> viz. That by <hi>Perſon,</hi> in the <hi>Trinity,</hi> we muſt not mean a <hi>compleat Intelligent Being</hi> diſtinct <hi>from every other Being. But only that every one of that Bleſſed</hi> Three, <hi>has a peculiar</hi> diſtinction <hi>in Himſelf, by which he is truly</hi> different <hi>from the other Two.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Different</hi> but not <hi>diſtinct;</hi> Not <hi>diſtinct</hi> but that has a <hi>Diſtinction!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the meaning of this? What is the Quarrel at the word <hi>Perſon?</hi> O that theſe <hi>Dr's</hi> would ſpeak out! That they would go fair over to the <hi>Socinian</hi> ſide! Or do they ſtay, that they may more Effectually under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Doctrine by <hi>diſtinguiſhing</hi> and <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodating</hi> all to the <hi>Socinian</hi> Hypotheſis. And by this means draw Men Inſenſibly into it? Therefore we muſt deal plainly with them and tell (becauſe they will not) what they would be at. Which is, to make the 3 <hi>Perſons</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> onely 3 <hi>Manifeſtations</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> Or, the ſame <hi>Perſon</hi> of God conſidered under 3 different <hi>Qualifications</hi> and <hi>Reſpects,</hi> as our <hi>Creator, Redeemer, Sanctifier.</hi> But we muſt Ask, if it was only a <hi>Manifeſtation</hi> that was made <hi>Fleſh?</hi> If we are Baptized into the <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>worſhip</hi> of a <hi>Manifeſtation?</hi> why but 2. or 3 <hi>Manifeſtations</hi> of God, are there not Hundreds? is God, or the <hi>first Perſon,</hi> one of his own <hi>Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> Why then is He reckoned as one of the <hi>Three?</hi> Are theſe three all <hi>one</hi> and the ſame <hi>Perſon?</hi> Is this then the meaning of <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.32. That whoſoever ſpeaketh againſt one of <hi>theſe One</hi> ſhall be forgiven, but whoſoever ſpeaketh againſt <hi>Another</hi> of the ſame <hi>One</hi> ſhall not be forgiven? That we are Baptized in the Name of the <hi>Father,</hi> and of the <hi>Son</hi> (who is the Same <hi>perſon</hi> with the <hi>Father</hi>) and of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> (who is the ſame <hi>Perſon</hi> with them both (or in the Name of the <hi>Father,</hi> and of <hi>Himſelf,</hi> and of <hi>Himſelf?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the <hi>plain, Eaſie,</hi> and <hi>Intelligible</hi> Socinian Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem of Divinity! This is the <hi>Rational</hi> account of their Faith.</p>
            <p>And this <hi>(Doctors Both)</hi> you muſt ſtick to, or give us leave to uſe the word <hi>Perſon</hi> in the already known and Received Notion of that Term, and as the <hi>Holy Catholick Church</hi> hath always underſtood it in Expreſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Glorious Trinity</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>B.</hi> Concludes this point with referring to the four bove-ſaid Sermons of <hi>Dr. T.</hi> and clawing him for the Grace of this <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> by giving his Judgment of that work, as perform'd with great <hi>Strength and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Reaſon.</hi> p. 128.</p>
            <p>Thus theſe two <hi>Pillars</hi> ſtand bound <hi>jointly and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally</hi> for one Anothers <hi>Ingenuity</hi> and <hi>Performances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that they may keep even pace, Dr. <hi>B.</hi> now paſſes on to the other great point of <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> the <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> p. 134. Wherein he Copys after, and comes up to the full of that Diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Hereſie, ſo bare-fac'd ſet up by Dr. <hi>T.</hi> againſt the <hi>Satisfaction</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which is the only <hi>Foundation</hi> for the <hi>Remiſſion</hi> of <hi>ſin.</hi> He firſt. p. 134. Endeavours to Remove the Great Ground-Work of any <hi>Satisfaction</hi> being due to <hi>Gods Juſtice</hi> for ſin, by Advancing that Notion of <hi>Juſtice</hi> which Dr. <hi>T.</hi> does in his Sermon of <hi>Hell.</hi> He calls it onely a <hi>Right</hi> of puniſhing which is <hi>veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Himſelf,</hi> and therefore <hi>which he may either uſe or not uſe at his pleaſure.</hi> Upon this is grounded the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cariouſneſs</hi> of <hi>Hell,</hi> that God not being Oblidg'd in his <hi>Juſtice,</hi> to inflict <hi>Hell,</hi> notwithſtanding of his threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tening it, It is not <hi>certain</hi> whether he will do it or not.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>B.</hi> Says that this <hi>Juſtice</hi> is a Right, <hi>veſted in God Himſelf;</hi> and which therefore, He argues. God may diſpenſe with at his pleaſure. So far he argues truely, That God is not, nor can be accountable to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other; And therefore, in this ſenſe, he may do, in every thing, as he pleaſes; That is, as to any Outward Compulſion, or giving an Account of his Actions to any whatſoever.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:53033:13"/>
            <p>But, on the other hand, <hi>God is</hi> (as I may ſo ſay) <hi>Ty'd up</hi> to his own Inherent Rectitude, and all the Perfections of his Nature. It is not being <hi>Ty'd up,</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way <hi>Limited,</hi> It is the Higheſt and moſt abſolute <hi>Liberty,</hi> that he <hi>can</hi> never be otherwiſe. If he <hi>could</hi> loſe his <hi>Liberty,</hi> He would not be ſo <hi>free.</hi> Thus God <hi>cannot</hi> Die, <hi>cannot</hi> ceaſe to be God, <hi>Cannot</hi> make Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf not to be <hi>Eternal, Infinite,</hi> &amp;c. And that he <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not</hi> depart from any of his <hi>Attributes</hi> (not withſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſound of the word <hi>Cannot</hi>) is no <hi>Stinting</hi> of his <hi>Prerogative,</hi> but the <hi>Height</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Justice</hi> is as much an <hi>Attribute</hi> of <hi>God</hi> as his <hi>Mercy.</hi> He is not onely <hi>juſt,</hi> that is, has <hi>Justice,</hi> or a <hi>Great deal</hi> of <hi>Justice</hi> in him, but he is <hi>Juſtice</hi> it ſelf, <hi>Juſtice</hi> in the <hi>Abstract; Juſtice</hi> is of the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> And therefore, He can no more depart from it than from Himſelf. The Higheſt Notion of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> as of <hi>Love</hi> or <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> that is <hi>God,</hi> it is the very <hi>Nature</hi> of God. <hi>God</hi> is <hi>Love.</hi> 1 John 4.8. <hi>God</hi> is likewiſe <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</hi> And as all the <hi>Love</hi> or <hi>Goodneſs</hi> in us, is but a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of the Infinite and Eternal <hi>Goodneſs;</hi> ſo all the <hi>juſtice,</hi> all the Notion we have of <hi>Right</hi> or <hi>Wrong,</hi> is but a Ray Sent down to us from the Eternal and Eſſential <hi>Reſtitude</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> which is <hi>God.</hi> Now here is the difference betwixt God and us, We have a <hi>Mixture</hi> of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and of <hi>Mercy</hi> in us: and ſometimes we Exert an Act of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and ſometimes of our <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; Juſtice</hi> has the Aſcendant in ſome, over <hi>Mercy;</hi> and in others <hi>Mercy</hi> has it over <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, if a Man <hi>Remits</hi> without <hi>Satisfaction;</hi> We ſay not that it is <hi>unjuſt</hi> in him, becauſe he then Exerts an Act of <hi>Mercy</hi> onely. But none ſay that this proceeds from his <hi>Juſtice.</hi> To <hi>forgive</hi> is no part of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> that is all-together <hi>Mercy. Juſtice</hi> will Exact to the uttermoſt farthing. <hi>Justice</hi> MUST do it, it were not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if <hi>Justice</hi> cannot do it; <hi>God</hi> cannot do it. For <hi>God is Juſtice;</hi> and therefore whatever is <hi>Eſſential</hi> to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> muſt be ſo to <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Justice</hi> do not <hi>thwart</hi> or <hi>overcome</hi> One Another in <hi>God,</hi> as in <hi>Man:</hi> becauſe each is <hi>Infinit</hi> in <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you cannot apprehend how <hi>Infinit Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> can ſtand together: Behold in the wonderful Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Man, <hi>Juſtice</hi> Requires <hi>full ſatisfaction:</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> Finds it: And thus the <hi>Attributes</hi> of God <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt</hi> and <hi>Magnify</hi> one Another; One Raiſes the other to the Height, and each Exert themſelves to the utmoſt, that is, <hi>Infinitly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Dr. B. ſays, Ibid. p. 135. <hi>That the Scripture ſets none of theſe ſpeculations before.</hi> What! Does not the <hi>Scripture</hi> tell us that God is <hi>Juſt?</hi> and theſe Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations are but Neceſſary Inferences from the Nature of <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But even as to the <hi>Exactneſs</hi> of God's <hi>Justice.</hi> Does the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſay nothing to give us a true and high Idea of it? God's Juſtice is there repreſented as exacting the <hi>utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Farthing</hi> (what ſtricter Notion of <hi>Juſtice?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.26. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.7.</note>) as <hi>Conſuming Fire. Burning Jealouſie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.36. <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.53.44.</note> 
               <hi>that will by no means clear the Guilty, of purer Eyes than to behold Evil, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not look on Iniquity.</hi> Who will take an <hi>Account</hi> of every <hi>idle word. A Worm that never dies, and a Fire that never ſhall be quenched.</hi> Whatever Dr. <hi>T.</hi> and his Brother <hi>B.</hi> have laboured to the contrary; to perſuade the World, in the words of the firſt Deceiver, that tho' ye ſin, <hi>yet ye ſhall not</hi> ſurely <hi>die.</hi> Gen. 3.4. Notwithſtanding that the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> has ſaid ſo in plain Terms That the <hi>Fire</hi> of <hi>Hell,</hi> that is, of God's <hi>Justice</hi> is <hi>everlaſting,</hi> ſhall <hi>never</hi> be quenched; yet theſe <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctors</hi> would have you venture againſt all this, a pretty diſtinction they have found out (of which the <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly Scriptures</hi> are totally ſilent) that <hi>Remunerative</hi> but not <hi>puniſhing</hi> Juſtice is Eſſential to God. Which is the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound-work of Dr. <hi>T's</hi> Sermon againſt the Truth of Hells <hi>Eternity.</hi> And repeated here by Dr. <hi>B.</hi> p. 135. and yet, in the very ſame Breath, he pretends to anſwer all the Arguments brought from God's <hi>Juſtice,</hi> by ſaying, <hi>That the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſets nine of theſe Speculations before us.</hi> Whereas Dr. <hi>T.</hi> does plainly confeſs in his above ſaid Sermon of <hi>Hell;</hi> That there is no ground or light in the World ſo much as to be expected from the <hi>Scripture,</hi> to ſupport his Hypotheſis of the <hi>No-certainty</hi> of <hi>Hell;</hi> and he gives a Reaſon for it. Becauſe, ſays he, leſs than the threatening <hi>Eternal</hi> puniſhment was not ſufficient to deter Men from ſin; and therefore that in the ſame <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation</hi> which told us of the <hi>Eternity</hi> of <hi>Hell,</hi> it was not to be expected that we ſhould find any thing which ſhould give the leaſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbrage</hi> to the contrary. This is very <hi>ſubtile!</hi> But then it would be enquired how theſe <hi>Doctors</hi> came by it, ſince they confeſs there is not the leaſt footſtep to be found of it in <hi>Scripture?</hi> Dr. <hi>T.</hi> in the aforeſaid Sermon does allow, for the above Reaſon, that God did, by his wording of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign that Men ſhould believe the <hi>Eternity</hi> of Hell, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which the threatening of it had been to no effect. It ſeems then that God could not keep it from theſe <hi>Doctors!</hi> But if they were either too <hi>Wiſe</hi> for <hi>God</hi>'s de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, or could not be <hi>Impos'd</hi> by God like other Men; or that God did, by a particular Revelation, diſcover the mighty ſecret to theſe Men, ſure it was not with a deſign that all the World ſhould know it; For, as the <hi>Dr.</hi> ſays, the contrivance of concealing it, in Scripture, was on purpoſe, leſt <hi>Mankind</hi> ſhould know it, or have the leaſt ſuſpicion of it; but that they ſhould believe the <hi>Eternity</hi> of Hell, to keep them to their Duty, I ſay, if theſe <hi>Doctors</hi> were ſo <hi>perfect</hi> as not to need ſuch an <hi>Awe</hi> upon them; and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God had opened their Eyes; Why would they <hi>Blabb</hi> this, and ſpoyl God's deſign, upon other Men? I dare ſay, he will tell them no more Secrets for this trick.</p>
            <p>It terrifies me while I muſt expoſe the wicked pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of theſe <hi>Blaſphemers.</hi> Who when God has ſaid plainly, That Hell is <hi>Eternal;</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi> has aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured us, as a true <hi>Doctor</hi> and <hi>Teacher</hi> of his Church, That the Fire ſhall <hi>never</hi> be quenched, would perſuade
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53033:14"/>us to believe <hi>Them</hi> contrary to all this; whereby they plainly inſinuate that they are wiſer than God: or deſign better for Mankind, in revealing to us, what they confeſs, God would have kept ſecret.</p>
            <p>And, to carry on the Argument of their Folly, that they ſhould object againſt the <hi>Christian Doctrine,</hi> That, as they ſay, it is not told plain enough in Scripture, when they confeſs their own to have no foundation at all in <hi>Scripture,</hi> They think they have a right to call God to an Account for his <hi>Remunerating</hi> Juſtice, to perform his <hi>Promiſes</hi> to them, and that this is <hi>Eſſential</hi> to his very <hi>Nature:</hi> But not ſo of his <hi>Puniſhing</hi> Juſtice: They will not have that to belong at all to the nature of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> tho' they can give no other Reaſon, than their not deſiring it. For I am confident there is hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Man in the World but thinks that <hi>Pun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhing</hi> as well as <hi>Rewarding</hi> does belong to the Nature of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</hi> It is a Principle as ſelt-evident, and rooted in the firſt Notions of Men as any whatſoever that can be named. So that theſe <hi>Doctors</hi> will find <hi>Reaſon</hi> as much their Enemy as <hi>Revelation,</hi> and it is a juſt Judgment that thoſe who proſumptuouſly go againſt the latter, ſhould diſcover their extreme folly in the other, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they boaſt themſelves.</p>
            <p>And this they do, with all their <hi>Socinian</hi> Brethren in moſt palpable manner, by the account they give of the <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> For upon their ground of the <hi>no neceſſity</hi> to <hi>ſatisfie</hi> God's <hi>Justice</hi> for ſin. They cannot find out any Reaſon why he ſhould <hi>die.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time they ſay to confirm the Truth of his Doctrine. But that does not confirm it, or ſay any more than that he was fully perſuaded of it himſelf. For Men have <hi>died</hi> for <hi>Errors.</hi> And <hi>Christ</hi> vouch'd his <hi>Miracles,</hi> not his <hi>Death,</hi> to confirm the Truth of his Doctrine.</p>
            <p>At other times, they ſay, It war only to ſhew God's Abhorrence to ſin. How! To <hi>excuſe</hi> the <hi>Guilty,</hi> and <hi>puniſh</hi> the <hi>Innocent!</hi> This, upon their way of Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhews rather God's <hi>acceptance</hi> of <hi>ſin,</hi> and <hi>abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> of <hi>Innocence.</hi> Were it not more reaſonable what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.18. That <hi>the Wicked ſhould be a Ranſom for the Righteous, and the Tranſgreſſors for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright?</hi> Or as he otherwiſe words it, <hi>Ch.</hi> 11.8. <hi>The Righteous is delivered out of trouble, and the Wicked cometh in his ſtead.</hi> Is not this more <hi>Juſtice</hi> than that the <hi>Righteous</hi> ſhould be puniſhed <hi>in the ſtead</hi> of the <hi>Wicked?</hi> It cannot ſtand with <hi>Juſtice</hi> any other way than upon the Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> nor can the <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> be otherwiſe rationally accounted for.</p>
            <p>In ſhort the <hi>Socinians</hi> can find no Reaſon for it that has the leaſt Pretence. And therefore they ſettle here as I have ſhew'n above. That God made a <hi>Covenant</hi> with <hi>Christ</hi> (tho for what Reaſon they do not know) to Remit the Sins of the <hi>Penitent,</hi> if he would ſuffer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be murdered, by thoſe whoſe ſins were to be Remitted by virtue of that <hi>Murder.</hi> They ſay there was no <hi>need</hi> for any ſuch <hi>Covenant,</hi> for that God might have Remitted ſins without it, or without any <hi>Covenant,</hi> or upon any ſort of Covenant. For as Dr. <hi>B.</hi> Says. p. 151. <hi>It is the Appointment and the Acceptation that makes the Satisfaction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then if the <hi>Appointment</hi> and <hi>Acceptation</hi> of the Sacrifice of a <hi>Bullock</hi> could have made <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> what need was there for <hi>Christ</hi> being <hi>Sacrificed?</hi> Why, no need at all, ſay our <hi>Dr's.</hi> that we can tell: But we find in Scripture oft Mention of Gods <hi>Covenant</hi> in <hi>Christ</hi> and we ſuppoſe this to be it.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Siripture</hi> gives a quite different account of it, <hi>viz.</hi> That in order to Remiſſion, there was a <hi>neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> for Chriſt's Suffering. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.46. That it <hi>beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> Him to Suffer, Becauſe <hi>it was not poſſible that the Blood of Bulls and of Goats ſhould take away ſins.</hi> Heb. 10.4. c. 7.13. That there was a <hi>diſanulling</hi> of the Legal Commandments and Inſtitution, not for want of <hi>Appointment,</hi> (for they were <hi>Appointed</hi>) but <hi>for the weakneſs and unprofitableneſs thereof.</hi> Here reſpect is had to the <hi>Nature</hi> of the <hi>means,</hi> and not only to the <hi>Appointment.</hi> Rom. 8.3. <hi>For what the Law cannot do, in that it was weak through the Fleſh, God ſending his own Son in the likeneſs of ſinful Fleſh, and for ſin, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns ſin in the Fleſh.</hi> Gal. 3.21. <hi>For if there had been a Law given which could have given Life, verily Righteouſneſs ſhould have been by the Law— For if Righteouſneſs came by the Law, then Chriſt is dead in vain.</hi> c. 2.21. And <hi>in vain</hi> did He die, for all the account theſe Men give of it, or can give, upon theſe <hi>Socinian</hi> Poinciples which they maintain.</p>
            <p>And they bewray their Erros to that degree, that ſometime they fall foul upon God's <hi>Juſtice,</hi> for ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Christ</hi> an <hi>Innocent</hi> Perſon to die. Thus Dr. <hi>B.</hi> p. 148. ſays that <hi>Chriſt</hi> had <hi>nothing to fear from a Juſt and Good God.</hi> Why? becauſe he was <hi>conſcious to him ſelf of no ſin. And therefore,</hi> he ſays, <hi>he cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend what could have rais'd ſuch amazing ſorrows in ſo pure and unſpotted a Soul that was conſcious to it ſelf of no ſin, and ſo could fear nothing from a Juſt and Good God, and therefore,</hi> ſays he, <hi>we muſt not pretend to explain what we cannot understand.</hi> But if he could have underſtood <hi>Chriſt</hi> then laying under the weight of all the ſins of the World, which he had undertaken, as our <hi>Surety</hi> to anſwer for, and <hi>ſatisfie</hi> the utmoſt demand of God's <hi>Justice</hi> for them, he would have found the reaſon of that unexpreſſible <hi>Agony</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> our Redeemer, who had an <hi>Adequat</hi> Notion of the <hi>Infinite</hi> demerit of <hi>Sin,</hi> and what was due to it; and had taken it all upon himſelf, and was to preſent to God a <hi>Senſe</hi> and a <hi>Sorrow</hi> for it, fully propotrionable to the whole Offence, which all the <hi>Damned</hi> in <hi>Hell</hi> can never do; No, nor all <hi>Creatures;</hi> for they are not all able to comprehend the full <hi>Heinouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Obliquity</hi> of an Offence againſt an <hi>Infinit</hi> Being. And when we conceive ſuch an <hi>Infinit Sorrow</hi> lodg'd in the Soul of <hi>Christ,</hi> and ſo ſtrong a <hi>ſenſe</hi> of the <hi>hatefulneſs</hi> of <hi>Sin,</hi> and its <hi>Monstrous Deformity,</hi> and of the full <hi>Wrath</hi> of <hi>God</hi> which lay upon that <hi>Accurſed</hi> or <hi>Devoted</hi> Head who was to anſwer for it, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. ſuch a <hi>Senſe,</hi> I ſay, and a <hi>Sorrow</hi> (which is always proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to the <hi>Senſe</hi> we have of the ſin) as all the Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities of all Creatures to Eternity were not large e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to contain; when we perceive <hi>Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Saviour</hi> under ſuch a <hi>Sorrow</hi> and <hi>Appreherſion</hi> as this, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not wonder at his ſo terrible an <hi>Agony.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:53033:14"/>
            <p>But indeed, without this conſideration of Chriſt's <hi>ſatisfying</hi> the <hi>Justice</hi> of <hi>God</hi> for our <hi>Sins,</hi> there can be no account given of his <hi>Agony.</hi> It is altogether unintel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible, as Dr. <hi>B.</hi> ſays. For he had no ſin of his own to anſwer for, and unleſs we ſuppoſe that he took our ſin upon himſelf, he had nothing (according to Dr. <hi>B.</hi>) to fear from a <hi>Juſt</hi> God. And Dr. <hi>B.</hi> denying the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of any <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> to be made to <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and conſequently thinking that Chriſt did not make any <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> or that our Sins were laid upon him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently muſt think that as <hi>Chriſt</hi> had nothing to fear from a <hi>Juſt</hi> God, ſo that God was not <hi>Juſt</hi> in inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Death</hi> upon <hi>Chriſt.</hi> elſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> had ſomething to fear from a <hi>Just</hi> God.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>T.</hi> likewiſe runs into the ſame ſtrain, in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon before ſpoke of <hi>concerning the Sacrifice and Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of Christ,</hi> wondering at the great Severity ſhewed to Chriſt, he ſays p. 34. That God ſeemed, in that, to have gone <hi>almoſt further than</hi> Goodneſs <hi>and</hi> Juſtice <hi>could well admit; to afflict</hi> Innocency <hi>it ſelf, to ſave the</hi> Guilty— And, <hi>that it looked almost like hatred of</hi> INNOCENCY <hi>and bis onely Son.</hi> Now to <hi>almoſt ordoubt</hi> of God's JUSTICE or GOODNESS, is next door, if not the ſame as <hi>denying</hi> it: Becauſe God is a <hi>Neceſſary</hi> Being; if this <hi>Being,</hi> or if any <hi>Attribute</hi> he had were <hi>doubtful,</hi> he could not be God: therefore to <hi>doubt</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> or of any of his <hi>Attributes,</hi> is <hi>almost</hi> and <hi>alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether</hi> not to <hi>believe</hi> a God.</p>
            <p>To ſuch ſtraits are theſe Men driven, who would give an Account of the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> without the Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction.</hi> I will end this Diſcourſe with ſhewing that the <hi>Doctrine of Satisfaction</hi> as I have ſet it down, is ſtrictly purſuant to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and conſequently, That theſe Doctors <hi>T.</hi> and <hi>B.</hi> have <hi>Apoſtatized</hi> from that Church, and from that very Doctrine, which they once profeſſed. Therefore my Proof ſhall be out of the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> and the <hi>Homilies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt for the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> in the <hi>Prayer of Conſecration</hi> of the Elements of the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> it is ſaid that Chriſt made, upon the Croſs, a <hi>Full, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and Sufficient Sacrifice, Oblation, and</hi> Satisfaction <hi>for the ſins of the whole World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the firſt <hi>Homily</hi> for <hi>Good-Friday</hi> it is expreſly ſaid, That <hi>without Payment</hi> (of our Debt by Sin) <hi>God the Father could never be at one with us.</hi> And through all that and the following <hi>Homily,</hi> it is inſiſted on as neceſſary to the Pardon of Sin, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf ſhould come down from Heaven, be <hi>Incarnat</hi> and <hi>Dis;</hi> and that no <hi>Prophet</hi> or <hi>Angel,</hi> or leſs than the Eternal Son of God, could have wrought our Deliverance. And this is agreeable to the Scripture Language, as before told: That Chriſt OUGHT <hi>to have ſuffered;</hi> that it BEHOVED <hi>Him to ſuffer.</hi> Luke 24.26.46. <hi>That thus it</hi> MUST <hi>be.</hi> Mat. 26.54.39. That it was not POSSIBLE <hi>the Cup ſhould paſs from Him,</hi> if He wou'd compleat the Redemption of Man.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Homily of the Salvation of Mankind,</hi> &amp;c. you have theſe words. <hi>God ſent his Son— to fulfill the Law for us, and by ſhedding his moſt precious Blood to make a Sacrifice and</hi> Satisfaction, <hi>or (as it may be called)</hi> Amends <hi>to his Father for our ſins— And whereas i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lay not in us to do that, he provided a Ranſom for us— And ſo the Juſtice of God and his Mercy did embrace to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and fulfilled the Myſtery of our Redemption.</hi> He would not <hi>by his Mercy deliver us clearly, without</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice <hi>or Payment of a Juſt</hi> Ranſom, <hi>but with his endleſs</hi> Mercy <hi>he joyned his moſt upright and equal</hi> Juſtice— <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon</hi> God's <hi>part, his Great</hi> Mercy <hi>and</hi> Grace, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon</hi> Chriſt's <hi>part,</hi> Juſtice, <hi>that is, the</hi> Satisfaction <hi>of God's</hi> Juſtice— <hi>So that in our</hi> Juſtification <hi>there is not only God's</hi> Mercy <hi>and</hi> Grace, <hi>but alſo his</hi> Juſtice— <hi>The</hi> Grace <hi>of God doth not ſhut out the</hi> Juſtice <hi>of God in our</hi> Juſtification— And <hi>whereas all the World was not able of themſelves to pay any part toward their Ranſom. It pleaſed our Heavenly Father of his Infinite Mercy without any of our deſert or deſerving, to propare for us the moſt precious Jewels of Chriſt's Body and Blood; whereby our</hi> Ranſom <hi>might be fully paid, the Law fulfilled, and his</hi> Juſtice <hi>fully</hi> ſatisfied. <hi>This Faith the Holy Scripture teaches us, is the ſtrong Rock and Foundation of Chriſtian Religion. This Doctrine all Old and Ancient Authors of Christ's Church do approve; This Doctrine advanceth and ſetteth forth the true Glory of Chriſt, and beateth down the vain Glory of Man, this whoſoever denieth, is not to be accounted for</hi> a Chriſtian Man— <hi>but for an Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to</hi> Chriſt <hi>and his</hi> Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Yet theſe Adverſaries <hi>Rear in the midſt of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, and ſet up their Banners for Takens.</hi> O God, in what a Condition is this poor <hi>Church,</hi> theſe miſerable, miſled People of <hi>England</hi> when ſuch Doctrine is taught from the <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>Canterbury!</hi> When Addreſſes are made to the <hi>Clergy by</hi> their <hi>Biſhops,</hi> publickly and in Print, to teach and propagate theſe <hi>Damnable Hereſies!</hi> When theſe Men are made <hi>Primates</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> of our Church, whom our <hi>Homilies</hi> think not fit to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as <hi>Christian Men,</hi> but <hi>Adverſaries</hi> to <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Goſpel! The whole Head is ſick, and the whole Hears faint!</hi> It is for the fins of theſe Nations, that ſuch <hi>Prieſts</hi> are ſent to them, according to the words of the Prophet, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.9. <hi>There ſhall be like People like Prieſt.</hi> 9.7. <hi>The Prophet is a Fool, the Spiritual Man is Mad, for the multitude of thine Iniquity, and the great Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred—</hi> 8. <hi>The Prophet is a ſnare of a Fowler in all his ways, and Hatred in the Houſe of his God.</hi> Jer. 23.9. <hi>My Heart within me is broken, becauſe of the Prophets. all my Bones ſhake— For the Land is full of Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, for becauſe of</hi> SWEARING, <hi>the Land mourneth—</hi> 5.31. <hi>Their cauſe is Evil, and their force is not Right. A wonderful and horrible thing is committed in the Land. The Prophets Propheſy falſly, and the Prieſts bear Rule by their means, and my People love to have it ſo, and what will ye do in the end thereof.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:53033:15"/>
            <head>POSTSCRPT.</head>
            <p>I Am the more encouraged in what I have here un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, that Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> who formerly was ſo rankly <hi>Socinian</hi> as to the Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> not only to <hi>Blaſpheme</hi> but <hi>Ridicule</hi> it, as Dr. <hi>S.</hi> has ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewn from his Book of the <hi>Knowledge of Chriſt,</hi> has now at laſt come off from theſe two Doctors, and Diſputed expreſly againſt them, upon this point, and anſwered their Arguments againſt the Doctrine of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction,</hi> in his Sermon Peached at <hi>White-Hall</hi> laſt <hi>Trinity Sunday,</hi> 1694. which it is much deſired that he would Publiſh, tho' he could get no <hi>Licenſe</hi> from <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</hi> It gave great ſatisfaction to many of his Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, from ſome of whom I had a very good Account of it. Particularly in anſwer to Dr. <hi>T's</hi> main, and (he thinks) unanſwerable Objection, where he <hi>Dares any Man to ſay that God could'not ſave Man otherwiſe than by the Death</hi> or <hi>Satisfaction of Christ.</hi> To which Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> Reply'd (as it was Repreſented to me) that if this was underſtood of any Compulſion from without, God could not be <hi>Compell'd</hi> or <hi>Oblig'd</hi> in any Caſe: But if the neceſſity proceeded from what is <hi>Internal,</hi> and conſequently <hi>Eternal</hi> in God, that is his <hi>Justice,</hi> it was no <hi>Imperfection</hi> to ſuppoſe ſuch a <hi>Neceſſity</hi> in God of requiring <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> &amp;c. But I will not Anticipate, nor Prejudice the Dr. We deſire it in his own words.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="supplement">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:53033:15"/>
            <head>A <hi>SUPPLEMENT</hi> upon Occaſion of <hi>A Hiſtory of Religion</hi> lately Publiſhed, ſuppoſed to be Wrote by Sir <hi>R.H—d.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Wherein likewiſe <hi>Charles Blount</hi>'s <hi>GREAT DIANA</hi> is Conſidered; And both Compar'd with Dr. <hi>TILLOTSON's Sermons</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis comes to you upon occaſion of a Book Publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this year 94. ſince the foregoing <hi>Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> were wrote. It is call'd, <hi>A Hiſtory of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> And gives a like account of <hi>Religion</hi> as what I have already told out of Dr. <hi>Till.</hi> but in ſomewhat another Form. And it quotes him with great Applauſe in the Preface, as the true Pattern of Orthodox Divinity; that is, ſuch Principles as he there ſets forth; and ſo much in the Doctor's Stile and Air, that if he be not the Author, it comes from ſome of his Diſciples that have Copy'd after him very exactly.</p>
            <p>He Ridicules all <hi>Reveal</hi>'d Religion, and turns it into what he calls <hi>Priest-Craft;</hi> This was but borrowed from a work of that Execrable <hi>Charles Blount,</hi> one of the Atheiſtical Club, and very intimate with Dr. <hi>Tillotſon.</hi> It was Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>London Anno</hi> 1680. and is Intituled, <hi>Great is</hi> Diana <hi>of the</hi> Epheſians, Or, <hi>The Original of Idolatry, together with the Politick Inſtitution of the</hi> Gentiles <hi>Sacrifices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Deſign and whole Import of that Book, is under the Name of the <hi>Gentile</hi> Sacrifices, and Religion, to Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme, and, like a <hi>Mad Dog,</hi> to Curſe and Reproach the whole Inſtitution of God, as well under the <hi>Law</hi> as the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> And he Builds upon the very ſame Foundation as Dr. <hi>Till.</hi> in the Sermons above Quoted, of <hi>Sacrifices</hi> and all the other Inſtitutions of <hi>Revealed</hi> Religion, being meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an Invention of Men. Though he does not go the length of his Maſter Dr. <hi>Till.</hi> to make the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and other Inſtitutions of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, to be only a <hi>Complyance</hi> with the <hi>Wicked</hi> and <hi>Diabolical</hi> Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Men, in their Bloody Sacrifices of Beaſts and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Kind, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that you may ſee the Thread and Progreſs of this horrid <hi>Maſtery of Iniquity</hi> (the like ſure never known or <hi>Tolerated</hi> in any <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Countrey) let me give you a ſhort view of this Book of <hi>Blounts:</hi> Then I will ſhew how this new <hi>History of Religion</hi> agreet with it, or was taken out of it: And how exactly both do ſquare with Dr. <hi>T's</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Scheme of <hi>Religion,</hi> which I have laid down in the Diſcourſe going before.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Blount</hi> makes it known, That there are no <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> in their Religion, for he tells you Sect. 11. p. 23. That <hi>they are too wiſe to hazard their own Ruin for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of fooliſh Men— knowing that if any Man ſhould be ſo vain, as to oppoſe the Common Belief, the</hi> Mobile <hi>would</hi> (<hi>as they did to</hi> Socrates) <hi>Oppreſi and decry him for an</hi> Atheiſt. <hi>Therefore the Wiſeſt among the Heathens followed this Rule, in their Converſe.</hi> LOQUENDUM CUM VULGO, SENTIENDUM CUM SAPIENTIBUS, SI MUNDUS VULT DECIPI, DECIPIATUR.</p>
            <p>And, in the next words, he Blaſphemouſly brings in our <hi>Saviour</hi> as obſerving the ſame Poor and Wicked Craft, and that this was his Reaſon for ſpeaking to the People in <hi>Parables.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He Inſtances almoſt in every Circumſtance of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's <hi>Life,</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> his <hi>Miracles</hi> and Proofs of his <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity;</hi> by telling over the Story, in ſomething that he finds or makes like it among the <hi>Heathens;</hi> and for which he gives all the ill Names can be to the <hi>Heathen</hi> Worſhip, as being contradictory to Reaſon, with a <hi>But</hi> the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is not ſo— when he has made them the very ſame, and no more Grounds for believing the one than the other, and that ſo plainly, that none who have but half an Eye can help ſeeing that the whole is meant to Ridicule and Blaſpheme the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, in this moſt Malicious and Provoking manner. p. 39. He thus Ridicules our Commemoration of Chriſt in the Bleſſed Sacrament. <hi>As all Entertainments</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the Company are apt to drink the Founder's Health.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The whole Book, from beginning to ending, is of the ſame ſtrain, that I muſt Tranſcribe it all if I ſhould under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to ſet down all his <hi>Blaſphemies</hi> and <hi>Prophaneneſs.</hi> And I am very glad to be releaſed from the Repetition of ſuch Wickedneſs as curdles my Blood, and ſhakes all my Frame. And the leſs that others hear of it the better. Would God it had never been heard or wrote, that there might have been no neceſſity of ever mentioning of it.</p>
            <p>Having thus made <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf to be <hi>Belzebub.</hi> the <hi>Great Deceiver,</hi> you cannot expect he ſhould treat his <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Servants</hi> better than their <hi>Maſter.</hi> And indeed he deals more roundly with them. He ſpares not to Name them plainly and above board. By which he puts it out of doubt that it was the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion which he Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels through all this Book. <hi>Sect.</hi> 18. Telling one of the <hi>Politick</hi> Ends of the Inſtitution of <hi>Sanguinary Sacrifices,</hi> to be the enuring People to <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Blood:</hi> But, ſays he, p. 45. <hi>The Primitive Church</hi> did prohibit the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſuch Bloody Sights, they choſe another way, <hi>i e. To Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern in the Spirit of Meekneſs and Innocence, Hopeing thereby to gain a greater Submiſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that <hi>Ambition</hi> was the whole End of all that <hi>Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Innocency,</hi> which is taught in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion— <hi>Hopeing thereby to gain a Greater Submiſſion!</hi> And
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53033:16"/>this he meant againſt <hi>Chriſt Himſelf,</hi> tho' <hi>Here</hi> he only names the <hi>Primitive Church:</hi> for <hi>Chriſt</hi> firſt taught that <hi>Meekneſs</hi> and <hi>Innocency</hi> which they afterwards Preach'd; and He was the <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> whom this <hi>Black Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del</hi> traduces; and he downright names the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that you may know againſt whom he writes. And that not only theſe later corrupted Times, but the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> in which the Times of <hi>Christ</hi> and the <hi>Apostles</hi> are included: And it is of theſe, and all other <hi>Chriſtian Prieſts,</hi> that he means what he ſays in the ſame page, under his <hi>Cobweb</hi> Vell of the <hi>Heathen Prieſts, who were certainly</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the Wickedeſt and the Craftieſt of Men.</hi> You muſt know he never Convers'd with any in his life, except Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> (becauſe he was a <hi>Politician</hi>) and thoſe of his Recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 10. p. 22. He argues againſt <hi>Future Puniſhments</hi> (but not <hi>Rewards</hi>) at leaſt the <hi>Eternity</hi> of them. (Exact Dr. <hi>Tilletſon</hi>'s Notion in his Sermon of <hi>Hell</hi> before ſpoke of) and Diſputes (as Dr. <hi>T.</hi> does; as If they were inconſiſtent with the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of God. And from their <hi>Inviſibility</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainty;</hi> He makes them nothing elſe but the Invention of <hi>Government</hi> to keep their Subjects in Awe. Which Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> words (in the ſaid Sermon of <hi>Hell</hi>) That God is under no other Obligation to <hi>Juſtice</hi> (or the <hi>Proportioning</hi> the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> to the <hi>Crime</hi>) than ſo far as it may tend to ſecure His <hi>Government.</hi> Nay, he ſays, that to <hi>Proportion</hi> the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> to the <hi>Crime,</hi> does not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to <hi>Justice</hi> at all, but is only a Conſideration of <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> to ſecure <hi>Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus while theſe bold <hi>Miſcreants</hi> are ſtraining their Wit to turn all <hi>Revealed</hi> Religion into <hi>Prieſt-Craft;</hi> they have reduced the whole Notion of <hi>Juſtice</hi> (which is <hi>God,</hi> who is juſtice in the Abſtract) into nothing elſe but a piece of <hi>State-Craft!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And have, in all their lewd Harangues, but Copied af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the old <hi>Roman</hi> Atheiſts. <hi>Primos in orbe Deos Timor fecit.</hi> Which <hi>Blount</hi> repeats in the ſame page above quoted, in theſe words, <hi>Animo tortore Eagellum.</hi> And having made the Belief of Eternal Puniſhments to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Goodneſs of God, and ſo <hi>Irrational,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together <hi>Pracarious,</hi> as being <hi>Inviſible</hi> and Imperceptible by any <hi>Natural</hi> means, he t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en, in his Method above-told, lays the Abſurdity upon the belief of the <hi>Stygian-Lake.</hi> But, <hi>So Rational</hi> (ſays he, thruſting out his Tongue) <hi>and ſo Natural is that Article of our</hi> Chriſtian <hi>Faith!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In like manner he deals with the Inſtitution of <hi>Sacrifices.</hi> Sect. 7. p. 15. which <hi>Superſtition</hi> (as he calls it) <hi>ſuffers neither God nor Man to live at reſt, as evidently appears by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe</hi> Heathen <hi>Sacrifices.</hi> But inſtead of Reproving them for that wherein only they were faulty, ſo far as they were Aberrations from the <hi>Divine Institution,</hi> and were Offer'd to <hi>Devils</hi> and not to God; I ſay, inſtead of this, he vents ſuch Reaſons againſt them as equally involve the Sacrifices of the <hi>Jews</hi> which were made to God, and by him Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; and conſequently the Sacrifice of <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord. This <hi>Wild Beaſt</hi>'s Reaſons againſt <hi>Sacriſices</hi> are in the words Immediately following thoſe above quoted, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q> What could be more Sottiſh and Irational, than to think that the ſlaughter of a poor Innocent Creature (who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the ſimplicity or his own Nature, without ever offending God) ſhould be ſo Grateful to the Deity, as thereby we might Expiate our Sins, and render a ſufficient Attonement for the moſt exerable Villanlei of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind? As if the Almighty Juſtice could be no otherwiſe appeaſed for the Errors of the Wicked, but by the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of the Innocent.</q> [<hi>This I deſire his Tutor Dr.</hi> T. <hi>to Anſwer, upon his Scheme of no Satisfaction being due to the</hi> JUSTICE <hi>of</hi> GOD <hi>for our Sins But</hi> Blount <hi>goes on.</hi>] <q> Now as Sacrifices were the moſt Ancient and Univerſal, ſo the Greateſt and moſt Myſterious Fourbs that ever were invented, or impoſed upon. Mankind. What have Sacrifices to do with Sins? Could none but their Enlightned Prieſts make Peace between God and Man, when Sins were committed?</q> Thus <hi>Blount.</hi> And in what follows, he tells you what he would be at. That is, to throw off all outward Ordinances, <hi>Sacrifices, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> &amp;c. and reſolve all to Inward Repentance. Which is the very Notion of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> whither his great Wit has carried him.</p>
            <p>Now I will ſhew you how he agrees with his Tutor in all this. I will ſet down their words over againſt one another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As if</hi> (ſays <hi>Blount,</hi> as above quoted) <hi>the Almighty Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice could be no otherwiſe appeaſed for the Errors of the Wicked, but by the Sufferings of the Innocent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In this Diſpenſation</hi> (ſays <hi>Tillotſon</hi> as before quoted, in his Sermon of the Sacrifice and Satisfaction of Chriſt p. 34.) <hi>of God's Grace and Mercy to Mankind, by the Death of his Son, God ſeems to have gone to the very Extremity of things, and almost further than Goodneſs and Juſtice will well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit; to afflict Innocency it ſelf, to ſave the Guilty— It looks almoſt like Hatred of Innocency and his own Son.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe two <hi>Almoſts,</hi> are like two Greek <hi>Negatives,</hi> which make an <hi>Affirmative.</hi> And ſhew this <hi>Dr.</hi> to be both al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, and altogether ſuch a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> as his Diſciple <hi>Blount.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed, without the Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> there can no Rational account be given for the <hi>Typical</hi> Sacrifices before <hi>Chriſt</hi> came, and much leſs for <hi>His</hi> Sacrifice, who was <hi>Innocency</hi> it ſelf. But, according to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> He could not otherwiſe have been an <hi>Expiato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sacrifice</hi> for <hi>Sin:</hi> And God's <hi>Mercy</hi> and His <hi>Juſtice</hi> do equally Magnifie one another in this <hi>Glorious</hi> and moſt <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional</hi> Diſpenſation. But this has been diſcourſed in the foregoing <hi>Obſervations.</hi> Wherein has been ſhewn, that Dr. <hi>Tidotſon</hi>'s Account of the <hi>Legal</hi> Sacrifices, it as <hi>Athei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical</hi> and <hi>Prophane</hi> as this which I have quoted out of <hi>Blount.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both of them agree that this was a Trick and Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Invention of Wicked and Fooliſh Men. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Dr. T.</hi> gets, I think, beyond <hi>Blount;</hi> where he makes the <hi>Jewiſh Religion</hi> and <hi>Sacrifices</hi> (as well as the <hi>Chriſtian</hi>) to be a Compliance in God with all this Barbarous Wickedneſs. <hi>And indeed</hi> (ſays he, in the above quoted Sermon of the Sacrifice and Satisfaction of Chriſt, p. 6.) <hi>a very great part of the</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Religion, which was Instituted by God Himſelf, ſeems to have been a plain Condeſcenſion to the General. Apprehenſion of Mankind, concerning this way of appeaſing the Offended Deity with Sacrifices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the moſt <hi>Irrational</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemous</hi> Account which thoſe who deny the <hi>Satisfaction</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (becauſe as they pretend, againſt their <hi>Reaſon</hi>) are forc'd to give of the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> [But I have Treated largely of this elſewhere.] And while they ſet up for the only Men of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> they have ſhewn themſelves utterly Uncapable of <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:53033:16"/>
            <p>To think (as <hi>Blount</hi> here) that there was no other End or Deſign in God's Inſtitution of <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> but the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure he took in the death of a <hi>Beaſt!</hi> How blind and wretched is the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of ſuch Men! How totally Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the Great Deſigns of God! Of the Glorious and ever Adorable Methods of His <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> in the Redemption of loſt Mankind! In the <hi>Satisfaction</hi> of His Infinite and exact Juſtice! Together with the Exaltation of equal Infinit <hi>Mercy!</hi> Which things the <hi>Angels</hi> delight to look into; but the wicked Arrogance of poor miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Men preſume madly to Blaſpheme; meaſuring the Eternal <hi>Wiſdom</hi> by their ſhort Plummet! Void of <hi>common ſenſe,</hi> as well as <hi>modesty,</hi> or any <hi>Reverence</hi> to that <hi>Being,</hi> whom, in words, they own to be <hi>Almighty</hi> and <hi>Incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How juſt is it in God to ſuffer theſe Men to Expoſe themſelves moſt ſhamefully, even in the point of <hi>Reaſon;</hi> their <hi>Great Diana,</hi> wherein they ſo vainly magnifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves!</p>
            <p>Which appears, very plainly, in the preſent Caſe, of the Account they give of the <hi>Original</hi> of <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> and the <hi>Poſſitive</hi> Inſtitutions of <hi>Revealed</hi> Religion. <hi>Perhaps</hi> (ſays <hi>Blount</hi> ibid. Sect. 8. p. 17.) <hi>Melancholly Men might at first ſight upon this Frenzy,</hi> He means of <hi>Sacrifices</hi> (calling the Inſtitution of God, after the <hi>Delirium</hi> of his own Brain, a <hi>Melancholly Frenzy</hi>) and the higheſt he can derive <hi>Sacrifices</hi> is from the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> among whom, he ſays, they were firſt uſed, and from them deriv'd to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> (Sect. 15. p. 39) as if he had never heard, or did not believe, that <hi>Cain, Abel,</hi> and <hi>Noah,</hi> Sacrificed, long before there were either <hi>Hebrews</hi> or <hi>Egyptians</hi> in the World. If he lay no greater ſtreſs upon the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> than upon other Common Hyſtories, this muſt betray the moſt ſtupid or wilful <hi>Ignorance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is nothing more plain than how the <hi>Heathen</hi> came to the Knowledge of <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> viz. That <hi>Cain,</hi> tho' he corrupted the True Religion, yet preſerved the <hi>Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and deriv'd that Worſhip of <hi>Sacrifices</hi> to his Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: Tho', in proceſs of time, they forgot both the <hi>Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> and the true <hi>Ends</hi> of it; as they did of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World, or their own <hi>Origination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But they preſerv'd, along with the <hi>Sacrifices</hi> ſo much of the true Import and Meaning of them, and of that to which they pointed, which was the <hi>Expiatory</hi> Sacrifice of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that they retain'd a Traditionary Belief of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a <hi>Vicarious</hi> ſuffering for Sin: which was a ſort of implicit and dark Falth in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> tho' they knew him not, nor had any true Notion of him; as the generality of the <hi>Jews</hi> had not, no nor the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves till after the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>How far this Intitl'd theſe very <hi>Heathens</hi> to a degree of <hi>Faith</hi> in <hi>Christ,</hi> and of Salvability by it, at leaſt, till He was Preach'd, and more plainly Exhibited to them, I will not now diſpure. The ways of God are unſearchable, and with Reverence to the Ador'd, even where they exceed our Underſtandings. But thus much we may conclude from hence, that the Repreſentation which I have ſhewn above <hi>Dr. T.</hi> has given of the <hi>Heathen</hi> Notion of a <hi>Vica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rious</hi> Suffering, as a <hi>Fooliſh</hi> and <hi>Wicked</hi> Notion, <hi>Ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,</hi> and of their own <hi>Fancy:</hi> And then his making this the <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Foundation</hi> of the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as a <hi>Gratification</hi> and <hi>Compliance</hi> with ſuch <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable</hi> and <hi>Bloody</hi> Notions and Practices; I ſay all this ſhews the <hi>Dr</hi>'s exceeding Ignorance of the true Principles of Chriſtianity; and the <hi>Brutality</hi> of theſe his <hi>Diſciples</hi> and <hi>Followers,</hi> who give this <hi>ſenſeleſs</hi> and <hi>malicious</hi> Account of the <hi>Gentile</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, on purpoſe to wound <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> under that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <p>And tho' they have no Account from the <hi>Heathens,</hi> how their <hi>Sacrifices</hi> began, yet theſe Gentlemen are very ſure, they were firſt introduced by <hi>Priest-Craft.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is the word! And every thing muſt be laid upon that. Tho' in this, they fall out among themſelves. And are not conſtant three pages together, to their own <hi>No-Hypotheſis.</hi> Thus, when they are angry with <hi>Kings</hi> (the malice to <hi>Them</hi> and to <hi>Prieſts</hi> commonly go together) then <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Sacrifices</hi> were the Invention of <hi>Kings;</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> came in but at ſecond hand, to keep it up, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it. This <hi>Blount</hi> (Sect. 2. p. 7.) endeavours to prove. <hi>The Primitive Inſtitution of Idolatry</hi> (ſays he) <hi>received its Birth from Princes: at whoſe Charge it was afterwards Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated by Eccleſiaſticks.</hi> Again Sect. 3. p. 8. <hi>Idolatry</hi> (and <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> which were the Worſhip Inſtituted to the Idol) <hi>being thus Instituted by the</hi> Civil Power, <hi>the</hi> Eccleſiaſtick <hi>was left to build upon that Foundation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Hiſtory of Religion</hi> p. 6. makes <hi>Prieſts</hi> to be the firſt Inventers; and that <hi>Kings,</hi> ſeeing the Veneration and Authority they obtain'd by it, became <hi>Prieſts</hi> themſelves; and joined that <hi>Title</hi> to the <hi>Imperial Dignity;</hi> thus <hi>Caſar</hi> and other Emperors of <hi>Rome</hi> were <hi>Prieſts;</hi> and among the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> their <hi>Kings</hi> were choſen from among the <hi>Prieſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus they preſerve to themſelves a double Handle (tho' by this, in true Reaſon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey loſe both) and make <hi>Religion</hi> to be <hi>Prieſt-Craft</hi> or <hi>State-Craft,</hi> as it ſerves their purpoſe. For theſe <hi>Latitudinarians</hi> in <hi>Religion</hi> are always the ſame in <hi>Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this <hi>History if Religion,</hi> being the lateſt Effort, brings the matter cloſer. <hi>Blount</hi> Ridicules <hi>Religion</hi> in the Perſon of the <hi>Heathen:</hi> This, in the ſame Form, expoſes it in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Whoſe Errors [they have given too much occaſion for it] he makes uſe of, not to <hi>Reform,</hi> but undermine <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> it ſelf: and makes all to be No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Prieſt-Craft.</hi> tho' he forgets not the <hi>Heathen</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel, and to ſpit his Venom at the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Inſtitution, when it comes in his way, to ſhew that he Grafts upon the ſame Stock.</p>
            <p>Page'<hi>s</hi> 8: Speaking of the Religious Inſtitutions before <hi>Christ,</hi> he calls them <hi>Strange and Puziling Methods of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ceremonies and Myſteries, and of various Rites of Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing, good for nothing but to confound and diſtract the Minds of Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then coming down to <hi>Christianity,</hi> he borrows the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian</hi> Arms againſt it: And ſo exactly in their very words, as points to us plainly, out of whoſe Quiver this Arrow came.</p>
            <p>He ſets up Irreconcilable War againſt all <hi>Myſtery;</hi> And making <hi>Tranſubstantiation</hi> his Mark, he levels directly at the <hi>Trinity, Incarnation, Divinity,</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and every thing that there is the leaſt pretence of <hi>Myſtery</hi> in.</p>
            <p>And yet theſe Gentlement endeavour all they can at <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery,</hi> while they wound <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> covertly as they think, through the ſides of the <hi>Heathens, Jews,</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks:</hi> But the <hi>Clov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n-Foot</hi> does plain appear: for their <hi>Wit</hi> is not ſo great as their <hi>Malice.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:53033:17"/>
            <p>They confeſs God to be <hi>Incomprehenſible,</hi> and his ways paſt finding out, yet they cry out upon <hi>Myſtery</hi> in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>There are <hi>Mysteries,</hi> Irreconſilable to them, in their own Natures, and in the Natures of every thing they ſee before them; yet they would have every thing in a <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural</hi> Religion Revealed from <hi>Heaven</hi> to be ſo plain, that their Reaſon ſhould be able to dive to the very bottom of it: which if it were, it would be no <hi>Revelation,</hi> or perfectly to no purpoſe: for what needed <hi>Revelation</hi> in things which are Plain and Obvious without it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phyſick</hi> is an <hi>Art,</hi> and a <hi>Myſtery</hi> to thoſe who know it not. Which leads only to the preſervation of <hi>Health;</hi> in thoſe <hi>Bodies</hi> whoſe Conſtitutions we know, and their Original, as much as of any thing that we ſee or touch.</p>
            <p>And yet we will let nothing be <hi>Myſterious</hi> (that is, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what every Man in the World perfectly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands, with all the Reaſons, and hidden Cauſes of it) in the ſaving of a <hi>Soul,</hi> whoſe <hi>Substance, Origination, Conſtitution, Operation,</hi> and every thing of it, but that we know it is, and feel it by its Effects, is altogether hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from us.</p>
            <p>Our coming into this World is totally a <hi>Myſtery.</hi> No Human Reaſon can attain unto it. And muſt there be no <hi>Myſtery</hi> at all in our <hi>Re-Generation,</hi> and being Born into the never-ending World of <hi>Spirits?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is not the other World, is not <hi>Heaven</hi> a <hi>Mystery</hi> to us? Do we underſtand it <hi>Perfectly?</hi> Can we Deſcribe it?</p>
            <p>And is it not <hi>Reaſonable,</hi> is it not <hi>Neceſſary</hi> that the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of fitting us for it, and of conveying us thither ſhould be very <hi>Myſterious</hi> to us?</p>
            <p>If we know not the End of out Journey, how do we pretend to underſtand every ſtep of the way?</p>
            <p>But let us hear this Author's <hi>Reaſon</hi> againſt <hi>Myſtery.</hi> You find it p. 60. and 61. in the very words of the <hi>Defence of the Hiſtory of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> and other <hi>Socinian</hi> Books lately Printed for the Inſtruction of this Age, <hi>viz.</hi> That no <hi>Revelation</hi> can be a <hi>Myſtery,</hi> more than a <hi>Secret</hi> when it is told, can be a <hi>Secret</hi> ſtill.</p>
            <p>But theſe ſtrong Reaſoners ſhould know, that a <hi>Myſtery</hi> is not that of which we know nothing at all. But that of which we know ſome part, but darkly and obſcurely, as in a Glaſs, which is the Compariſon the Apoſtle makes uſe of, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12.</p>
            <p>Thus it is we know <hi>Heaven.</hi> Yet it is <hi>Revealed.</hi> And thus we know the <hi>Trinity, Incarnation,</hi> and <hi>Divinity</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> If they had not been <hi>Revealed,</hi> we ſhould have known nothing of them: Yet we underſtand them not <hi>Perfectly,</hi> nor can give the Reaſon for every <hi>Modus</hi> of them, <hi>Why</hi> it is thus and thus, and the manner <hi>How.</hi> For that is not <hi>Revealed:</hi> Nor are our Underſtandings capable of Comprehending the whole Nature of God; for nothing but <hi>Infinit</hi> can Comprehend <hi>Infinit.</hi> And to attempt it, or go about it, and reject every thing we do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand in it, is not only Wicked and <hi>Prophane,</hi> but it argues the greateſt Weakneſs and Folly in any Man who is capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſuch a Thought, of any other Inſtance that is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be given.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſays to his <hi>Apoſtles, Joh.</hi> 16.12. He had many things to tell them, which they were not able to bear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If I have told you Earthly things,</hi> (ſays He to <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> that is, concerning the <hi>Re-generation</hi> by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in this life) <hi>and ye Believe not</hi> (that is, cannot Comprehend it, for the <hi>Difficulty</hi> and <hi>Myſteriouſneſs</hi> of it) <hi>How ſhall ye Believe, if I tell you of Heavenly things?</hi> Joh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.12. Will not theſe be much more <hi>Myſterious</hi> to you?</p>
            <p>This Author would have called him a <hi>Myſtery-Monger,</hi> as he does his Diſciples for Preaching what he Taught. p. 62.</p>
            <p>He laughs at any thing that is called <hi>Sublime</hi> in Religion, or above the reach of <hi>Servile Reaſon,</hi> as he thinks he Ral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, p. 43. And it is a <hi>Servile</hi> and <hi>Poor Reaſon</hi> indeed that can ſee nothing above it ſelf; that can find nothing <hi>Sublime</hi> in <hi>God,</hi> or His <hi>Religion;</hi> in thoſe Infinit Promiſes of an Eternal Heaven; and the wonderful Methods by which He has appointed to Conduct us thither, in ways ſuitable to His <hi>Juſtice,</hi> which is as much <hi>Himſelf,</hi> and as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſible in Him, as His <hi>Mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth of the matter is, Theſe ſort of Gentlemen do not love to <hi>Think.</hi> Their <hi>Wet</hi> is <hi>Frothy</hi> and <hi>Superficial;</hi> but will endure no Teſt. Therefore, to ſave themſelves further Trouble, they take up with a ſhort thought of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion;</hi> and reduce all to what they call <hi>Morality</hi> (tho' they agree not among themſelves what that is; and keep to it the leaſt of all Mankind) which being what every Man pleaſes to make of it, they are ſure that it ſhall not be uneaſie to them, for they keep the <hi>Diſpenſing Power</hi> in their own Hands</p>
            <p>Whereas <hi>Revealed</hi> Religion puts them under <hi>Diſcipline;</hi> and that managed by others; and ſets them out of all Hopes of future Happineſs, without Conforming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the <hi>Rules</hi> und <hi>Methods</hi> therein preſcrib'd.</p>
            <p>Therefore they Roar againſt this. And becauſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry <hi>Religion</hi> by Name is not ſo <hi>Popular</hi> (and their <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmuns Bonum</hi> being EASE, they never run any hazard for their Opinion) therefore they cry out againſt the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> which have the Adminiſtration of <hi>Religion,</hi> which is the ſame thing as to decry <hi>Religion</hi> it ſelf: Becauſe without <hi>Prieſts</hi> there can be no <hi>Religion.</hi> There may be a Belief of thoſe things which <hi>Religion</hi> teaches (that is, it is barely <hi>Poſſible;</hi> for without <hi>Teachers</hi> that would ſoon decay) but <hi>Religion</hi> is not only a <hi>Belief</hi> or a <hi>Perſuaſion,</hi> which is ſufficient in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to Intitle a Man to a <hi>Sect,</hi> to be an <hi>Epicurean,</hi> a <hi>Stoick,</hi> or other <hi>Sect</hi> of <hi>Phyloſiphers,</hi> to which no more is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired than to be of ſuch and ſuch an <hi>Opinion;</hi> but <hi>Chriſt</hi> has ſettled his <hi>Religion</hi> not only in a <hi>Sect of Believers;</hi> but He has Form'd thoſe <hi>Believers</hi> into a <hi>Society,</hi> or <hi>Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which is called His <hi>Church,</hi> to which He has anne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed great and unconceavable <hi>Priviledges</hi> and <hi>Promiſes;</hi> upon <hi>Conditions</hi> therein required; and under the <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Administration</hi> of the <hi>Officers</hi> the <hi>Biſhops</hi> whom He has appointed in that <hi>Society,</hi> with Power to Expel out of the <hi>Society,</hi> and admit into it, according to the Rules pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in their <hi>Charter:</hi> And which when they do, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuant to thoſe Rules, He has given his Infallible Promiſe to ratifie every ſuch Sentence of theirs in <hi>Heaven:</hi> But Men cannot be <hi>Excommunicated</hi> or hindered from an <hi>Opinion.</hi> Therefore <hi>Religion</hi> is ſomething more.</p>
            <p>From hence it follows, That inſtead of there being no <hi>Revealed</hi> Religion (as theſe <hi>Moraliſts</hi> would have it) there is nothing elſe <hi>Religion</hi> but that which is <hi>Revealed.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe my Believing according to the Light of my <hi>Nature,</hi> which we call <hi>Morality,</hi> does not Intitle me to any <hi>Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> beyond what I have by <hi>Nature,</hi> which every Man has as well as I; it does not diſtinguiſh me into any
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53033:17"/>diſtinct <hi>Society</hi> from other Men, put<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> me under no other <hi>Rules, Conditions,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And therefore theſe <hi>Moral-Men</hi> may be any thing, but a <hi>Church,</hi> which is a <hi>Society.</hi> And She is a <hi>Society</hi> founded upon ſuch a <hi>Belief,</hi> which is called Her <hi>Religion:</hi> But ſuch a <hi>Religion</hi> or <hi>Belief</hi> cannot be meerly <hi>Natural,</hi> otherwiſe all Men muſt have it, and conſequently <hi>all Men</hi> muſt be of that <hi>Society;</hi> which deſtroys its being a <hi>Society;</hi> becauſe a <hi>Society</hi> is a particular Company of Men, <hi>Excluſive</hi> of others, elſe it is no <hi>Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And every <hi>Society</hi> muſt be by <hi>Poſſitive Institution,</hi> by which the <hi>Officers</hi> and <hi>Rules</hi> of the <hi>Society</hi> are appointed.</p>
            <p>So that the <hi>Church</hi> being a <hi>Society,</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> being that <hi>Belief</hi> upon which the <hi>Society</hi> is Founded; the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is neceſſary that <hi>Religion</hi> can be nothing elſe but that which is <hi>Revealed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not ſpeak againſt <hi>Morality,</hi> or undervalue it. No, by no means. On the contrary, that can be no <hi>True</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which goes againſt <hi>Morality: Religion</hi> improves and heightens <hi>Morality.</hi> But <hi>Morality</hi> it ſelf could never carry us to <hi>Heaven,</hi> more than our own <hi>Natural</hi> ſtrength could lift us up to the <hi>Skies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, I do not take upon me to vindicate all <hi>Prieſts:</hi> No doubt there have been many wicked of them (never more than in this Age) and ſuch wicked <hi>Prieſts</hi> are no where more ſeverely Reprehended than in <hi>Scripture:</hi> But upon this handle, to turn all <hi>Religion</hi> into <hi>Prieſt-Craft,</hi> and to make that <hi>Craft</hi> to be all <hi>Imposture</hi> and <hi>Villany,</hi> is to place the ſame Character upon <hi>Christ</hi> Himſelf, for He was a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and is ſo at this day, and for ever. And indeed all theſe <hi>Myſtical</hi> Harangues are levell'd only at Him; for His is the only truly <hi>Reavealed</hi> Religion; and His <hi>Priests</hi> are the only <hi>Prieſts</hi> in the World; all others do but falſly bear that Name. And therefore to deny <hi>Prieſthood</hi> in the General, or ſet up this Common place of <hi>Prieſt-Craft,</hi> is down-right to deſtroy <hi>Christianity,</hi> and all <hi>Religion</hi> out of the World.</p>
            <p>I will not Retort upon theſe Men, that what they call <hi>Prieſt-Craft</hi> appears, by their own Arguments, to be more <hi>Lay-Craft,</hi> or <hi>State-Craft:</hi> Becauſe true Religion is neither: And it would ſerve theſe <hi>Anti-Chriſts</hi> to have it any <hi>Craft,</hi> whereby it might be thought a <hi>Cheat,</hi> and loſe its Force; and be no longer a Yoke (as they think it) upon them.</p>
            <p>The true Religion (of God's Inſtitution) has been cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by <hi>Kings,</hi> by <hi>Priests,</hi> by <hi>Lay-Men:</hi> and, if it were to any purpoſe to make the Compariſon, as much, or more by <hi>Lay-men,</hi> by <hi>Parliaments,</hi> than by the <hi>Prieſts</hi> themſelves.</p>
            <p>But it does not ſeem ſo direct a blow to <hi>Religion,</hi> as when all is made to be <hi>Prieſt-Craft:</hi> Becauſe, if that be believ'd, or but <hi>ſuſpected,</hi> the Regard to the Office of <hi>Priest-hood</hi> is taken away; and conſequently <hi>Religion</hi> muſt infallibly ſink with it, for the Reaſons above told.</p>
            <p>It was never known but that the Reſpect and Reverence to <hi>Prieſts</hi> and to <hi>Religion</hi> riſe and fell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. They are ſo inſeparably annexed, that the one cannot be without the other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wicked</hi> and <hi>Profligate Prieſts</hi> cannot be reſpected as the <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Pious</hi> are. But this is <hi>Perſonal,</hi> and touches not the <hi>Office.</hi> Where <hi>That</hi> is brought into <hi>Contempt, Religion</hi> muſt bear it Company. It was never otherwiſe, nor ever can be. And that is the whole Deſign of this Modiſh word <hi>Prieſt-Craft.</hi> Which tho' not Pardonable upon the <hi>Stage,</hi> I and others have heard it often from Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> where he <hi>Acted,</hi> in <hi>Lawn</hi> or <hi>Scotch Cleath</hi> Sleeves.</p>
            <p>I think of all Mankind ſuch ſort of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, who Betray, who Diſgrace <hi>Religion,</hi> are the moſt <hi>Vile</hi> and <hi>Contemptible,</hi> moſt <hi>Nauſeous</hi> and <hi>Loathſom:</hi> But, that is no more an Argument againſt <hi>Prieſt-hood</hi> than the <hi>Devils</hi> are againſt the <hi>Angelick-Order</hi> in <hi>Heaven.</hi> And there is as much pretence for Harangue againſt <hi>Angel-Craft.</hi> as againſt <hi>Priest-Craft.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Ancient Prophets while they inveigh'd ſo ſeverely againſt the <hi>Corrupt Priests</hi> of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and our <hi>Saviour</hi> againſt the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> yet preſerv'd the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence due to the <hi>Office</hi> Sacred and Inviolable. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.1.3, Chriſt Commands his <hi>Diſciples</hi> as well as the <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi> to pay entire Submiſſion to them. <hi>Heb,</hi> 5.5. <hi>No Man taketh</hi> (that is, ought to take) <hi>this Honour to himſelf, but he that is called of God, as was</hi> Aaron: 6. <hi>So alſo</hi> Chriſt <hi>Glorified not Himſelf to be made an</hi> High Prieſt, <hi>but He that ſaid unto Him—Thou art a Priest for ever after the Order of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lchiſedeck.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was it a <hi>Glorification</hi> even to <hi>Christ</hi> to be made a <hi>Prieſt</hi> And how it that <hi>moſt Sacred Office</hi> become (amongſt us) Contemptible!</p>
            <p>It is in Veneration to that <hi>High Character</hi> that I expoſe theſe Curſed <hi>Priests, Latitudinarians</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi> Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the Croſs of Chriſt, the Miniſters of <hi>Satan</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd into <hi>His</hi> Miniſters; as <hi>Satan</hi> himſelf into an <hi>Angel of Light:</hi> and then he is moſt a <hi>Devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a true ſaying, That the <hi>Corruption, of the best thing proves the worſt.</hi> A Corrupt <hi>Angel</hi> is a <hi>Devil;</hi> and a Corrupt <hi>Priest</hi> the next in wickedneſs to him. <hi>Falſe-Chriſts</hi> and <hi>Falſe-Prophets</hi> are much the greater Enemies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <hi>Christ</hi> that they come <hi>in His Name.</hi> As <hi>Falſe-Friends</hi> can do much more Miſchief than <hi>Open-Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vice</hi> is moſt dangerous when it is recommended under the Notion of <hi>Virtue.</hi> Barefac'd <hi>Wickedneſs, Atheiſm,</hi> and <hi>Infidelity</hi> create a Horror in any Mind not thorowly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunch'd, and hardened. Therefore we are Caution'd againſt the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of <hi>Iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that is it which now worketh in theſe Men who Diſpute againſt any <hi>Mystery</hi> in <hi>Religion;</hi> where it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and cannot be otherwiſe, unleſs we were able, clearly and fully to comprehend the whole Nature of God, in which there is ſomething which is and ever will be <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious,</hi> that is <hi>Dark</hi> and <hi>Hidden,</hi> not fully <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtood</hi> by all the <hi>Angels</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> to <hi>Eternity:</hi> And yet where there is no neceſſity in the World, ſo much as can be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, except that of <hi>Knavery,</hi> they write all <hi>Mystery,</hi> and work under ground that they may not be diſcover'd.</p>
            <p>They dwell all in <hi>Generals,</hi> in which as the Proverb ſays; <hi>Dolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>later,</hi> there is always <hi>Deceit</hi> at the bottom: They will not tell plainly what they would beat: But wound ſide-ways and by ſtealth, as theſe Authors whom we have Examin'd. And their admired <hi>Teacher</hi> Dr. <hi>Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotſon,</hi> in his ad Sermon <hi>concerning Family Religion,</hi> p. 61. gives ſpecial Caution not to have Children bred up in the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53033:18"/>JARGON <hi>of any Party:</hi> But will not tell what <hi>Party</hi> or what JARGON he means. You may apply it to all, to <hi>Christianity</hi> it ſelf (as it was intended) but ſo, that you ſhall not fix it upon him, he dwells in the <hi>Clouds,</hi> and <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious Politicks;</hi> more <hi>Subtile</hi> than any of which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> was ever Maſter: Whoſe <hi>Phyloſophy</hi> the <hi>History of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> takes pains (from p. 74. to 80.) to prove was brought into ſuch eſteemation by <hi>Prieſt-Craft,</hi> on purpoſe to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance <hi>Mystery.</hi> Great <hi>Wits</hi> make ſtrange Diſcoverys! It is the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s <hi>Foot in the Pot</hi> which ſinges the Milk.</p>
            <p>Among theſe <hi>Mysterious Arts</hi> of <hi>Prieſt-Craft,</hi> there is none moves this Author's Spleen ſo much as <hi>Creeds,</hi> and <hi>Rules of Faith.</hi> Againſt which he vents his Indignation. <hi>Hiſt. Rel.</hi> p. 64. <hi>In very deed</hi> (ſays he) <hi>Creeds were the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Revenges of Diſſenting Parties upon one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Creeds</hi> are ſtrange ſort of things! That a Man (whatever he believes) may not have Liberty <hi>openly</hi> to <hi>Profeſs</hi> and <hi>Preach</hi> what likes him beſt. But muſt go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Buſh and take pains to Blaſpheme! And that <hi>Atheists, Socinians,</hi> and <hi>Latitudinarians</hi> cannot get in to the Preforments of the Church without <hi>Swearing; Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing,</hi> or <hi>Declaring</hi> I know not how many <hi>Lyes:</hi> And all to no purpoſe! For that will never keep them out.</p>
            <p>He calls theſe <hi>Creeds</hi> p. 115. <hi>The Inſolent value of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions.</hi> Yet he values his own Opinion highly; and would have others to value it, above that of the Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the whole World, in all Ages, who have ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd a great value for <hi>Religion,</hi> and what he Blaſphemes, under the opprobrious <hi>New-made</hi> JARGON of <hi>Priest-Craft.</hi> He calls <hi>Their</hi> valuing, an <hi>Inſolent Value.</hi> This was to ſhew his <hi>Modeſty</hi> and <hi>Good Breeding.</hi> Inſolent for any to be <hi>Peſſitive</hi> but himſelf. He has <hi>Preſcription</hi> and would have the <hi>Monopoly,</hi> he may have the <hi>Reward</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>He ſhews great Reſpect to the <hi>Socinians,</hi> becauſe they retain nothing of <hi>Christianity</hi> but the <hi>Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, in the ſame page, he falls foul upon St. <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> his <hi>Creed,</hi> knowing that moſt offenſive to the <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians.</hi> And p. 85. He abuſes the <hi>Homo-ouſians,</hi> that is, the <hi>Christians,</hi> and the whole Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> which (he ſays) <hi>Shew'd a Spirit of Contention, rather than of Peace and Charity.</hi> This was for their <hi>Inſolent Value</hi> of their <hi>Faith,</hi> ſo as to Expreſs it in a <hi>Creed.</hi> And p. 116. He thinks to make great advantage to the <hi>Socinian</hi> Cauſe, by the difference 'twixt Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> and Dr. <hi>South,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Trinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this was only a difference in their <hi>Expoſition</hi> of what both acknowledg'd. The <hi>Holy and ever Bleſſed Trinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas I can tell you, Sir <hi>Poſſitive</hi> (and ask your <hi>Prieſt-Craft</hi> at <hi>Lambeth</hi> if it be not true) that the <hi>Socinians</hi> do differ, not only in their <hi>Expoſition</hi> of the Object of their Worſhip, but in the thing it ſelf: and that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly two Doctors, or ſo, but whole Parties and Nations of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Brief History of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> upon <hi>Act.</hi> 9.14.21. tells us, that the <hi>Polonian <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> were ſo Zealous for <hi>Divine Worſhip</hi> to be paid to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that they <hi>Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated,</hi> and <hi>Depos'd</hi> from their <hi>Miniſtry</hi> ſuch of their own Party as deny'd it. Which, I think, they generally do in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where likewiſe they are of moſt different <hi>Faiths;</hi> tho' they call themſelves <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> and own one another <hi>(in odium Tertij)</hi> as Chriſtian Brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Biddle</hi>'s <hi>Confeſſion of Faith touching the Holy Trinity,</hi> [Printed in the <hi>Devil</hi>'s <hi>Reformation</hi> of 43. and now Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed, with other Works of his, among Volumes of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian</hi> Treatiſes which are with great Induſtry, diſtributed <hi>Gratis</hi> ſince this Revolution] owns <hi>Three Perſons</hi> in the <hi>Holy Trinity:</hi> But make the <hi>Second</hi> and <hi>Third Perſons</hi> to be <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reſt of our <hi>Socinians</hi> (as thoſe that wrote <hi>The Brief Hiſtory of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> which is Printed in the ſame Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume with <hi>Biddle</hi>'s <hi>Confeſſion of Faith</hi> aboveſaid) do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a <hi>Trinity,</hi> that is, <hi>Three in Heaven,</hi> but the Second and the Third, <hi>i. e.</hi> The <hi>Word</hi> and the <hi>Spirit,</hi> they would have to be the very ſame with the Firſt, that is, the <hi>Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that theirs is the only <hi>Contradiction</hi> in the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> who would have <hi>Three</hi> to be <hi>Three,</hi> and yet all the <hi>Three</hi> to be really but <hi>One.</hi> It is they who are out in <hi>Counting</hi> or <hi>Reckoning,</hi> which the <hi>Hiſt. of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> calls <hi>Brutal</hi> in us.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and <hi>Biddelite-Socinians</hi> do confeſs <hi>Three</hi> in Heaven, whom they acknowledge to be <hi>Three</hi> diſtinct <hi>Perſons,</hi> this is fair and plain <hi>Reckoning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then the <hi>Biddelites</hi> are guilty of very groſs <hi>Idolatry,</hi> in joyning two <hi>Creatures</hi> into the ſame <hi>Holy Trinity</hi> with <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other Hand, how is it, that theſe <hi>Biddelites,</hi> and the other <hi>Socinians</hi> do own one another to be of the ſame <hi>Faith?</hi> and Print their Books together, as ſetting forth the ſame Doctrine?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Trinity</hi> of the one is <hi>Three,</hi> who are <hi>One Perſon</hi> (a moſt palpable Contradiction, which no Diſtinction can ſolve) the <hi>Trinity</hi> of the other is <hi>God</hi> and two <hi>Creatures</hi> (which is rank <hi>Idolatry</hi>) One Party of them ſay, That the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> are <hi>Perſons,</hi> the other ſay, <hi>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</hi> One, that they are <hi>God,</hi> the other that they are not <hi>God;</hi> one, that they are <hi>Adorable,</hi> the other ſay, <hi>No.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here are differences, not only concerning the <hi>Explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of their <hi>Faith</hi> (as that Objected 'tiwxt Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> and Dr. <hi>South;</hi> and may happen to any of the ſame Faith; as different Expoſitions of a Text in <hi>Scripture,</hi> does not infer, in either, a disbelief of the <hi>Scripture;</hi> and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Explanations of the Nature of <hi>God,</hi> which often happens among <hi>Divines,</hi> does not conclude any of them to be <hi>Atheiſts</hi>) but this difference among the ſeveral <hi>Sects</hi> of <hi>Socinians,</hi> is concerning the very Object of their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> thoſe whom one Part of them make to be <hi>God,</hi> the reſt of them ſay are but <hi>Creatures.</hi> Then which it is impoſſible to imagine a <hi>Greater</hi> or more <hi>Fundamental</hi> difference. Yet theſe are the Men who cry out upon <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery!</hi> Whoſe <hi>Faith</hi> is flatly contradictory to it ſelf, as theſe <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> ſtand <hi>Divided</hi> from one another: And if you take the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> of any of their <hi>Sub-Diviſions</hi> by it ſelf, it is nothing but <hi>Myſtery:</hi> If by <hi>Myſtery</hi> you mean an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intelligible</hi> thing.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Three</hi> in one <hi>Nature</hi> (which is the <hi>Christian-Trinity</hi>) is not fully Explicable to us; (tho' there is ſomething ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry like it even in <hi>Human-Nature,</hi> which contains in it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Perſons</hi>) yet <hi>Three</hi> in <hi>One Perſon</hi> (which is the <hi>Socinian-Trinity</hi>) muſt be flat <hi>Contradiction,</hi> and has no <hi>Parallel</hi> or <hi>Image</hi> in any Created Nature.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:53033:18"/>
            <p>And Two <hi>Creatures</hi> to make up One <hi>Holy Trinity</hi> with God (which is another <hi>Socinian-Trinity</hi>) tho' not ſo <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory,</hi> is yet more <hi>Blaſphemous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Great is the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of <hi>Godlineſs. God</hi> dwells in Light <hi>Inacceſſible,</hi> in thick Clouds and Darkneſs (cauſed by Light too ſtrong for our weak Senſes) becauſe of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſibility</hi> of his Nature, ſo far exalted above all <hi>Created-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Devil</hi> and his <hi>Socinian-Latitudinarian</hi> Miniſters, wrap up the <hi>Mystery</hi> of their Iniquity in Darkneſs, leſt it ſhould be Detected: Whoſe Form would be ſo <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous</hi> if ſeen in its own Native Colours, as would deter all, but invite none, to enter into the Black and Diſmal Regions of Error.</p>
            <p>But theſe <hi>Libertines</hi> would fain perſuade themſelves and others, that there is no Condemnation for <hi>Error.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho' our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſays, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. Thoſe who <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> not, upon the <hi>Preaching</hi> (the <hi>Sufficient Publication</hi>) of His Goſpel, ſhall be <hi>Damned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what is their Reaſon why they ſhould not account for <hi>Error.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Poſſitive</hi> tells, p. 96. Becauſe <hi>Error</hi> proceeds from our <hi>Innocence,</hi> that is (ſays he) our <hi>Weakneſs</hi> and <hi>Ignorance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are they who accuſe the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and laugh at them for making <hi>Ignorance</hi> the <hi>Mother of their Devotion!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when <hi>Ignorance</hi> is ſet up to Countenance <hi>Infidelity</hi> and <hi>Irreligion,</hi> then it is all <hi>Innocence!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They decry all <hi>Myſtery</hi> as being a Subterfuge for <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance:</hi> And plead their <hi>Ignorance</hi> as an excuſe for not Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in <hi>Myſteries!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But is all <hi>Ignorance, Innocence?</hi> Why then do theſe Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable Pretenders to <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> ſeek to Rob us of our <hi>Innocence?</hi> Why do they ſay ſuch ſevere and bloody things againſt the <hi>Papists,</hi> the <hi>Jews,</hi> or the <hi>Heathens</hi> for their <hi>Ignorance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if there be an <hi>Affected</hi> and <hi>Wilful Ignorance;</hi> an <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance</hi> that proceed; from our <hi>Negligence,</hi> from our <hi>Vice;</hi> If we ſpend that time in <hi>Debauchery</hi> or <hi>Idleneſs,</hi> which, if well Imploy'd, would have improv'd our Underſtandings; If our <hi>Ignorance</hi> proceeds from ſuch Cauſes as theſe, and therefore will be rather an <hi>Aggravation</hi> than an <hi>Excuſe</hi> to us; then can none truſt to their <hi>Ignorance,</hi> who have not been all their life-time, perfectly <hi>Innocent;</hi> and who have not improv'd every minute to the beſt advantage of inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings.</hi> Which ſince no Man in the World can pretend to) and that there is no Remedy for miſ-ſpent time, but to Employ the remainder more diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Ignorance</hi> will be an excuſe for very few of our <hi>Faults:</hi> And it will be very hard to determine which theſe are.</p>
            <p>But it is much eaſier to gueſs what they are not. Not Sins of <hi>Affectation</hi> and <hi>Pride,</hi> for a true ſenſe of our <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> would make us <hi>Humble</hi> and <hi>Modeſt:</hi> Therefore nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Poſſitives</hi> nor <hi>Poſlings</hi> will have any ſhare in this Excuſe.</p>
            <p>Nor Sins of <hi>Ingratitude.</hi> Becauſe <hi>Forgetfulneſs,</hi> in that Caſe, is the <hi>Sin.</hi> Elſe <hi>Poſling's</hi> turning his Father out of Door, proceeded from his <hi>Innocence,</hi> that is, his <hi>Ignorance.</hi> However it may ſerve as a <hi>Feſcue</hi> to Sir <hi>Poſſitive;</hi> he having, not long before aſſiſted in the ſame ſin againſt a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, who never injur'd him; and who had done more for him than all the Friends and Relations he had in the World.</p>
            <p>Nor, Laſtly, in Sins of <hi>Intriegue</hi> and <hi>Deſign;</hi> to <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent</hi> and <hi>Deceive</hi> when we cannot <hi>Perſuade</hi> by plain Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which is the drift of theſe Books, and of all the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. For <hi>Ignorance</hi> cannot be pretended in that Caſe, more than of direct <hi>Lying;</hi> in which their Ability are much ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd and have been made uſe of.</p>
            <p>And I believe the ſenſe of what they deſerve for this, is that which chiefly moves them ſo Zealouſly againſt what they call <hi>Perſecution,</hi> hopeing to include within that Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation, the <hi>Just Puniſhments</hi> for their <hi>Crimes:</hi> for if all <hi>Errors</hi> are <hi>Innocence,</hi> it would be very hard to <hi>Puniſh</hi> them. <hi>Blaſphemy, Idolatry,</hi> and <hi>Treaſon</hi> too may eſcape at this rate, for they are but <hi>Errors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this Author's Proofs againſt <hi>Perſecution,</hi> p. 94. are theſe.
<list>
                  <item>1. That <hi>Force</hi> does not <hi>Convince.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. That the Preſcriptions of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> are all <hi>Gentle</hi> and <hi>Meek,</hi> not <hi>Force</hi> and <hi>Arms:</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I confine my Anſwer to the Point of <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> and ſeeking to turn Men away from the Worſhip of <hi>God.</hi> For theſe are the <hi>Errors</hi> of which we now Diſpute. I am far from thinking every Error <hi>Criminal,</hi> much leſs <hi>Capital.</hi> And am as much in my Opinion as any body for that Gentle and Perſuaſive Methods as to Errors which proceed meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from <hi>Weakneſs,</hi> and have no <hi>Malice</hi> in them.</p>
            <p>But in the preſent Caſe of <hi>Blaſpheming,</hi> and which is worſe, <hi>Ridiculing</hi> of God and of <hi>Religion;</hi> God Himelf has Pronounc'd it to be <hi>Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor would thoſe <hi>Sons of Belial</hi> have eſcap'd it, if they had liv'd in any <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Country.</p>
            <p>Shall the Honour of the <hi>King</hi> be Guarded with <hi>Death;</hi> and <hi>God</hi> be Blaſphem'd <hi>Impune</hi> in Print, and in the ſtreets!</p>
            <p>Has not this Propagated <hi>Atheiſm</hi> to the Degree we now ſee it! Not only to paſs unpuniſhed, but to be thought a <hi>Grace</hi> in Converſation, and the mark of a <hi>Wit!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shall not God viſit for theſe things! Will not his Soul be avenged on ſuch, a Nation as this!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the two foreſaid frivolous Objections; for the firſt, That <hi>Force</hi> does not <hi>Convince.</hi> Anſw. <hi>Puniſhments</hi> are inflicted for other ends than <hi>Converting</hi> the <hi>Criminal,</hi> tho' they often too work that effect, where they meet with Minds not thorowly hardened. They are intended to vindicate the Honour of the Government, chiefly of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Governor</hi> of Heaven and Earth. In the next place to prevent the Infection of others, and to deter them from the like.</p>
            <p>As to the ad Obj. That the Preſcriptions of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> are all <hi>Gentle</hi> and <hi>Meek.</hi> Anſw. That is as to the <hi>Preachers.</hi> Who might not make uſe of <hi>Force,</hi> nor Uſurp the <hi>Sword,</hi> which God had committed to the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate,</hi> who <hi>Beareth it not in vain, but is a Revenger to execute Wrath upon them that do Evil.</hi> Rom. 13.4. And that <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> is not one of the <hi>Evils</hi> which is within his Commiſſion to Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, I believe will not be found in all the <hi>Goſpel. Chriſt</hi> urg'd no ſuch thing when He Himſelf was Condemn'd for alledg'd <hi>Blaſphmy.</hi> But on the contrary He Confirm'd the <hi>Magiſtate's</hi> Power, in that very Caſe; and own'd that it was <hi>given Him from Heaven.</hi> John 19.11.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:53033:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> Commands, if a Man ſmite us on one Cheek, to turn the other. If a Man take our Coat, let him have our Cloak alſo, and not to <hi>avenge</hi> an injury done to us. Will any Man ſay that theſe are Rules for <hi>Judges</hi> to go by, in diſtributing Juſtice 'twixt Man and Man?</p>
            <p>There is no better pretence, from the Injunctions of <hi>Meekneſs</hi> and <hi>Forgiving</hi> of Injuries, to conclude againſt the Power of the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> in caſe of <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> or to call this a <hi>Perſecution</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But they are in no fear of the Laws at preſent. They cry before they are hurt. But they think, by this Argument, to raiſe an <hi>Odium</hi> againſt <hi>Kings</hi> as well as <hi>Priests;</hi> and to Curtall the Power of both: for they are equal Enemies to both. There are none of theſe <hi>Latitudinarians</hi> that are not <hi>Commonwealth-Men:</hi> They are againſt <hi>Monarchy</hi> in <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> or on <hi>Earth:</hi> and indeed againſt all <hi>Government,</hi> if they could tell how: that is, all that is not in their own Hands. They cannot bear to be under the Diſcipline of any other. This is the true ground of their Quarrel at <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi> It is not the <hi>Mystery</hi> of it, that they would not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble their Head with: nor ſpend their Breath to undeceive thoſe Fools (as they call them) who believe it: they would not concern themſelves at <hi>Prieſt-Craft,</hi> or care if <hi>Prieſts</hi> wore Fools-Caps, ſo they were not under their Correction. It is the <hi>Law</hi> not the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> which is Grievous to them. They would break his <hi>Bonds</hi> aſunder, and caſt away his <hi>Cords</hi> from them. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2, 3. And they will flie in the Face of the <hi>Civil Government</hi> if it tie theſe faſter upon them, or reſtrain their <hi>Libertiniſm</hi> in this, or in any other Inſtance. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> enforces and ſtrengthens <hi>Government;</hi> and <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> Protects and Encourages <hi>Religion:</hi> therefore both are equally Obnoxious to theſe <hi>Filthy Dreamers,</hi> who <hi>Defile the Fleſh,</hi> Deſpiſe <hi>Dominion,</hi> and ſpeak Evil of <hi>Dignities,</hi> of thoſe things <hi>which they know not,</hi> Jude 8. <hi>But what they know</hi> naturally, <hi>as Brute Beaſts, in thoſe things they corrupt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi> 10. <hi>Woe unto them, for they have gone in the way of</hi> Cain, 11. <hi>and ran greedily after the</hi> Error <hi>of</hi> Balaam, <hi>for Reward, and periſhed in the gainſaying of</hi> Core: 12. <hi>Clouds they are without Water, carried about of Winds; Trees whoſe Fruit withereth, without Fruit, twice dead, plucked up by the Roots;</hi> 13. <hi>Raging waves of the Sea, foaming out their own ſhame, wandering Stars, to whom is reſerved the Blackneſs of Darkneſs for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is not this a lively Deſcription of theſe Men? And are theſe Men to be <hi>Tolerated</hi> in any Government? Will God Bleſs that <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Government?</hi> Is it a <hi>Chriſtian Lenity</hi> to Indulge this ſort of Men? God Commends the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Epheſus</hi> Rev. 2.6. becauſe they hated the Deeds of the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colaitans</hi> (who gave way to the ſins of the Fleſh, tho' un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of <hi>Religion</hi>) <hi>which I alſo hate,</hi> ſays God. And he threatens to fight againſt the Church of <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rgam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had amongſt them thoſe that taught that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. 15. And who held the Doctrine of <hi>Balaam</hi> to caſt a <hi>Stumbling-Block</hi> 14. before the People (and are not theſe <hi>Stumbling-blocks</hi> which I have mentioned out of theſe Mens Works?) The Church of <hi>Thyatira</hi> 20. was condemn'd for <hi>ſuffering</hi> that wicked Woman <hi>Jezebel</hi> to ſeduce the Servants of <hi>Christ:</hi> Who will <hi>ſpue thoſe out of his Mouth,</hi> Chap. 3.16. who have no more Zeal for his <hi>Religion,</hi> who are neither <hi>Hot</hi> nor <hi>Cold,</hi> who have a <hi>Latitudinarian</hi> Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency. Let every Man go his own way.—</p>
            <p>I would thou were either <hi>Cold</hi> or <hi>Hot</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 15. being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly <hi>Cold.</hi> That is, having no Religion at all, is prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to this <hi>Luke-warm Loadicean</hi> temper, to profeſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Religion</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and be ſo careleſs and unconcern'd what becomes of it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were Blam'd and ſeverely Puniſhed by God, for <hi>permitting</hi> of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> which could not be, if it did not belong to their Office to <hi>Reſtrain</hi> it.</p>
            <p>And thoſe <hi>Kings</hi> muſt be very weak indeed who will be gain'd by the ſometimes ſervile ſoothings of theſe <hi>Prieſt-Craft-Men,</hi> and not ſee that all they Belch out againſt the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> is equally levell'd againſt <hi>them.</hi> They cannot keep it (always) Conceal'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lount</hi> beſtows his loving Glances upon them. <hi>Sect.</hi> 16. p. 41. where he repreſents them under the Figures of <hi>Beaſts</hi> of <hi>Rapine, Lions, Dragons,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But for petty Princes</hi> (ſays he) <hi>a Fox may be the better Emblem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And theſe Men who cry out of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> at the ſame time, endeavour to raiſe all Mankind againſt thoſe whom they <hi>Hate</hi> or <hi>Fear.</hi> They would ſtir up <hi>Perſecution</hi> againſt thoſe whom they call <hi>Perſecutors.</hi> That is to ſay, <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> is only Evil when it touches them.</p>
            <p>And of all Mankind none were more violent <hi>Perſecutors</hi> than the <hi>Arians</hi> (that is, the <hi>Socinians</hi>) when they had the Power: who now ſpeak againſt <hi>Perſecution,</hi> becauſe they have not the Inflicting of it: yet go in it, as far as their Power reaches, that is, their <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Malice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But tho' the Sword of Juſtice be (at preſent) otherwiſe employ'd than to Animadvert upon theſe <hi>Blaſphemers;</hi> is the Cauſe of <hi>God,</hi> is the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> (not to name the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi>) Religion ſo ſunk, that none muſt oppoſe, and that boldly and openly, ſuch loud Contempt of all that is <hi>Sacred!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when the <hi>Chief</hi> and <hi>Father</hi> of them is advanc'd to the <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> and thence infuſes his deadly Poiſon through the Nation; Preaches it Publickly at <hi>White-Hall;</hi> and gets it Printed by <hi>Their Majesties Special Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</hi> to give it greater Countenance and Authority; and another Collegue of his at <hi>Salisbury:</hi> Recommends the ſame in Print, to be Preach'd and Taught through the <hi>Dioceſs</hi> which <hi>(Indignatione Divinâ)</hi> is committed to his Charge, and all the other <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Clergy</hi> of their Communion let it paſs, with at leaſt <hi>Silent Conſent:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the <hi>Braves</hi> of this (at beſt) <hi>Theiſtical Junct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Place Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi>'s Name (not only in his private Capacity, but as <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Canterbury</hi>) in the <hi>Front</hi> of their <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-Chriſtian Haranguea</hi> in Print; and he ſhews no Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in it. And (to Recapitulate a little of what is ſaid before.)</p>
            <p>He himſelf has exceeded them in the Barbarous Account he has given of the <hi>Riſe</hi> and <hi>Foundation</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion. They make <hi>Religion</hi> to be the Invention of <hi>Wicked Men,</hi> or of <hi>Devils;</hi> and he improves it, making the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion only a <hi>Compliance</hi> with that <hi>Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> As before is ſufficiently ſhewn.</p>
            <p>When he dares ſo openly and bare-fac'd Attack all <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial'd</hi> Religion as to make: it good for nothing but to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve outward. Peace in this World. As he does in his Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on upon <hi>Luke</hi> 9.55. which is quoted with Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence in the Preface to this <hi>Hiſtory of Religion.</hi> But this <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> himſelf, had the Modeſty or Cunning to leave
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53033:19"/>out thoſe broad words of the Doctors, which I have ſhewn above, <hi>viz.</hi> That it were better there had never been any <hi>Revealed</hi> Religion; that is, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> had never come, than to make uneaſineſs in the World, and diſturb Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for it. And tho', as I have ſhewn above, The <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion</hi> is the greateſt Security to Government, and the outward Peace of this world; yet that Notion could never have come into the Head of a <hi>Christian,</hi> that we had better never have had any <hi>Chriſt,</hi> than that any Worldly Government ſhould be diſturb'd.</p>
            <p>Nay, farther, when, as I have ſhewn above, this Dr. makes a Mother Suckling her own Child, to be of a more <hi>Neceſſary</hi> and <hi>Indiſpenſible</hi> Obligation than to believe in Chriſt, that is, <hi>than any poſſitive Precept of Revealed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> (which are his words) for the Belief of Chriſt is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a <hi>Poſſitive</hi> Precept of <hi>Revealed</hi> Religion.</p>
            <p>When <hi>He</hi> Diſputes openly againſt the <hi>Satisfaction</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and makes all our Thirty Nine Articles, or the Belief of any particular Church, but the <hi>Jargon</hi> of a <hi>Party,</hi> and Commands all the Children of the Nation to be bred up looſe from any ſuch <hi>Narrow</hi> Principles.</p>
            <p>When <hi>He</hi> makes not only the <hi>Eternity</hi> but the <hi>Being</hi> of a <hi>Hell</hi> wholly Precarious.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, when (as I have ſhewn from Dr. <hi>Burn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens'd by Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi>) That <hi>Chriſt</hi> is made to be no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>God</hi> than the <hi>Cloud of Glory</hi> in the <hi>Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When ſuch Wickedneſs is ſet up in our <hi>High Places,</hi> ſhall we not give warning!</p>
            <p>Firſt, to the <hi>Clergy</hi> in theſe Mens Communion, quickly and ſpeedily to ſeparate from them.</p>
            <p>I meddle not <hi>(Here)</hi> with the point of <hi>Schiſm.</hi> (That ſtands a Diſpute by it ſelf) but as the 15th Canon of the Synod of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> which was omitted in Mr <hi>Hody</hi>'s Edition of the <hi>Baroccian MS.</hi> expreſly ordians, That if any <hi>Biſhop</hi> (though a lawful <hi>Biſhop</hi>) do hold <hi>Heretical Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,</hi> and ſhall PUBLICKLY <hi>Teach</hi> and <hi>Preach</hi> the ſame <hi>bare-fac'd in the Church,</hi> all, even the meaneſt <hi>Laick</hi> is Obliged to <hi>Separate</hi> from ſuch wicked Teacher, even <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Synodical Condemnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whether the Opinions before told are not, in the groſſeſt manner, <hi>Heretical:</hi> And whether <hi>Preaching</hi> them at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> and <hi>Printing</hi> them, be not a <hi>publick</hi> Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and Preaching the ſame, is left to the Judgment of the Reader.</p>
            <p>And then what an Indiſpenſible Obligation muſt lie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the <hi>Clergy</hi> (eſpecially) in their Communion to Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from them! and, as publickly and openly as they have done, to Diſclaim, Renounce, and Confute their Damnable Hereſiel, Otherwiſe the Blood of all thoſe Souls who ſhall be infected by them, and of all their <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities,</hi> whom they ſhall likewiſe infect, will be required of every ſingle <hi>Clergy-Man,</hi> who but by his <hi>Silence</hi> and <hi>continuing</hi> in their <hi>Communion,</hi> ſhall, ſo far, giue Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to their <hi>Errors. Silence</hi> can never be an excuſe in a <hi>Watch-Man,</hi> whoſe Office it is to <hi>cry aloud:</hi> And if he <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>low</hi> not the <hi>Trumpet,</hi> he cannot deliver his <hi>Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And tho' immediate <hi>Death</hi> attended it, this he ought to do. But there is not that Hazard. The <hi>Government</hi> is not concern'd in this. It is the Common Cauſe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity: And I ſee no Reaſon but to expect that every ſuch <hi>Clergy-Man</hi> would be eſteemed and valued, even by <hi>this Government,</hi> which would (beſides) think it ſome ſort of a <hi>Vindication</hi> of the <hi>Government,</hi> from what ſhare it may be ſuppoſed they have in the Abetting or Encouragement of ſuch <hi>Heterodox</hi> Principles <hi>Preach'd</hi> before them, by thoſe in ſuch High Place with them, and ſaid to be <hi>Printed</hi> by <hi>Their Special Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the <hi>People,</hi> ſuch <hi>Clergy</hi> would certainly be great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly regarded by them; as Men of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>Zeal</hi> for their <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if the <hi>Clergy</hi> (which God forbid) ſhould prove ſo <hi>Laodicean</hi> as not to think this worth their while, and ſo leave the Imputation to fall upon their whole <hi>Communion:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then I muſt Admoniſh all the Godly <hi>Laity,</hi> that they are obliged, in their Station, as much as the <hi>Clergy</hi> in theirs, to Separate from ſuch wicked <hi>Teachers:</hi> and that by the above quoted Council of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> they are not to be Reputed <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> for ſo doing, but a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Preſervers of the Unity of the <hi>Church,</hi> whoſe Unity conſiſts chiefly in the Unity of their <hi>Doctrine.</hi> But they have a greater Authority than that of any <hi>Council.</hi> Gal. 1.8. <hi>Tho' we</hi> (ſays one of the Apoſtles) <hi>or an Angel from Heaven Preach any other Goſpel unto you, than that which we have preached un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, let him be Accurſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as all the <hi>Laity</hi> are hereby oblig'd, under the penalty of, <hi>Sin,</hi> to Separate from the <hi>Church-Communion</hi> of theſe <hi>Heretical Biſhops,</hi> and of all who <hi>Communicate</hi> with them: ſo is it likewiſe required of them to abſtain, as much as is poſſible, even from their private Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>with ſuch a one,</hi> ſays St. Paul, <hi>not ſo much as to eat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let them think that theſe are <hi>Trying Times,</hi> ſent on purpoſe to diſtinguiſh God's <hi>Elect</hi> from the <hi>Reprobate,</hi> to Separate His <hi>Little Flock</hi> from the World of <hi>Iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For there muſt be alſo</hi> Hereſies <hi>among you, that they which are approved, way the made manifest among you.</hi> 1 Cor. 11.19.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
